<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The kingdom of Jesus Christ entering its succession at 1697, according to a calendar of time drawn by the four monarchies, and by the time, times, half time allowed to the papacy, and the ten kingdoms, as the last state of the Roman, or fourth monarchy then ending : given in Daniel, and expounded by the Revelation in content with all history, and carrying on the scripture line of time / by T. Beverley ...</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 254 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38705</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17894005</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17894005</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106747</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27613)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106747)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1116:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The kingdom of Jesus Christ entering its succession at 1697, according to a calendar of time drawn by the four monarchies, and by the time, times, half time allowed to the papacy, and the ten kingdoms, as the last state of the Roman, or fourth monarchy then ending : given in Daniel, and expounded by the Revelation in content with all history, and carrying on the scripture line of time / by T. Beverley ...</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 66, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A scripture line of time.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Prophecies --  Chronology.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Daniel II, 7.</term>
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:1"/>
            <p> THE KINGDOM OF JESUS CHRIST Entering its Succeſſion at 1697.</p>
            <p>According to a Calendar of Time.</p>
            <p>Drawn by the Four Monarchies, and by the Time, Times, Half Time allowed to the Papacy, and the Ten King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; as the laſt ſtate of the Roman, or Fourth Monarchy then Ending;</p>
            <p>Given in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and Expounded by the <hi>Revelation</hi> in Conſent with All Hiſtory; and carrying on the Scripture Line of Time.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. Beverley,</hi> a moſt Humble Miniſter in the Word of God and the Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1689.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt Excellent MAJESTY OF WILLIAM and MARY: By Eſpecial Grace of God According to Propheſie, KING and QUEEN of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Truly Defenders of the Faith. AND To the <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> At this Time Aſſembled. Grace and Peace from Him, which is, which<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. 4, 5.</note> was, and which is to Come: And from the ſeven Spirits, which are before his Throne; and from Jeſus Chriſt the Faithful Witneſs, the firſt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the Dead; and the Prince of the Kings of the Earth.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Dread Soveraigns. Moſt Reverend and Noble Lords. Moſt Worthy Senators and Patriots.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Great God of Heaven</hi> having made known of old, even to <hi>Pagan Princes,</hi> by his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> the <hi>Prophets,</hi> what ſhould <hi>come to paſs hereafter,</hi> concerning the <hi>Kingdom of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:106747:3"/> 
               <hi>his Son,</hi> and the <hi>cleanſing of his Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> his truly <hi>Catholic Church;</hi> He hath<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. 14.</note> enabled me, the moſt unworthy of all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, the <hi>leaſt of Saints,</hi> and the <hi>chiefeſt of Sinners,</hi> for the laſt five years to <hi>ſearch,</hi> and to <hi>underſtand</hi> by <hi>Books</hi> the <hi>number of years,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 2.</note> He would accompliſh in the <hi>Patience</hi> or <hi>Delay of the Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and in the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations of his Sanctuary;</hi> I having then <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge,</hi> that the. <hi>Accompliſhment</hi> of thoſe <hi>years</hi> is, as near, as 1697, Have believ'd it my Duty, in Fear of God, who hath <hi>committed the Diſpenſation to me;</hi> as alſo in <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and <hi>Fidelity</hi> to the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Government</hi> of theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> to make publication of the Time; and alſo to explain All thoſe Symbols, wherein the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Propheſie</hi> hath been, though more hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, yet as certainly, when juſtly concerted, conveyed, as by plaineſt words; and to make <hi>Dedication</hi> of it to the Soveraign Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Nation, with a loweſt Obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, as the meaneſt of Subjects; and yet with the Aſſurance, ariſing from the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Sacred Truth; that ſo the <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:106747:3"/> might be known in the Grand <hi>Pretori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or <hi>Pallace</hi> of the Nation, and thereby in <hi>all other Places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The View preſented is worthy the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeſt Conſideration of the Greateſt Princes, Statiſts, and Divines; Four <hi>Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies,</hi> which have one after another, borne ſuch ſway in the World; and whoſe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs caus'd their Terror in the Land of the Living,</hi> for near <hi>Daniels Twenty</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>17. &amp;c. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Three Hundred Evenings, and Mornings, prophetically</hi> multiplyed into <hi>years;</hi> but moſt of Them being <hi>gone down into the Pit,</hi> have <hi>laid their Swords under their Heads,</hi> with their <hi>Iniquities on their Bones;</hi> and to Riſe with them, if Enemies to the <hi>Kingdom of God;</hi> and herewith, the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian State</hi> for above theſe laſt <hi>twelve hundred years,</hi> with the <hi>Monarchs</hi> of the <hi>Ancient Imperial Roman Territories,</hi> who have for moſt of the ſpace given their <hi>Power</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. 17.</note> 
               <hi>to the Beaſt;</hi> But ſome have already, The Reſt ſhall Renunciate to that <hi>Adulterous Church;</hi> and though ſome of them now with a High
<pb facs="tcp:106747:4"/> Hand <hi>cauſe their Terror in the Land of the Living,</hi> yet They ſhall without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance <hi>beare their Shame alſo in going down to the ſides of the Pit;</hi> But how much more does that indeed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Kingdom of Chriſt at the end of theſe <hi>Four</hi> deſerve Thought, that ſhall receive Theſe, and many more Kingdoms into its Boſom, and it ſelf <hi>never End,</hi> and that within ſo few years.</p>
            <p>It is therefore Princely Wiſdom, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs to <hi>ſearch,</hi> and to command, that<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 11.</note> 
               <hi>ſearch</hi> be made into the <hi>Scriptures of the New and Old Teſtament,</hi> whether <hi>Theſe Things be ſo or no;</hi> Not that <hi>Divine Oracles</hi> can be over-rul'd by a <hi>Counſel of Angels, or Men;</hi> but that by the <hi>Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>Holy Records</hi> the <hi>certainty of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 22. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Words of Truth</hi> may be <hi>Receiv'd;</hi> For the more They are examin'd, the more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent their Truth will be; And least, (the Things being indeed ſo) ſo <hi>Grand a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Aſſembly</hi> ſhould under-value Them, and Know with Diſadvantage hereafter; ſo <hi>Great a Propheſie</hi> hath been among Them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 2. 5.</note> and They Rejected it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:4"/>
            <p> And <hi>why ſhould it be thought incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> that the <hi>God of Heaven,</hi> the <hi>Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Secrets</hi> ſhould ſo near the Time make Known, as He hath always done, by whom He pleaſes, the <hi>Great Things, that are to come to paſs</hi> ſo ſhortly.</p>
            <p>God hath honour'd this <hi>Nation,</hi> with a moſt ſtupendious mirror of Providence, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Expiration of the Papacy</hi> ſo nigh at Hand; why may He not be pleas'd to Honour it alſo with ſuch <hi>a Glaſs of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie,</hi> that by the <hi>Underſtanding</hi> of the <hi>Times, our Iſrael may know what it</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 32.</note> 
               <hi>ought to do,</hi> and <hi>All</hi> the <hi>People</hi> be most devotely <hi>at their Command,</hi> both as to <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs Eccleſiaſtical, Civil, Military!</hi> for the ſteerage of All which the Conſideration of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> ſo near would be as the <hi>Pole-ſtar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For that an <hi>Account</hi> of All may be <hi>Render'd</hi> with <hi>Comfort to that Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Kingdom</hi> ſo nigh Approaching, what <hi>Purity in our Religion, Holineſs, Juſtice, Mercy, Amendment of Life, Reformation</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:106747:5"/> 
               <hi>of Manners, Contempt of the World, Magnanimity, Moderation of Church-Power, Brotherly Love</hi> is neceſſary; even in preparation to ſo Glorious a <hi>Revolution?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor</hi> give his <hi>Urim,</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> to the <hi>Evangelical Miniſtry</hi> of the <hi>Nation; a Divine Sentence into the Kings Lips</hi> that <hi>His Mouth</hi> in this <hi>Matter</hi> may not <hi>Tranſgreſs in Judgment; a Spirit of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to them who <hi>ſit in Counſel;</hi> and an <hi>Ear to his Churches,</hi> to Hear, what the <hi>Spirit ſayeth to them;</hi> that ſo a People in theſe <hi>Nations may be made ready, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Lord,</hi> and a <hi>High way</hi> for <hi>our God;</hi> So prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>GREAT SOVERAIGNS, And Supreme Councel,</salute>
               <signed>Your Moſt proſtrately Devoted in the Records of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>T. Beverley.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:5"/>
            <head>TO THE King and Queens Moſt Excellent Majeſty, And to the High Court of Parliament, And to All who Love, and wait for the Appearance of Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <head type="sub">The moſt Humble Petition of your Faithful Miniſter in the Propheſies of Scripture.</head>
            <p>THAT ſeeing, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath promulg'd that <hi>Divine</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Canon;</hi> That they who <hi>Preach the Evangile</hi> or <hi>good Tydings,</hi> ſhould live of the Evangelick reward that<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. 7.</note> is given to Him, that is the Meſſenger of it; And ſeeing moſt particularly the declaring the <hi>Finiſhing of the Myſtery of God</hi> in <hi>the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is ſtyl'd God's <hi>Evangelizing by the Prophets.</hi> And Laſtly, ſeeing it hath pleas'd the Infinite Grace of God, to conſtitute me his moſt unworthy Servant ſuch an <hi>Eu-Angeliſt</hi> to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to declare the moſt preciſe Time of that <hi>Happy Revolution; The KINGDOM of CHRIST in its Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> upon ſuch undeniable <hi>Prophetic</hi> Evidence; I moſt Humbly pray that for an <hi>Evangelion,</hi> or reward of ſo <hi>good Tydings</hi> I may be Enabled by the Aſſiſtances of ſo Great <hi>Proteſtant Princes, Aſſembly,</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> to perfect the whole <hi>Prophetical Miniſtration committed to me;</hi> And
<pb facs="tcp:106747:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> that it may be laid up for ſo near a Time to Come, as 1697. and the Truth may be Juſtified by the Event.</p>
            <p>In the mean Time, I moſt Humbly Appeal to the moſt <hi>Reverend Epiſcopal Robe,</hi> who are ſo able, and whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Function it is to Judge, whether any Line of the Chain of the <hi>Scripture Argument</hi> I have us'd, be looſe, or weak.</p>
            <p>Now that the Contempt of ſo great a Meſſage, and neglect of the Meſſenger may not reſt, as a Reproach of the <hi>Goodly price, Jeſus Chriſt is prized at;</hi> but that your Bounty may be accepted, as a <hi>Sacrifice of ſweet ſmelling Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor</hi> to God, and <hi>Abound to the Account</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> value<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> ſhall be the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Soveraign Princes, Moſt Noble Lords, Moſt Honourable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives of this Proteſtant Nation.</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioner and Servant in this Evangile. <hi>T. Beverley.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>Parts Printed.</head>
            <p>The <hi>Scripture Line of Time</hi> from the firſt Sabbath to <hi>Abraham.</hi> From <hi>Cyrus</hi> to the Millennial Sabbatiſm. The Prophetick Song of <hi>Solomon</hi> from <hi>Davids Kingdom</hi> to the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>Christ.</hi> The Command to come out of <hi>Babylon.</hi> The late Revolution. <hi>Daniel</hi>'s two Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Expounded.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>To be Printed.</head>
            <p>The <hi>Scripture Line of Time</hi> from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Cyrus.</hi> The Prayer of the Kingdom, or the Lords Prayer. The Sacrament of the Kingdom, or the Lords Supper; adjuſted to this Kingdom. The Doctrine of the Kingdom and the New <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> The Epiſtles to the ſeven Churches, the ſeven Voices or Thunders, the ſeven Vials Expounded.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:6"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Angels of the Churches</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Evangelical Miniſtery,</hi> moſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Grace and Peace from Him, that <hi>Holdeth</hi> the <hi>Seven Stars</hi> in his <hi>Right Hand,</hi> and <hi>walks in the midſt of the Seven Golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks,</hi> and hath the <hi>Seven Spirits</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is to you, My moſt <hi>Reverend,</hi> and <hi>Dearly Honoured Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that in the Second place, as in due order, I Preſent the following Diſcourſe; Not becauſe you <hi>know not the Truth,</hi> but becauſe you <hi>know it,</hi> and that <hi>no Lye is of the Truth,</hi> and ſo according to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> preſcription concerning <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 29.</note> are able to <hi>Judge,</hi> when a divine Revelation by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as well, as of Immediate Inſpiration is given to <hi>Any One.</hi> Not, as you well know, that you can add, or take away from what hath the Evidence of <hi>Divine;</hi> when you find that, Suffrage, and Joynt Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, <hi>Blowing the Trumpet</hi> and <hi>Giving warning</hi> is Your All.</p>
            <p>I therefore <hi>Communicate</hi> to you <hi>Apart,</hi> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the particular <hi>Good Tydings,</hi> I declare, leaſt if I am not able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go<note place="margin">Gal. 2. 2.</note> your Teſt, I <hi>had,</hi> or ſhould <hi>Run in vain,</hi> But I am able, if I may ſo allude, to be <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> with that <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and to <hi>Render an Apology</hi> with <hi>Meekneſs,</hi> and <hi>Fear</hi> to any, that ſhall moſt ſeverely Examine me of <hi>the Hope,</hi> I Promulge, through <hi>his Grace,</hi> that I Truſt in, to <hi>work in me Mightily</hi> to that purpoſe. I onely Fear Prejudging without Hearing; I know I have not onely <hi>Believ'd,</hi> and <hi>therefore Spoken,</hi> but that I have <hi>Propheſied</hi> according to the<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Analogy of the Faith</hi> at once <hi>given to the Saints;</hi> according to the <hi>Doctrine of Godlineſs,</hi> and the <hi>Symmetry</hi> of All <hi>Scripture Prophecy,</hi> the Light of which hath from God ſhone into me, above what I can expreſs; As the <hi>Prophets</hi> of Old, <hi>Divinely mov'd,</hi> were more Inwardly aſſur'd of being <hi>Sent,</hi> then They could expoſe to Others.</p>
            <p>I would Humbly offer that one Credential, concerning the <hi>Time, Times, Half Time</hi> to ſtrict Judgment; What greater Argument, the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> deſign'd, That Time ſhould be ſearch'd, then giving<note place="margin">Dan. 7. 1</note> it ſo peculiarly to the <hi>little Horn,</hi> call'd ſo diſertly by Him; <hi>The Beaſt,</hi> and to the <hi>Beaſtian Times</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and to no other; And why ſearch'd, if not to be found? And is not the <hi>Dividing and Multiplying</hi> among Themſelves thoſe <hi>Characters,</hi> according to preciſe certain <hi>Epochs</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Time</hi> and of the <hi>Half Time,</hi> even <hi>Mathematical?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let none therefore ſay the <hi>Book is Seal'd,</hi> or I am not <hi>Learn'd;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Acceptance with God tho' the Things being of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult
<pb facs="tcp:106747:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> Interpretation, require greater Attention. Eſpecially, You will not ſay ſo, <hi>Moſt Reverend,</hi> and <hi>Learned,</hi> whoſe peculiar office It is to <hi>Search the Scriptures;</hi> And you know, <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> are <hi>Scripture;</hi> And Loe I preſent you the <hi>Book unſeal'd,</hi> by the Aſſiſtance of Him, who prevail'd to <hi>Open the Book</hi> of <hi>Seven Seals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, How would this ſo near <hi>Appearance</hi> of the <hi>Chief Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd,</hi> oblige us to <hi>Feed the flock of Chriſt,</hi> not as <hi>Lords,</hi> nor for <hi>Filthy lucre,</hi> but as <hi>Enſamples</hi> of the <hi>Flock!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 5. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How would this Doctrine of the Kingdom, <hi>Open a door wide and Effectual</hi> to all manner of Re-Reformation, and to a new and <hi>Apoſtolick miſſion</hi> for the preaching the <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> as by the ſpeed of an <hi>Angel flying through the midſt of Heaven?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 6.</note> It will be ſo anon within a <hi>Prophetical laſt Half Hour</hi> of the <hi>Three Days and a Half,</hi> if not juſt now.</p>
            <p>How would this preſerve us from <hi>Grudging one againſt another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames 59.</note> and cauſe our <hi>Moderation</hi> one towards another to be <hi>known to All,</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Judge is before the doors,</hi> and the <hi>Lord at Hand;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hil. 4. 5.</note>
               </hi> How would it cauſe us to ceaſe to <hi>De-Synagogue one another</hi> ſo<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ev. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 8.</note> proper to the <hi>Synagogue of Sathan,</hi> eſpecially when for <hi>Indifferents,</hi> leaſt we <hi>come to worſhip at the Feet of Them,</hi> we have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to <hi>ſhut the Door</hi> upon, and to acknowledge <hi>Chriſt lov'd them!</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t us then Haſten to the <hi>Philadelphian State</hi> of Purity, Love, and Peace; And ſo the <hi>God of Love</hi> and of <hi>Peace, ſhall be with us.</hi> For <hi>this cauſe I bow my Knees</hi> to the <hi>God and Father of</hi> our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> of whom the whole <hi>Family of Heaven and Earth is call'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I moſt Humbly and Earneſtly Recommend to you alſo the aſſiſting and <hi>Furthering</hi> of me in this work of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> according to my Humble Petition Prefix'd who am (however otherwiſe moſt juſtly) through the <hi>Riches of his Grace</hi> as in an <hi>Iſle of Patmos, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the <hi>word of God</hi> and for the <hi>Teſtimony of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as Proſtrate upon the ground, I moſt earneſtly beg pardon of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> Acknowledging my ſelf <hi>Leſs then the leaſt</hi> of All <hi>the Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> and not worthy to be call<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>by the Grace of God I am what I am;</hi> and I have <hi>Labour'd</hi> more <hi>Abundantly</hi> in this great point, thro' the aſſiſtance of that <hi>Spirit,</hi> who <hi>Divides</hi> to all as <hi>He will,</hi> and becauſe <hi>He will.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Moſt Reverend, and Dearly Loved, and Honoured Fathers and Brethren.</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt unworthy Fellow Servant in the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>T B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:7"/>
            <head>THE General Preface, With a Table of Contents.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Preface</hi> I intend, ſhall be to preſent a <hi>Key</hi> of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe, in the plaineſt manner I can.</p>
            <p>The great Intencion of it is, to Aſſert ſo Happy a <hi>Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution</hi> of the World, as the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in its Succeſſion, within ſo few Years, as lye betwixt the preſent 1689, and the next enſuing 1697.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Kingdom,</hi> however the Prophane, and wicked World may take it, and be <hi>Angry</hi> at it, muſt needs be the Joy and deſire of all good Men, and Women. The change will be ſo Great, and Happy, that the <hi>Heathen Empire</hi> becoming <hi>Chriſtian</hi> under <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> was ſo dark a ſhade of it, that notwithſtanding it, the <hi>Churches flight</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 12. 6.</note> 
               <hi>into the Wilderneſs</hi> for 1260 days Is immediately upon it given out. At this 97. It ſhall return from the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> and not before, How much more Glorious ſhall that Time then be? The <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Turk</hi> ſhall go off the Stage of Power, and which is much greater to us; The <hi>Reformation,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant State,</hi> ſhall be purg'd from all the Remains of <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> in <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,</hi> and <hi>Manners,</hi> which, God knows, are very great; For<note place="margin">Rev. 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath not <hi>Found our works perfect</hi> or <hi>Fill'd up before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a dangerous thing to ſay, if God hath ſaid it; How ſhall this thing be? How did he raiſe the World in <hi>Six days,</hi> when as yet there was none of it? How did he bring in a <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> after the Cruelties of thoſe <hi>Salvage Emperors, Diocleſian</hi> and the other Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants of that Time, juſt before Raging in the Laſt, and greateſt <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Perſecution</hi> by the <hi>Pagan Empire!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:8"/>
            <p> The great Queſtion is then, whether he hath ſaid it or not! To ſhew he hath ſaid it, Theſe Two <hi>Viſions</hi> of <hi>Daniel</hi> are expounded by themſelves, together with the Light of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as a <hi>Calendar,</hi> and here offer'd.</p>
            <p>To make out this, It is firſt Intimated, which in its proper place<note place="margin">pag. 1.</note> is more fully prov'd, that <hi>Daniel</hi>'s great <hi>Viſions</hi> throughout his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> and ſo theſe two are on purpoſe to ſhew, how long it would be, e're <hi>Ezekiels viſion</hi> of the <hi>Glorious City,</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> would come out of <hi>Viſion</hi> into the <hi>Everlaſting Throne,</hi> and the <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary cleans'd,</hi> as Real Event.</p>
            <p>To ſhew it would be a long Time, God gives in theſe two <hi>Viſions</hi> a Subſtantial <hi>Calendar</hi> of <hi>Four great Monarchies,</hi> running out themſelves, e're the Everlaſting <hi>Throne</hi> would be Erected; At the end of them, It would; As in another <hi>Viſion,</hi> He gives 2300 <hi>Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>Mornings,</hi> till the <hi>Sanctuary cleans'd,</hi> as a numeral <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar</hi> of the whole Time.</p>
            <p>The beſt Key, that can be given to this, is, to give the Contents of the Diſcourſe, Referring to the pages, wherein each part is diſcours'd, in the way of Argument, That theſe two <hi>Viſions</hi> give ſo Subſtantial a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar</hi> of more value, then <hi>Seth's pillars,</hi> if Extant; and then a <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> ending 1697.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Viſion</hi> is, in the Exquiſite frame, and admirable contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of it, and the moſt Illuſtrious Remarks, Providence ſo deſignedly gave it in <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Expoſition of it, made out to be ſuch a <hi>Calendar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 2.</note> and to end in a <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> neither the <hi>Heavenly,</hi> nor the <hi>Spiritual Evangelical Kingdom</hi> onely; nor that of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>to</hi> pag. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Empire,</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> ſince <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> But One to Come.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Viſion</hi> is then ſhown to be doubled, to Fix the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty,<note place="margin">p. 14. 15. 16</note> as alſo, that It is more particular, as given to <hi>Daniel,</hi> a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick of the <hi>Divine Kingdom,</hi> above what, was allowed to <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> an <hi>Alieu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Grand Argument of ſuch a <hi>Calendar</hi> propos'd, and all along purſued is; That Things have been ſucceſſively, and are to this day in Motion according to this <hi>Calendar;</hi> And by expreſs <hi>Scripture,</hi> as<note place="margin">pag. 16. 17.</note> to the <hi>Babylonian,</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Graecian Monarchies,</hi> All acknowledg'dly paſs'd, and gone off.</p>
            <p>It is therefore in the next place ſhown, the <hi>Calendar</hi> could not expire in the <hi>Graecian Monarchy,</hi> as it ſtood divided after <hi>Alexander the Great;</hi> And that therefore it muſt ſubſiſt in the <hi>Roman Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> and how Agreeably with <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the
<pb facs="tcp:106747:8"/> 
               <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> even to the Evidence of an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> It doth there ſubſiſt, is argued; And that this <hi>Monarchies</hi> having no Name in the <hi>Old</hi> or <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as the other <hi>Monarchies</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 18. <hi>to</hi> p. 25.</note> have, nor any particular ſhape in <hi>Daniel,</hi> as the other <hi>Kingdoms</hi> have in the three <hi>Beaſts,</hi> does not weaken, but ſtrengthen the <hi>Calendar,</hi> is alſo Argued.</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Calendar</hi> therefore might continue in the <hi>Roman Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> That <hi>Monarchy</hi> remain'd unbroken at the Reſurrection,<note place="margin">p. 26.</note> and Aſcenſion of Chriſt; and from thence, it is to be divided into three <hi>Periods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Period</hi> of the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> before <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s moſt<note place="margin">p: 26. 27.</note> Livelily <hi>Symbold</hi> in the <hi>Revel.</hi> c. 12. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Period of the Chriſtian Empire</hi> from <hi>Conſtantine</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 28.</note> till the <hi>Abdication</hi> of <hi>Auguſtulus;</hi> The Symbol of it in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> and the wonderful care, <hi>Prophecy</hi> takes about it, Shown at<note place="margin">
                  <hi>to</hi> p. 38.</note> large, Becauſe it was not <hi>Beſtian,</hi> but a ſhade of the <hi>Kidgdom of Chriſt;</hi> That yet the <hi>Calendar</hi> ſhould not be thought deſtroyed, is diſplayed from the <hi>Apoſtle Paul.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. and from ſeveral <hi>Apocalyptical</hi> Concerts concerning it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Calendar,</hi> as brought down to the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> and plac'd there, as on a Grand pillar of Time, is Reviewed, as in that<note place="margin">p. 39.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> Beginning, and Ceaſing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third <hi>Period</hi> is, of the <hi>Roman Papacy,</hi> wherein is prov'd, that whatever ſucceeded the <hi>Chriſtian Roman Empire,</hi> and hath continued all along to this day, muſt be the <hi>Beſtian</hi> State of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire;</hi> and it could be no other but the <hi>Papacy,</hi> with the<note place="margin">p. 40.</note> 
               <hi>Ten Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> into which that <hi>Empire</hi> was after the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> Divided.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the State of the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> under the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> would be ſo long, that the <hi>Calendar</hi> could not be enough ſupported by the Real ſubſtantial Notes of diſtinction, nor known, <hi>how long!</hi> Here therefore the <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 41. 42.</note> 
               <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time</hi> is given; which had been in vain given, if not to be underſtood; The explication is therefore undertaken in that Aſſurance, and Ballanced, with <hi>Forty Two Months, Prophetically divided</hi> and <hi>multiplyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Epoch,</hi> or Beginning of theſe <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Half Time,</hi> is argued to be at the <hi>Abdication</hi> of <hi>Auguſtulus</hi> (where, by the way<note place="margin">p. 43. <hi>to</hi> 45.</note> the true Notion of <hi>Abdication</hi> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lear'd, and urg'd) and the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> thereupon <hi>Receiving Power with the Beaſt</hi> at <hi>one Hour;</hi> which <hi>Receiving</hi> at <hi>One Hour</hi> is explain'd, and argued.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:9"/>
            <p> The real <hi>Calendar</hi> in the <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Half Time</hi> is argued by ſuch undeniable, and unparalellable Agreements betwixt the <hi>Prophecy of Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and the State of the <hi>Roman Empire</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 46. <hi>to</hi> 53.</note> under the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> as can be no way overcome, by ſo much, as an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> or <hi>Papiſt,</hi> that will conſider.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> of <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time,</hi> is made out by Ballance with the 1260. <hi>days</hi> and <hi>Forty two Months,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 54. <hi>to</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> as the Time of the <hi>Eclipſe</hi> of the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> by the <hi>Beſtian Moon</hi> under its <hi>Feet;</hi> Giving Great underſtanding of the <hi>Calendar,</hi> both in Alluſion to an <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> one of the ſureſt Characters of Time in <hi>Chronology,</hi> and alſo moſt exactly Calculated in its Time of Durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and various degrees of Beginning, Middle, and Going of; And the Application of a <hi>Calendar</hi> onely to the <hi>Little Horn</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and to the Time of the <hi>Beſtian Tyranny</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſhews us, They muſt be both the ſame; and that therefore we muſt be Right in the duration, knowing the <hi>Epoch</hi> of the <hi>Times</hi> and of the <hi>Half Time;</hi> This is diſcours'd at large, and then by way of Brief Recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; That if the <hi>Beaſts Times</hi> and <hi>Half Time</hi> are taken alone, and <hi>Divided,</hi> and <hi>Multiplyed</hi> by themſelves, according to that fix'd <hi>Epoch</hi> of the <hi>Times,</hi> and of the <hi>Half Time;</hi> They muſt needs end at 1697.</p>
            <p>The ſucceſſion of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> is demonſtrated neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily to follow at the end of the <hi>half Time:</hi> together with ſome Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal<note place="margin">p. 64. <hi>to the End.</hi>
               </note> Intimations.</p>
            <p>If then to the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Graecian Monarchy</hi> in its <hi>Divided ſtate,</hi> we have expreſs <hi>Scripture</hi> for the <hi>Calendar;</hi> if all <hi>Hiſtory</hi> aſſures us, the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> ſwallowed that; and <hi>Scripture</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it then in its Greatneſs, even to an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> and hath both by a real Conſpicuous Agreement betwixt it, and <hi>Prophecy</hi> all along preſented it to us in its State <hi>to this day,</hi> and given us a <hi>Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Calendar,</hi> that, tho' <hi>Myſtick,</hi> is to be, and is (I ſolemnly Aſſert) with undoubted Certainty unlock'd to us; as ending at 97. And that nothing can Follow, but the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> Let us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo near a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that <hi>cannot be ſhaken, have Grace,</hi> wherewith to <hi>ſerve God</hi> with <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Godly fear,</hi> For <hi>Our God</hi> is a <hi>Conſuming Fire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. 12. 28.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Beſides ſome ſmall Miſtakes in Pointing, theſe few Faults have eſcap'd, which the Courteous Reader is deſired to mend thus;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. line 6.</hi> for were <hi>read</hi> we. <hi>p. 46. l. 28.</hi> point thus, Compos'd, are; The<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>p. 50 l. 40. r.</hi> Beſtianiſm. <hi>p. 64. l. 30. r.</hi> ſlay. <hi>p. 66. l. 26. r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106747:9"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE UPON Thoſe two Grand <hi>Viſional Dreams</hi> of <hi>Daniels Prophecy;</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The <hi>Dream</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> given to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and Interpreted by <hi>Daniel,</hi> Chap. 2. And the <hi>Dream</hi> of the <hi>Four Beaſts</hi> given to <hi>Daniel,</hi> Ch. 7.</head>
            <head type="sub">Wherein it is endeavoured to be proved, That Theſe <hi>Two Viſions</hi> are a <hi>Calendar</hi> of <hi>Time;</hi> comprehending the whole Space from the Time of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarchy,</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> of Chriſt under the <hi>whole Heaven.</hi> The <hi>Proclaimings</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhall be heard as from <hi>Heaven</hi> 1697.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>I Have in the Foregoing Diſcourſes Adjuſted theſe <hi>Viſions</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and his whole <hi>Prophecy</hi> to the Time of <hi>Ezekiels Prophecy,</hi> and particularly to that <hi>Cardinal Viſion</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>c.</hi> 40. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> of the <hi>Glorious Temple</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> and therein to the laſt <hi>Joynt</hi> of the <hi>Line of Time</hi> before it, <hi>viz.</hi> the 390 <hi>days,</hi> at the end of which, as I have ſhewn; <hi>Ezekiel</hi> had that ſo great <hi>Viſion,</hi> giving a <hi>viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Ceſſation</hi> to his <hi>Bearing</hi> the <hi>Iniquity</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have adjuſted alſo the firſt of theſe <hi>viſions</hi> to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s <hi>Supreme Monarchy</hi> by his Conqueſt of <hi>Egypt, viz.</hi> to the <hi>Second year</hi> of it, and the twenty ſeventh of <hi>Jehoiachins Captivity,</hi> and the Thirty fifth of <hi>Nebuchadnezzers</hi> general Reign.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:106747:10"/>
               <p> Now in all theſe parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulars, theſe Two <hi>viſions</hi> have deep Intereſt, as I have ſhown; I now addreſs my ſelf onely to this point, to prove that theſe Two <hi>viſions</hi> are a Real, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial <hi>Calendar</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> when the <hi>Sanctuary ſhall be Cleans'd;</hi> according to that Great Note of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Third <hi>viſion,</hi> at the End of the 2300 <hi>Evenings</hi> and <hi>Mornings,</hi> and moſt Agreeing with <hi>Ezekiels Prophacy,</hi> when alſo according to that <hi>Prophecy,</hi> the <hi>Everlaſting Throne</hi> ſhall be<note place="margin">Ezek. 47. 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> ſet up.</p>
               <p>Theſe Two, then and indeed the Third <hi>viſion</hi> of <hi>Daniel</hi> give the Time, <hi>how Long;</hi> That great <hi>viſion</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſhall be <hi>viſion</hi> onely, and put nothing into Act, and Effect: The Third <hi>viſion</hi> which is Exactly numeral, I have already publiſh'd the probation of, as Reaching that <hi>End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Without any further preface therfore, I lay down theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Arguments to prove, that theſe Two <hi>viſions</hi> are ſuch a Subſtantial real <hi>Calendar,</hi> and contain alſo a ſhort <hi>Hierogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical</hi> numeral <hi>Calendar;</hi> of <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time,</hi> that Falls into all the Variety and yet Complication of the Characters of Time, in the great <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the <hi>Revelation,</hi> which together with the real Subſtantial Characters of theſe <hi>viſions,</hi> make the Time demonſtratively certain, that the ſucceſſion of <hi>Chriſts Ringdom</hi> ſhall be 1697.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>1</label> The firſt Argument I ſhall Level to this point, ſhall be; That Theſe Two <hi>Dreams,</hi> or <hi>viſions</hi> are made ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable by God, that They are worthy to be ſuch a <hi>Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar</hi> of Time, as I affirm of Them; Now the firſt <hi>viſion</hi> as laying the Foundation, is fuller of outward pomp, and more prepar'd for publick, and univerſal notice; But the ſecond is more Inward to the Glory, and <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> as a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and more perfecting Hand drawn upon the Firſt.</p>
               <p>The Firſt <hi>viſionary Dream</hi> was granted to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> in whom an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> then Reſided; which made him a fit <hi>Head</hi> of that <hi>Image,</hi> and of that Time alſo to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued all along in a Courſe, deſcending from the <hi>Head</hi> to the ſeveral parts, even to the <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes,</hi> and then and there to be <hi>Broken</hi> in pieces, and to be ſucceeded by the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as in preparation to this very purpoſe, the Greatneſs of this <hi>Monarch</hi> is ſo often Amplyfied in the <hi>Prophets;</hi> He is ſeveral Times Call'd by God, <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, My Servant;</hi> as the Great, not onely Subſtitute of Divine power, but as the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106747:10"/> 
                  <hi>proto Type</hi> of it, as it ſhall appear in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> God gave Him <hi>All</hi> Nations <hi>to ſerve Him,</hi> even the <hi>Beaſts of the Field</hi> and the <hi>Fowls of the Heaven; Jeremiah</hi> was Commanded to <hi>ſend Yokes to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> as a Symbol of <hi>ſerving Him,</hi> and ſubmitting <hi>to his Yoke; Ezekiel</hi> calls Him <hi>King of Kings,</hi> a ſtyle <hi>Prophetick</hi> of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſupreme <hi>Title;</hi> and the <hi>Mighty one of the Heathen; Daniel</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents him by the great <hi>Tree,</hi> whoſe <hi>ſhaddow cover'd</hi> and <hi>protected</hi> the very <hi>Fowls</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Beaſts of the Earth;</hi> and All <hi>Fleſh</hi> was Repleniſh'd with its <hi>Fruit.</hi> His <hi>Greatneſs</hi> reach'd to <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and his <hi>Dominion</hi> to the <hi>End of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This made Him the <hi>Head of Gold,</hi> the Beginning of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarchy,</hi> that was to ſucceed in the <hi>Perſian, Grecian,</hi> and <hi>Roman States;</hi> and to Foreſhow, what a <hi>Kingdom</hi> the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt</hi> was to be in its Univerſal Extent; For whoſe ſake ſuch a <hi>Calendar</hi> of <hi>Monarchies</hi> was given; To fore-tell which the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſtood, as one Body under the <hi>Shade</hi> of the great <hi>Tree, Nebuchadnezzar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that this <hi>Dream</hi> of the <hi>Image</hi> might be the more Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Remarkable; There was a Concurrence of all things, that might make it ſo: Firſt, in regard of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> of the Prince, that had the <hi>Dream,</hi> whereby every Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the whole matter had an eaſie and almoſt a neceſſary paſſage through the moſt known parts of the World.</p>
               <p>It being given to the Prince himſelf, it muſt needs be the more Notorious, and the more Certain; and to a prince not worſhipping the <hi>True God;</hi> It muſt be the more undeniable, and free from the Suſpition of a <hi>pious Fraud;</hi> The manner of giving the <hi>Dream</hi> was by the ordination of <hi>Providence</hi> ſuch, as to cauſe the greateſt Agony, and Perplexity to his Thoughts; For his Imagination was deeply Imprinted, that a very Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious <hi>Dream</hi> had found a place in it; And what yet it was, was gone from Him, which contributed exceedingly to the Notoriety of the Thing. For firſt all the <hi>Magicians, Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> and <hi>Wiſe men</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> were ſummon'd upon the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
               <p>When they came, there was nothing offer'd them, but a rude Apprehenſion of ſuch a <hi>Dream;</hi> whereas if the <hi>Dream</hi> it ſelf had been told them; They might have faſtend ſome ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory, however falſe Interpretation to it, and ſo the thing have dyed? When they could offer no Reſolution in ſo diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult a Caſe, there was to make the matter more Notable, a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106747:11"/> 
                  <hi>decree</hi> to <hi>put them to death;</hi> After all the King's perplexity, and even Fury, God gave him ſuch a Reſolution by <hi>Daniel,</hi> as ſav'd ſo many Lives, which fix'd the thing yet deeper in all Mens Thoughts, and gave Aſſurance, that the King was fully ſatisfi'd within Himſelf; That the <hi>Dream</hi> reveal'd to him by <hi>Daniel</hi> was the ſame, that had Graven it ſelf ſo deeply on his mind in his ſleep.</p>
               <p>And it was therefore ordered to be a <hi>Dream,</hi> becauſe accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the opinion of thoſe Nations, and alſo in the thing it ſelf, a <hi>Dream</hi> ſo exactly Fram'd, under ſo great ſenſe, was leaſt under the power of the underſtanding, and therefore Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, and Immediately from God.</p>
               <p>Now that all theſe great Preparations, and ſolemn Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſhould be thus ordered, and diſpoſed by God, without ſome High deſignation of God for the Glory of his own <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and ſome very Admirable <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and Courſe of Time lay'd out to it, I appeal to any perſon, that ſhall duely weigh, and conſider it, whether it be ſo much, as probable.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, whether if there ſhall be other very weighty Reaſons, that ſuch a Courſe of Time to the divine <hi>Kingdom</hi> is deſign'd; This great Ceremony ſo immediately order'd by providence, does not exceedingly concert with it, and add to the Reaſons otherwiſe drawn? Seeing elſe, All this Dvine ſtate was to adorn a <hi>Heathen Prince's Dream</hi> concerning <hi>Heathen Potentacies,</hi> and no change upon the <hi>Heathen</hi> world for the better, nor any Accruement to the divine Kingdom here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by; but onely thoſe Temporary, ſhort Acknowledgments, that dyed upon the Breath, and Lips of that <hi>Pagan Prince</hi> that made them, while neither Himſelf, nor his Kingdom were Converted to the <hi>True God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>2</label> Although there was no End of Glory to the <hi>Divine Kingdom,</hi> worthy the Magnificence of the Manifeſtation to the <hi>Babyloniſh Prince</hi> in this <hi>Dream,</hi> ſhort of the <hi>Divine Kingdom</hi> it ſelf; Yet taking the <hi>Divine Kingdom</hi> at the End, there is a very great and Glorious Correſpondence betwixt this Manifeſtation, and the <hi>Divine Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For at the Time, when the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> ſeem'd to be loſt, and ſwallowed up, and to be even as it were, none at all, through the deep <hi>Captivity</hi> of the onely True people of God, then in the World, under this <hi>Babylonian</hi> King; Yet to ſhew the ſurmount of the <hi>Divine Kingdom</hi> in its vertue, and efficacies,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106747:11"/> there is by the true, and Supreme <hi>Monarch</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> a <hi>Dream</hi> ſo Rivetted into all the Imaginative faculties of this ſo great viſible <hi>Monarch,</hi> his Subſtitute and Servant, that could not be, by all the Pleaſures, and buſineſs of a Court, forc'd from thence; and which yet could not be ſo much as call'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Knowledg, what it was, nor Expounded but by a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Miniſter of the <hi>Divine Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Prophet Daniel;</hi> All the Fatigues of the <hi>Aſtrologers, Magicians,</hi> and <hi>Wiſe-men,</hi> the <hi>Seers</hi> of that great Prince being to no purpoſe in their Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>And this <hi>Dream</hi> retreived out of the dark of a Troubled, but unknowing Imagination, where it was written, as in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in ſo indelible, and yet ſecret Characters prov'd to be, and was Acknowledg'd in the Inlightned underſtanding, and not Incertain Imagination of this Prince, to be a <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the uneaſie Reſt of his own <hi>Monarchic</hi> Power, that was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually <hi>Over Turn'd, Over Turn'd, Over Turn'd</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian. Perſian. Grecian.</note>, till He whoſe Right it is, ſhould come, and take it out of the laſt Reſt of it<note n="*" place="margin">Roman.</note>, Even the <hi>Son of God</hi> Himſelf.</p>
               <p>All which ſo wrought upon this otherwiſe Haughty <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate,</hi> that He made this <hi>Confeſſion</hi> to <hi>Daniel; Your God is the God of Gods,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Kings,</hi> and a <hi>Revealer of Secrets;</hi> And as a further Acknowledgment, He exalts <hi>Daniel,</hi> as in a <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation</hi> of Gods Supremacy over the World, to be over the <hi>Province of Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Chief</hi> of all the <hi>Governouors,</hi> and over all the <hi>Wiſe men</hi> of the <hi>whole Dominion.</hi> A great Prophecy of the Subjection of <hi>Babylon</hi> it ſelf to the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and here the <hi>Horn of Iſrael</hi> that ſeem'd Dead, was made to Bud according to <hi>Ezekiels prophecy</hi> of this very Time, as before argued. <hi>c.</hi> 29. 17.</p>
               <p>And further, that <hi>Miracle</hi> from Heaven ſo Encloſing his Servants in the <hi>Furnace</hi> with the Guards of Providence, that the Flame was a <hi>Wall of Fire</hi> to defend onely, and not to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle upon them, while it <hi>Burnt</hi> up their <hi>Enemies,</hi> vindicated Gods <hi>Supreme Royalty</hi> over Nature, and caus'd that Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant power, that durſt erect ſuch an <hi>Image</hi> for his own Glory, and command the worſhip of it, under a penalty ſo dreadful, to proclaim the reverence of the <hi>True God,</hi> under a more dreadful penalty.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, God ſuſpended this <hi>Monarch</hi> from his <hi>Throne,</hi> and Levell'd him with the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> by depriving him of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106747:12"/> 
                  <hi>Reaſon,</hi> till he came to ſuch a humble Publication of the <hi>Name of God,</hi> as was the neareſt to True Religion, that could be, not to be determin'd to be True Religion.</p>
               <p>And it is moſt obſervable, that as the <hi>Son of God</hi> appeared to this very firſt of the <hi>Four Monarchs,</hi> as it were in perſon, who was the <hi>Supreme Monarch</hi> truly ſo call'd, that his Right to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> deſigned Him, might be the more underſtood, and Teſtified; So <hi>Daniel,</hi> a <hi>Jew</hi> had his <hi>Skirt</hi> taken hold off, thus leading to the <hi>True God</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and He himſelf with the other his Three Companions in the <hi>Patience,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> had a promotion in that <hi>Babyloniſh Monarchy, Prophetical</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> firſt comming to the <hi>Jews,</hi> when it ſhall be <hi>Given</hi> under the <hi>whole Heaven</hi> to the <hi>Saints of the moſt High.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus jealous was Divine honour, not onely over it ſelf, but careful of preſenting to Univerſal view, and notice its great deſign of ſetting up an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> in a <hi>viſible Glory</hi> by that great <hi>Son of Man,</hi> who is alſo the <hi>Son of God;</hi> The <hi>Glory</hi> was not ſo <hi>Given to another,</hi> but that it was ſeen to this <hi>Gentile Ruler,</hi> as ſitting <hi>on a Throne</hi> far above Him; and He on all occaſions was humbled, and abaſed before it.</p>
               <p>And whether theſe Acknowledgments of the Father, might not have an influence on <hi>Evilm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rodach</hi> the Son, and move Him to that kindneſs to <hi>Jehoiachin,</hi> and to <hi>ſet his Throne above any of the Kings,</hi> the word of God gives us no poſſitive Rule to aſſert; Yet probable it is, both the Father and the Son, however convinc'd of the true God, knowing Gods determination of the <hi>Seaventy years Captivity</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> They minght not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe it, as <hi>Cyrus</hi> did. It being God's Councel, it ſhould not be done during that <hi>Monarchy,</hi> becauſe as in Time, ſo in other great Regards, it could not Agree to that <hi>Type, Babylon</hi> was to Bear, to be ſo honour'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>3d.</label> The very Frame and Fabrick of the <hi>Dream,</hi> or <hi>Viſion</hi> it ſelf is a full Evidence of a <hi>Calendar</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> to the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>Image</hi> it ſelf is a <hi>Calendar</hi> of Time, and while that sands, the <hi>Calendar</hi> cannot be out of date, for the <hi>Monarchy</hi> like the <hi>Sun,</hi> from ſign to ſign moves on, and ſlides down from the <hi>Head</hi> to the <hi>Arms,</hi> and <hi>Breaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> then to the <hi>Belly,</hi> and <hi>Thighs,</hi> then to the <hi>Legs,</hi> and <hi>Feet;</hi> and points to time all along according to the nature of a <hi>Calendar,</hi> both by its duration and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106747:12"/> by its motion, and while the <hi>Feet</hi> are <hi>unbrokan,</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> ſtands, and remains a <hi>Calendar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Four Mettals, Gold, Silver, Braſs, Iron,</hi> and a mixture of <hi>Clay,</hi> according the General Emblem of ſucceſſive Ages, in this very order ſignifies the Flower, and top of Time, and the Head of it at firſt, and at laſt the very dregs of Time.</p>
               <p>In which the ſecond is ſaid to be a <hi>Kingdom Inferior,</hi> not ſo<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan</hi> 2. 39.</note> much intending the ſtrength, or Temperament of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Perſian Monarchs,</hi> in many regards exceeding the <hi>Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> as the Inferiority, and Poſteriority of Time, in regard of which the <hi>Head</hi> was of <hi>Gold,</hi> as further off from Ruin, and Deſolation; to which every ſucceſſion approached nearer, till the very <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes of Clay</hi> had the Fatal and Deſtructive ſtroke, wherein all fail'd and fell. So as in <hi>Litteral Bobylon,</hi> the Glory began in <hi>Gold,</hi> ſo in myſtical <hi>Babylon</hi> the <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes</hi> of <hi>Iron</hi> and <hi>Clay</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſtruck</hi> and <hi>Broken,</hi> and the whole <hi>Image</hi> ſhall <hi>Fall,</hi> and <hi>Great</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Fall</hi> of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Monarchies</hi> themſelves, into which the parts of the <hi>Image</hi> are Interpreted, Deſcribe a long Time; ſince it is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently known, ſuch <hi>Potentacies</hi> muſt have Time to diſplay Themſelves in; And that if They ſucceed one Another, it muſt be a long Tract of Time, that muſt give them oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to Come on, and go off from the Stage of ſo publick Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Therefore They themſelves, as <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> or <hi>Monarchiies</hi> deſcribe long Time.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that ſhall <hi>ſtand for Ever and Ever,</hi> and that ſhall have the <hi>dominion</hi> under the <hi>whole Heaven,</hi> is plainly plac'd at the End of theſe <hi>Four,</hi> and <hi>Breaks</hi> in peices the laſt; The <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> that does this, and ſo the whole <hi>Falling</hi> and <hi>Beaten</hi> to <hi>Powder,</hi> and paſſing away as the <hi>Chaff of the Summer Floor,</hi> muſt needs be the Scene, that muſt open laſt, and its <hi>Times</hi> be beyond all their <hi>Times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Till therefore Theſe <hi>Four Kingdomes</hi> have had their Time, the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> comes not on, nor breaks them in pieces, and till the Time, the <hi>proper Time</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> be come, theſe have not had their Full Time; So this is an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dented Character of Time, if any one, That if the laſt of theſe <hi>Kingdomes</hi> be yet continuing, It is certain, <hi>Chriſt's Kingdom</hi> is not yet; And if <hi>Chriſts Kingdom</hi> be not yet, it is certain, the laſt of thoſe <hi>Kingdomes</hi> is yet continuing, and is not daſh'd to powder, and all the <hi>Image</hi> with it, as it ſhall be by the <hi>Stone</hi> cut out
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106747:13"/> of the <hi>Mountain, Filling the whole Earth,</hi> when his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall come.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>4</label> After a moſt ſtately, and Magnificent deſcription, or <hi>Iconiſm</hi> of <hi>Four</hi> mighty <hi>Monarchies,</hi> that viſibly and ſenſibly rul'd over the World, and aw'd it; and that by force, and power broke in pieces all who did not ſubmit; There is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd the preſence of a Fifth <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or <hi>Monarchy,</hi> that the <hi>God of Heaven</hi> ſhould <hi>Set up,</hi> and had never yet been ſet up, that ſhould <hi>Break in pieces,</hi> and <hi>Conſume</hi> all theſe <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> and ſhould it ſelf <hi>ſtand for ever.</hi> And the deſcription of the <hi>Four</hi> precedent is evidently on purpoſe to Introduce, and ſet at the cleareſt, and fulleſt Light the laſt.</p>
               <p>The doubt then is, what <hi>Kingdom</hi> this laſt ſhould be; The Sovereignty of Supreme, and Univerſal providence is at all Times alike; The <hi>moſt High</hi> always <hi>Rules, changes Times,</hi> and <hi>Seaſons, Pulls down,</hi> and <hi>Sets up;</hi> It cannot therefore be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of that; For to what Account would ſo particular and expreſs <hi>Iconiſm</hi> of that Turn, that is always the ſame, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways alike? or why ſhould that <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the ſupreme <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> adminiſtred by his <hi>Providence,</hi> that is an <hi>Everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Endureth throughout All Generations,</hi> be thus Poſtpon'd to <hi>Four</hi> great <hi>Monarchies,</hi> that exiſted before them; and by, and in which they Themſelves always ſubſiſt while they do ſubſiſt? This divine Providential <hi>Kingdom</hi> then it cannot be.</p>
               <p>Let it then be ſuppos'd to be the <hi>Spiritual Evangelick Kingdom</hi> of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> beginning at his Reſurrection and <hi>Chriſtianizing</hi> ſo great a part of the then <hi>Known</hi> World, and which by degrees brought <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> into Subjection to it, not onely <hi>Spiritual,</hi> but alſo <hi>Politick, Civil</hi> and <hi>Monarchic,</hi> from the Time of <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that it was not the <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Evangelical Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I will conteſt onely on this <hi>Topick;</hi> When an <hi>Image</hi> is made up of <hi>Four Monarchies,</hi> Senſible, Viſible, and that did all their work in ſuch a Senſible, Viſible manner; It is againſt thoſe curious Laws of <hi>Iconiſm,</hi> in which the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> is as Exquiſite, as in the very order of the <hi>Creation,</hi> or in the Fabrick of Mans Body, to ſubjoyn a Spiritual <hi>Stone</hi> and <hi>Mountain,</hi> that ſhould as a <hi>Stone</hi> ſmite the <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>Break</hi> it in <hi>Pieces,</hi> and then it ſelf became a great <hi>Mountain filling the Earth,</hi> and all this one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in an <hi>Evangelical Spiritual</hi> ſenſe, and then Riſe up into a perfect <hi>Spirituality</hi> or <hi>Heavenlineſs,</hi> and therein continue <hi>for Ever.</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106747:13"/> This I aſſert, (and leave the aſſertion to every judicious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderer,) to be ſo unlike the admirable <hi>Emblematizings,</hi> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations of the <hi>Divine Spirit,</hi> as to be by no means endured.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Stone</hi> and the <hi>Mountain</hi> thus underſtood, take up no Room, nor give any more Reſiſtance, or <hi>Anti-typy</hi> to the four <hi>Monarchies</hi> before, then the <hi>Hoaſts</hi> of <hi>Immaterial</hi> Beings do to <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> how innumerable ſoever; or then the <hi>Omnipreſence</hi> of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſity</hi> does to the motion of <hi>material Beings</hi> throughout the whole Sphere of worldly ſpace; or the Notions of Vertue and Juſtice make reſiſtance after the manner of Armies to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults of bodily Puiſſance: and therefore though the Kingdom of Chriſt had great Effects upon the World in that very ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Senſe, and by way of Conſequence, upon bodily Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet the <hi>Imagery</hi> of it were as improperly joyn'd with the <hi>Imagery</hi> of the <hi>Monarchies,</hi> as the laying Spirits in Colours would be, when the Action of Body and Matter is intended to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented firſt; and then that Body and Matter forc'd out of its place by other however purer Matter, that ſhould fill its Room and Space: for ſo it is here, the <hi>Stone,</hi> though <hi>Cut out of the Mountain without Hands,</hi> becomes a <hi>Mountain filling the Earth,</hi> and the Saints of the <hi>moſt High</hi> take the <hi>Dominion</hi> under the <hi>whole Heaven,</hi> which Expreſſions plainly ſhew, the State of theſe <hi>Monarchies</hi> is not taken away, and ſupplyed by a State above <hi>All Heavens,</hi> but by a State as well under the <hi>Heaven,</hi> and upon the <hi>Earth,</hi> as on high; ſo that the taking away all Earthly State, and a Heavenly State ſucceeding it, cannot be the meaning of this <hi>Viſion;</hi> nor a ſpiritual State before that, can be the meaning; for the higheſt <hi>ſpiritual</hi> State that hath been yet in the World. <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Miniſtery of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> gave no diſturbance to the <hi>Monarchies</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> made any remove of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>5</label> The <hi>Heavenly</hi> State of <hi>Chriſts Kingdom,</hi> or in the pure and perfect <hi>Eternity</hi> being foreprized by thoſe Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons forenam'd, from being the meaning, and importance of this <hi>Viſion,</hi> we may further argue, that neither the <hi>Spiritual</hi> State of <hi>Chriſts Kingdom</hi> at his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> nor that Spiritual State prevailing upon the multitude of Chriſtians, firſt by Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and then upon Temporal <hi>Princes,</hi> as <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and Princes, ſince the Empire becoming <hi>Chriſtian</hi> under Him, can be the purport of this <hi>Viſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106747:14"/>
               <p> For though the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt did grow great in its Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituality and Divine Truth, in the <hi>Miniſtry, Death,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</hi> of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; And though the World was in very Great, and wonderful manner converted to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity after it, and though the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> did become viſibly and ſenſibly Great under <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and did <hi>break in pieces the whole material,</hi> and ſecular frame of the <hi>Heathen Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Monarchy,</hi> and might ſeem hereupon to become a <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain filling the whole Earth;</hi> and indeed great notice is taken of it in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> as if <hi>the Kingdom of our God</hi> had been <hi>come, Revel.</hi> 12. Yet by comparing two things; one in this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> the other in the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> we ſhall be plainly convinc'd, that neither the <hi>Spiritual Kingdom,</hi> nor his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſuppoſed in the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> can be this <hi>Stone, Mountain,</hi> nor <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and certain Knowledge not only of <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> but of the general State of the World will make it good.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Kingdom <hi>God ſets up</hi> ſhall not be <hi>left</hi> to other <hi>People,</hi> that is, It ſhall not be as the other <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> bequeath'd, left by Will, or as we ſpeak <hi>demiſed</hi> to other <hi>People;</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Death, that is, the Ruine of the Teſtator, as to his <hi>Dominion,</hi> however his <hi>Life might be prolonged.</hi> This is ordain'd by him, whoſe <hi>Dominion</hi> is to all <hi>Generations.</hi> Thus the <hi>Babylonian</hi> demis'd to the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> to the <hi>Graecian,</hi> the <hi>Graecian</hi> to the <hi>Roman,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> ſhall be forced to ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the <hi>People of the moſt High;</hi> But they ſhall never paſs away their <hi>Dominion,</hi> over whom the Lord Jeſus is Prince to any <hi>diverſe People,</hi> as the Inheritor of their Power.</p>
               <p>But now let the <hi>Kingdom</hi> be underſtood of the Spiritual <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, or of the <hi>Empire</hi> as <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> becoming the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and this Character will fit neither; for the <hi>Spirituality</hi> of Chriſts Kingdom was thus far <hi>left</hi> to <hi>other People,</hi> that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> after the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of Chriſt, ſays, <hi>That day ſhall not come,</hi> except there come an <hi>Apoſtaſie Firſt,</hi> a defection<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Theſ. c.</hi> 2.</note> from the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> who is a Prince moſt oppoſite to Chriſt, be <hi>Revealed;</hi> accordingly it is ſaid, <hi>The Spirit ſpeaketh expreſly, ſome, viz.</hi> a Generation of men ſhall <hi>depart</hi> from the <hi>Faith, &amp;c.</hi> How then can ſo much as the <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> be ſaid to <hi>ſtand for ever and ever:</hi> And then for the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> being ſuppoſed to become Great by <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and other <hi>Chriſtian Princes</hi> ſince Him, It cannot be made good, for beſides the Inrodes, the <hi>Barbarous</hi> Nations
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106747:14"/> made on the <hi>Empire,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom of the Beaſt</hi> Riſing ſo ſoon, as the ſame <hi>Hour,</hi> the <hi>Empire</hi> fell; Beſides all this, the <hi>Mahometan Impoſture</hi> and <hi>Pſeudo-Religion</hi> aroſe againſt the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual part of <hi>Chriſts Kingdom;</hi> and its <hi>Tyranny</hi> againſt the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> that ſhould <hi>fill the Earth.</hi> How then did the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in this Senſe <hi>break in pieces</hi> all other <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and <hi>conſume</hi> them, that It might it ſelf <hi>fill the Earth?</hi> Or how was the <hi>Kingdom under the whole Heaven given to the Saints of the moſt High?</hi> Or how was his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſuch an <hi>Everlaſting Kingdom?</hi> But when ever Chriſt takes the Kingdom, It muſt be thus univerſal in its ſpread, and Everlaſting in its Duration.</p>
               <p>From whence I conclude neither the <hi>Spiritual Evangelical Kingdom,</hi> begun at the <hi>Reſurrection of Chriſt,</hi> nor the <hi>Chriſtian Imperial Kingdom</hi> at <hi>Conſtantine</hi> is the <hi>Kingdom</hi> here foretold; but one yet to come, and though the <hi>Spiritual Kingdom</hi> then begun never indeed can be totally <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> nor ſo much as the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialneſs</hi> of the <hi>Name of Chriſt</hi> declared in <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſhall ever be depoſed; yet the <hi>Conſumption</hi> of all other <hi>Dominions,</hi> and the Greatneſs of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> under the <hi>whole Heaven</hi> cannot ſo much, as be pretended to be Fulfilled, while <hi>Popery,</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometaniſm</hi> have ſuch a Name in the World; nor can the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie</hi> poſſibly allow any Abridgment of what was once obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which yet hath certainly fallen out to <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in both the <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Imperial Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt; from whence it is certain, It is not the <hi>Kingdom</hi> here <hi>propheſied,</hi> that hath yet been.</p>
               <p>Nor, to ſpeak Impartially, can It be underſtood by either of theſe <hi>Propheſies,</hi> that there ſhould be any viſible Regiment at leaſt in the then known parts of the World, but what ſhall be <hi>given to the Saints of the moſt High,</hi> when That <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall appear, for All ſhall be taken from thoſe of the <hi>four ſucceſſive Monarchies,</hi> that had it before, or what ever was enjoyed by any of them within any of thoſe Territories; ſeeing of Them particularly It is <hi>propheſied</hi> that their <hi>Dominion</hi> ſhall be <hi>taken away,</hi> and given to the <hi>Saints of the moſt High,</hi> and then are added more large, and comprehenſive Words, taking in the whole World.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>6</label> If the very Frame of the <hi>Viſion</hi> be ſuch, as is moſt proper for the giving ſuch a <hi>Calendar</hi> until that <hi>Great Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> then we have Reaſon to look upon it as ſuch a <hi>Calendar.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106747:15"/>
               <p> Let us then conſider in the <hi>Image</hi> theſe ſeveral Things;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The whole <hi>Image</hi> made up of all its Parts.</item>
                  <item>2. The Diſtribution of the Parts, as the ſeveral Reſidencies of the <hi>Monarchies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The <hi>Monarchicneſs</hi> it ſelf.</item>
                  <item>4. The <hi>Monarchicneſs</hi> firſt United in its Reſidency to ſuch and ſuch Parts, and then its remove to other Parts.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Now in every one of theſe Particulars by the Wiſdom of the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> ſome aſſurance of Time in general is Given, as It runs to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> but moſt particularly, the <hi>Calendar</hi> is fix'd in the Duration of the <hi>Monarchic Reſidence</hi> in each part; then in the Remove of the <hi>Monarchicneſs</hi> from one part to another; as ſhall be ſeen by this following Reflection on each.</p>
               <p>The whole <hi>Image</hi> is made up of <hi>Four Monarchies,</hi> which in Alluſion to the Humane Body, make the upper and lower parts of ſuch a Body; the higher Parts the Precedent, and firſt Ages of Time, at and after the <hi>Viſion</hi> given; and ſo furtheſt from the <hi>End,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the lower parts the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ages nearer, and nearer to the <hi>End,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The whole <hi>Image</hi> therefore hath a fitneſs to deſcribe Time by its Higher, and Lower parts; and further, It ſelf ſtanding, and having its ſeveral parts ſubſiſtent or in Being, is thus far a <hi>Calendar,</hi> that we know thereby; The Time of the <hi>Image</hi> is yet, and that therefore the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not yet <hi>Come,</hi> even as we know by the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> not yet <hi>Appearing;</hi> The <hi>Image</hi> is yet ſtanding.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee, the whole <hi>Image,</hi> and the diſtribution of its Parts is prepared, as the Dial-plate of a Clock, or Watch; or as the Months in the year, giving together the Circle of the Suns motion.</p>
               <p>But then the <hi>Monarchicneſs</hi> is as the Sun moving from Sign to Sign, or from Month to Month, or as the Hand on the Dial-plate from Hour to Hour; ſo moves that <hi>Monarchicneſs</hi> from the higher to the lower parts, and thereby defines Time; For the Higher the parts in which the <hi>Monarchy</hi> reſides, the further off from the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> the lower it ſubſides, the nearer to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> If then we can find the <hi>Monarchicneſs</hi> in any parts of this <hi>Image</hi> yet Reſiant or Reſting, we know in general the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> hath not yet appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but if we find it in not only the <hi>Legs,</hi> but in the <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes,</hi> we know, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſays, It is the <hi>laſt Hour,</hi> but it is not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106747:15"/> yet out. Let us then conſider theſe <hi>Four Kingdomes,</hi> or <hi>Monarchies,</hi> as cloſely united, as they make this <hi>Calendar of Time,</hi> as the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Body is; however the parts, as ſeveral <hi>Kingdomes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt one with another, where the <hi>Monarchicneſs</hi> ſhall Reſide; while then the <hi>Feet</hi> ſupport the whole, the whole ſtands; and as the <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> the <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Breaſt</hi> of <hi>Silver,</hi> and <hi>Thighs</hi> of <hi>Braſs,</hi> give Luſtre to the <hi>Iron Legs,</hi> and <hi>Feet part of Iron,</hi> and <hi>part of Clay;</hi> So the <hi>Feet of part Iron, part Clay,</hi> at the ſame Time ſupport the more excellent <hi>Mettals,</hi> and ſhow their danger of being Beaten together, when ever thoſe partly <hi>Brittle Feet</hi> fail, and the <hi>Image</hi> falls thereupon; Till then they Remain, as in the <hi>Type</hi> united, as Bodily parts, however the <hi>Monarchicneſs,</hi> as a <hi>Spirit</hi> Flitts and ſhifts in its efficacy of Power, and Action from one to another; <hi>viz.</hi> from the Higher to Lower, on which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in the following <hi>Viſion,</hi> it is ſaid, the laſt or fourth <hi>Beaſt</hi> in the <hi>Little Horn,</hi> and his <hi>Body</hi> is <hi>given to the devouring Flames;</hi> But the <hi>other Beaſts</hi> had onely their <hi>Dominion taken from them,</hi> but their <hi>Lives</hi> were <hi>Prolonged;</hi> That then, which principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gives us the Time of the <hi>Calendar</hi> is the Motion of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchic Spirit</hi> from part to part.</p>
               <p>Now that <hi>Monarchic Spirit,</hi> which is ſpecific to all theſe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies</hi> is <hi>Idolatrous,</hi> Salvage, Cruel, oppos'd to the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> So long then as ſuch a <hi>Spirit</hi> Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, and Informs any part of this <hi>Image,</hi> ſo long the <hi>Calendar</hi> is in date. And if we can find where this <hi>Spirit</hi> is now in its <hi>Monarchic,</hi> Energetic force, we may know whereabout, we are in this <hi>Calendar;</hi> For ſeeing it is moſt undeniable, the <hi>Head of Gold</hi> was the <hi>Firſt Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom</hi> ariſing after, and <hi>Inferior</hi> in Time was the Second <hi>Kingdom,</hi> That which next followed after was a <hi>Third Kingdom,</hi> that was of <hi>Braſs,</hi> and then a <hi>Fourth</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> firſt as in the <hi>Legs,</hi> and then <hi>part of Iron, part of Clay,</hi> as in the <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes</hi> of the laſt ſtate; and that each of theſe are called <hi>Kingdomes</hi> and not ſingle Kings, and one after another, and that <hi>God</hi> hereby <hi>made known</hi> to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> what <hi>ſhould be hereafter;</hi> Seeing All theſe things are undeniably thus; It is alſo undeniable, theſe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies</hi> are a <hi>Calendar of Time:</hi> And laſtly, ſeeing the <hi>Kingdom</hi> that <hi>ſtands for Ever, and Ever,</hi> ſo particularly <hi>ſmites the Image</hi> in the <hi>Feet,</hi> and <hi>Toes of Iron,</hi> and <hi>Clay,</hi> and that the <hi>Iron,</hi> and the <hi>Clay</hi> and the <hi>Braſs</hi> and the <hi>Silver,</hi> and the <hi>Gold</hi> were <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in pieces together;</hi> and that in the <hi>days of the Kings, Symboll'd</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106747:16"/> by the <hi>Toes,</hi> the God of Heaven would <hi>Set up a Kingdom,</hi> and laſtly, that the <hi>Stone cut out of the Mountain without Hands,</hi> ſhall <hi>Break</hi> in <hi>Pieces</hi> the <hi>Iron,</hi> the <hi>Braſs,</hi> and the <hi>Clay,</hi> (which is ſet in the middle, as in the point where all were Broken) and the <hi>Silver,</hi> and the <hi>Gold;</hi> It is moſt evident, This <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Gold, Silver, Braſs, Iron,</hi> and <hi>Clay,</hi> is a <hi>Calendar</hi> of Time till the <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Throne,</hi> which muſt be the ſame with the <hi>Throne</hi> in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and that the <hi>Toes</hi> particularly, as of <hi>Clay</hi> are the very Laſt part or End of the <hi>Calendar</hi> before that <hi>Throne,</hi> or <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>7</label> The Conſideration of the following <hi>Viſion</hi> of<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p.</hi> 7.</note> the <hi>Four Beaſts</hi> given by God to <hi>Daniel,</hi> is a further Aſſurance of the <hi>Calendar</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> drawn in theſe two <hi>Viſions:</hi> For therein God hath <hi>doubled</hi> the <hi>thing</hi> for the <hi>certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of it; as in <hi>Pharohs Dream</hi> of old, Interpreted by <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and there is no Reaſon to doubt, both <hi>Viſions</hi> Center in the ſame deſign to lead by the ſame <hi>Four Kingdomes</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and at the ſame Time, <hi>viz.</hi> at the End of the <hi>Four Monarchies:</hi> There is no Reaſon, I ſay, to doubt, although the Materials, or Symbols of the <hi>Viſions</hi> differ ſo much, as one to be taken from the ſeveral parts of the <hi>Body of a Man,</hi> the other from <hi>Salvage Beaſts.</hi> For ſo the ſimilitudes in <hi>Pharohs dream</hi> much differ'd; one taken from <hi>ſeaven Ears of Corn,</hi> the other from <hi>ſeaven Kine.</hi> But as then, ſo now, The great Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was to Aſcertain the Event by Ingemination, For the <hi>Four Kingdomes</hi> in both <hi>Viſions</hi> ſo evidently plain, and the <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom</hi> at the <hi>End,</hi> are unqueſtionable Aſſurances, that both Intend the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> a Subſtantial <hi>Calendar</hi> of <hi>Four Monarchies</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet this latter <hi>Viſion</hi> differs from the Former in Two regards.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The former was originally given to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> a Heathen Prince, and Expounded by <hi>Daniel;</hi> This is firſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Daniel,</hi> and upon after <hi>Viſional</hi> ſearch more fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd by God to him; and ſo there is a more inward diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of things relating to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Church of God,</hi> then was vouchſaf'd to an <hi>Alien</hi> to the <hi>Common-Wealth of Iſrael,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though That was admirably Great, and greatly for the Glory of the ſupreme Being and Governor of the World; and a laſting Monument of it to after Ages, and alſo an Illuſtrious Teſtimony of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> that ſhould at the laſt break
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106747:16"/> in pieces his own and the three ſucceding <hi>Monarchies,</hi> which were, as hath been ſhewn, a Table of Time to that Kingdom, and therewith all other <hi>Monarchies</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet this was but in the groſs; To <hi>Daniel</hi> an eminent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the <hi>Divine Kingdom,</hi> there is a more explicit <hi>Revelation</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> the great Enemy, and oppoſite of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> who was the <hi>Clay</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> and in whom the whole ſhould be <hi>broken;</hi> and this with the incident particulars, of the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, Antichriſt</hi> ſhould exerciſe over the Saints; of the <hi>Son of Man Receiving the Kingdom</hi> from God <hi>ſitting in Judgment</hi> on <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> and then the Saints <hi>poſſeſſing the Kingdom</hi> under Chriſt, are great Amplifications of the former <hi>Viſion,</hi> and more agreeable to <hi>Daniel,</hi> a Domeſtick of the <hi>Divine Kingdom,</hi> and ſo moſt fit to lead to that <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The former <hi>Viſion</hi> was in the <hi>ſecond year of Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> when the <hi>Babylonian Monarchy</hi> had gain'd the aſcendent over all the <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> ſo as to be an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy.</hi> The lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Viſion</hi> was in the Weſt, and Evening of that <hi>Monarchy, viz.</hi> in the <hi>firſt year of Belſhazzars</hi> ſhort Reign, who was the laſt <hi>Babyloniſh Monarch,</hi> and to whom the Scripture records only three years. In the firſt <hi>Viſion</hi> thereof the <hi>Types</hi> were more condecent to a Prince ſo aggrandiz'd by God, <hi>viz.</hi> A great <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>excellent Brightneſs,</hi> and <hi>terrible Form; a Head of Gold;</hi> but in the latter <hi>Viſion,</hi> theſe four <hi>Monarchies</hi> are repreſented by <hi>Beaſts,</hi> ſeated in the midſt of Violence, Blood, and Spoil; and chiefly beaſtly and bruitiſh <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Perſecution;</hi> eſpecially the firſt and laſt of theſe <hi>Monarchies</hi> were ſo. And as to the ſecond, although the great Services of ſome of the <hi>Perſian Princes</hi> to the <hi>Church of God</hi> might ſeem to have deſerved a fairer Character: and ſo the acknowledgment, the <hi>Great Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> is reported to have made to the <hi>True God</hi> in the <hi>High Prieſt;</hi> yet in regard of the <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and Ravage upon the World, and as making up one <hi>Image</hi> of Univerſal <hi>Monarchy</hi> oppos'd to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and laſtly in regard of the Perſecution of ſome of the Princes of both thoſe Monarchies againſt the Church of God, of which the <hi>Perſan</hi> Princes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>Chriſt, Dan.</hi> 10. 13. <hi>Haman</hi> in <hi>Eſther,</hi> and <hi>Antiochus</hi> of the <hi>Graecian Monarchy</hi> ſo great a <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt deſolating the Sanctuary,</hi> and <hi>taking away the daily,</hi> are Inſtances, They are all under the ſame Name of Infamy.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106747:17"/>
               <p> Yet in the Infinite Mercy of God to any degree of Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, <hi>Nebuchadnezzar's</hi> acknowledgment of God after his ſo great Humiliation ſeems remembred with Honor in that Symbol; After the <hi>plucking of the Wings</hi> on the <hi>Lyons back,</hi> ſhewing at once both the ſpeed, and the ſhortneſs of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> firſt <hi>Monarchy;</hi> It was <hi>lifted up from the Earth, and made as a man to ſtand on its Feet,</hi> and a <hi>mans Heart was given to it:</hi> In all other, Theſe Monarchies together, as alienated from the Worſhip, and Religion of the <hi>True God,</hi> and as Predeceſſors of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> are deſcribed from what is worſt; Beſtialneſs and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and therefore the whole of their <hi>Dominion</hi> to be taken away, and <hi>conſum'd</hi> by the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in that this <hi>Viſion</hi> thus reſumes the Time, that was paſt, from the firſt <hi>Viſion,</hi> It argues, The two <hi>Viſions</hi> ſo evidently of the ſame Importance, One at the Beginning, the other at the End of the <hi>Babylonian Monarchy</hi> are a ſubſtantial Calendar of Time, to begin as from the <hi>Viſion</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and to determine at the <hi>Everlaſting Throne</hi> that <hi>Ezekiel</hi> had foretold, as they moſt evidently both do; and ſo define the Time betwixt that <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and that <hi>Throne,</hi> which is the point we are in purſuit of.</p>
               <p>It is true, when the <hi>Sacred Chronology</hi> comes to a <hi>numeral Line,</hi> or a <hi>Line of Time</hi> by <hi>Number,</hi> the <hi>Babylonian Monarchy</hi> is then left out, as it muſt needs be; becauſe elſe the <hi>numeral Line</hi> beginning after it could not be exact, and becauſe it is ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the Account of the 2300 <hi>Even. Morn.</hi> that there needed no ſervice from the <hi>ſubſtantial Calendar,</hi> which is thenceforth to be guided by it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>8</label> I come now to the laſt and undeniable Argument, that Theſe <hi>Viſions</hi> are a <hi>Calendar</hi> of Time to the great <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt.</hi> And that is, if it can be made out by <hi>Holy Scripture</hi> in Agreement with Univerſal <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> That from the very Time of theſe <hi>Viſions</hi> given, Things have been in Motion, and are ſtill in the Motion, They ſhould be, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this <hi>Calendar</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> Then it will be impoſſible to deny, that Theſe <hi>Viſions</hi> are indeed a <hi>Calendar of Time</hi> to that <hi>Kingdom.</hi> But this is to be made out from <hi>Scripture,</hi> and therefore They muſt be a <hi>Calendar;</hi> For firſt the <hi>Scripture</hi> is expreſs, that according to this <hi>Calendar,</hi> the <hi>Babylonian Kingdom</hi> gave way to the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that <hi>Hand-writing,</hi> that ſo much Terrified <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> of which <hi>Daniel</hi> was the Interpreter, <hi>Thy Kingdom is divided</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106747:17"/> 
                  <hi>and given to the Medes and Perſians; viz.</hi> to the <hi>Breaſt</hi> and <hi>Two Arms</hi> of the <hi>Medes,</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> but ſo that the <hi>Perſian Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> Roſe above the <hi>Medes;</hi> and that one <hi>Horn</hi> in <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſtarted up ſo much higher, than the other, that it had the ſole <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> So that though <hi>Darius the Mede,</hi> took the <hi>Kingdom</hi> or the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Monarchy from <hi>Babylon</hi> firſt; Yet we read of <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> his firſt year Following immediately; For in anſwer to <hi>Daniel</hi>'s prayer at the very End of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty years, the Commandment immediately came forth, which was by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> making in his firſt year a decree for the Releaſe of the <hi>Captivity,</hi> and therefore his <hi>Firſt year</hi> muſt be at the End of <hi>Darius</hi> his <hi>firſt year;</hi> So we read of his <hi>Third year,</hi> and of the years of the following Kings of <hi>Perſia,</hi> by which we know the <hi>Perſian Kingdom</hi> was the <hi>Second Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The paſſing off of the <hi>Perſian Monarchs</hi> is no leſs expreſs; For the <hi>Grecian He Goat Brake</hi> the <hi>Two horns</hi> of the <hi>Perſian Ram,</hi> who <hi>Took the Kingdom</hi> from <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Stamped</hi> upon<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. 7.</note> Him; And to ſhew the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> then paſs'd, the <hi>King of Grecia</hi> is ſaid to <hi>do according to his Will,</hi> an expreſſion of the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>c.</hi> 11. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> in this <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> is by all allowed to be that <hi>Grecian King,</hi> figur'd by the <hi>Leopard,</hi> and <hi>He Goat,</hi> and is expreſly nam'd <hi>King of Grecia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After <hi>Alexander,</hi> There was a continual mutation, and change of that <hi>Monarchy</hi> out of one Hand into another; that it was as into the <hi>four Winds</hi> in regard of the motion, and Variation, till it after ſettled in the <hi>four Kingdoms,</hi> and Conſpicuouſly in Two; the <hi>Lagidae of Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>Seleucidae of Greco-Syria,</hi> as in the Two <hi>Thighs</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> ſo Remarkable a Character of Time as to be known by the <hi>Dhil-Karnain</hi> or <hi>Two Hornes,</hi> as it were from this <hi>Prophecy of Daniel,</hi> and theſe, <hi>Prophecy</hi> eſpecially inſiſts upon in the <hi>Eleaventh Chapter,</hi> as the <hi>King of the South,</hi> and of the <hi>North,</hi> as ſhall be after explain'd.</p>
               <p>And in this ſucceſſion, the <hi>Calendar</hi> is very clear, and not to be doubted, as hath been already, and ſhall be further made good in theſe Three great Poſitions, wherein the further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the <hi>Calendar</hi> down to our very Time, ſhall be even de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſit.</hi> 1. That the Time delineated by this <hi>Calendar</hi> cannot be expir'd.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106747:18"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Poſit.</hi> 2. That the <hi>Calendar,</hi> and its Time being not expir'd, it can be continued onely in the <hi>Roman Monarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poſit.</hi> 3. That the <hi>Calendar</hi> having its ſubſiſtence in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Monarchy,</hi> there is, as may juſtly be expected, ſuch an <hi>Idea</hi> of it, partly <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> but eſpecially <hi>Prophetical</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> agreeing with undoubted <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> as ſhall exactly correſpond this <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> whereby we may know whereabouts we are in this <hi>Calendar,</hi> with an anſwer to Objections.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>1</label> This <hi>Calendar</hi> is to expire in the <hi>Stone</hi> cut out of the <hi>Mountains without Hands,</hi> that is, by a High, divine, ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural power; ſmiting the <hi>Image,</hi> and <hi>Becomming a Mountain,</hi> that ſhall <hi>Fill the whole Earth.</hi> And in the <hi>days</hi> or <hi>Their dayes</hi> of <hi>thoſe Kings</hi> (to make the date moſt exact) <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>Feet,</hi> and <hi>Toes, part of Iron,</hi> and <hi>part of Clay; The God of Heaven</hi> ſhall <hi>ſet up a Kingdom,</hi> that <hi>ſhall not End,</hi> not be <hi>left to other people,</hi> but it ſhall <hi>Break</hi> in <hi>pieces,</hi> and <hi>Conſume all theſe Kingdoms,</hi> and They ſhall be <hi>Broken in pieces</hi> and become, as the <hi>chaff in the Summer Threſhing Floors,</hi> and the <hi>Wind ſhall carry them away, ſo that their places ſhall be no more found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And according to the Second <hi>Viſion,</hi> the <hi>Calendar</hi> muſt expire in the <hi>Giving</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> of the <hi>Little Horn (Broken</hi> in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Viſion</hi> without <hi>Hand</hi> that is, by an immediate divine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to the <hi>conſuming Flame)</hi> and giving a <hi>Dominion, Glory,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom to the Son of Man,</hi> that <hi>All People, Nations,</hi> and <hi>Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſhould ſerve Him;</hi> The <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Dominion,</hi> and <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Kingdom, viz.</hi> particularly of that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy,</hi> that had been according to the <hi>Image</hi> ſhifted from part to part; and more then that, the whole <hi>Dominion</hi> or the <hi>Dominion under the whole Heaven</hi> ſhall be given to the <hi>People of the Saints of the moſt High.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I would appeal to all thinking, and conſidering Men, who do not Implicitly yield up their faith to the Stream of Interpreters, whether Theſe things have yet been plainly, viſibly, and notoriouſly Fulfill'd; as is juſtly to be expected in <hi>Prophecies</hi> already Incarnate, and compleated in their Events; And eſpecially in an Event ſo great above all other Events; or whether it can be ſuppos'd; ſuch Firm, Solid, natural Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of a <hi>Kingdom</hi> can be Attennuated, and Evaporated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Metaphor,</hi> and <hi>Similitude;</hi> Seeing it is much to be believ'd, that therefore <hi>Metaphor</hi> and <hi>Similitude</hi> is ſo often us'd; becauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106747:18"/> 
                  <hi>All Things</hi> that are <hi>written,</hi> ſhall be at laſt <hi>Fulfill'd</hi> in ſo High, Perfect, Subſtantial, maſſy Event, and uncontradictable Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <p>If then theſe Things are in this manner to come to paſs, and are not yet come to paſs; we know, this <hi>Calendar</hi> cannot be as yet expir'd, or out dated.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>2</label> If the <hi>Calendar</hi> then be not expir'd, it can be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued onely in the <hi>Roman Monarchy;</hi> For there is nothing more evident, then that it muſt be continued in one of thoſe <hi>Four Monarchies,</hi> that are given in the <hi>Image,</hi> and in the <hi>Viſion</hi> of the <hi>Beaſts;</hi> and ſeeing the <hi>Babylonian,</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> and <hi>Grecian,</hi> whether in <hi>Alexander,</hi> or in the <hi>Diviſions,</hi> into which his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Fell,</hi> have had their ſucceſſion, one after another, and that none of them continue at this day in ſuch a ſucceſſion, The <hi>Calendar</hi> muſt ſubſiſt in a <hi>Monarchy</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> as is given in thoſe <hi>Viſions,</hi> and a <hi>Monarchy</hi> that ſurvives in that Succeſſion at this very day.</p>
               <p>It muſt be a <hi>Monarchy</hi> of ſuch a Succeſſion, becauſe the Two <hi>Viſions</hi> do plainly import, and declare ſuch a Succeſſion, as cloſely connected, and conjoyn'd, as the members of a Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Body from Head to Foot, and as the parts of Time from part to part are conveyed in each Month and Year; As therefore the member of any other Body, the Legs, or Foot of a Foreign Body, cannot ſupply the place of ſuch a member in this, or that Body that it is not of, no more can any other <hi>Monarchy</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſupply the place of any of theſe <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies,</hi> that are not Joyn'd in the juſt order, and ſcituation of each <hi>Monarchy,</hi> with reſpect one to another in this <hi>Image;</hi> or any more, then a Month, or a day taken from another Year, or Month, can ſupport the Courſe of this Year, or Month.</p>
               <p>And it muſt be a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> that ſurvives at this day, or elſe it cannot be a <hi>Monarchy</hi> of the <hi>Image;</hi> For ſuch a <hi>Monarchy</hi> muſt whatever it be, ſuſtain the Courſe of Time to the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt</hi> as before deſcribed; which no <hi>Monarchy</hi> can do, that is not even now extant, becauſe the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> hath not yet appeared.</p>
               <p>Now no <hi>Monarchy</hi> can anſwer <hi>Prophecy</hi> in theſe Two points, but onely the <hi>Roman Monarchy;</hi> For all <hi>Hiſtory</hi> agrees, no <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Alexanders</hi> proper and perſonal <hi>Kingdom</hi> deſcrib'd in this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> but the <hi>Grecian diviſion</hi> of that his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which beſides it was <hi>Grecian</hi> ſtill, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106747:19"/> cannot be ſaid to ſucceed the <hi>Grecian Monarchy;</hi> beſides this, Is does not remain in that ſucceſſion at this day, that it ought to do, to ſupport the Courſe of Time as given in this <hi>Prophecy;</hi> That <hi>Grecian diviſion</hi> therefore muſt be reputed one <hi>Third Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> with <hi>Alexanders,</hi> All <hi>Grecian,</hi> though of another Model from <hi>Alexanders;</hi> Yet ſuch as <hi>Prophecy</hi> gave it, as of one in <hi>Alexander,</hi> and as divided into <hi>Four</hi> after Him, and then more Remarkably into <hi>Two;</hi> If that be ſo, then no other <hi>Monarchy,</hi> but what ſucceeded that <hi>Grecian Monarchy</hi> as ſo divided, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally into the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>North,</hi> call'd the <hi>Greco Syrian,</hi> or <hi>Seleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidean,</hi> and the <hi>King of the South,</hi> the <hi>Egyptian,</hi> or <hi>Lagidean Kingdom,</hi> can be the <hi>Monarchy</hi> we deſign; Becauſe, as hath been ſaid, it muſt be in immediate ſucceſſion to the Foregoing <hi>Monarchies;</hi> ſo that any ſuppoſable <hi>Grecian Monarchy,</hi> or <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> under the <hi>Turk</hi> at this day, that hath come in, out of the orderly courſe of <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and not of ſuch a <hi>Figure,</hi> as this <hi>Prophecy</hi> hath given it, can be the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> we are in purſuit of, although ſuch <hi>Monarchy</hi> may continue, till the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall ſucceed.</p>
               <p>But now how exactly does the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> Anſwet in the point of Succeſſion; For firſt, the very <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Daniel</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Kingdom of Alexander</hi> ſhould be <hi>divided</hi> to the <hi>four Winds,</hi> and then that it <hi>ſhould be pull'd up for others, beſides Thoſe;</hi> It was <hi>divided</hi> for the <hi>Four,</hi> and yet remain'd the ſame;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. 8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. 4.</note> But it was to be <hi>pull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</hi> up for <hi>others,</hi> ſo as to ceaſe to be a <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy;</hi> Now thoſe <hi>others</hi> beſides muſt be they, whoever they were, who <hi>devour'd,</hi> and <hi>ſtamp'd on the Reſidue</hi> with <hi>Legs of Iron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 40.</note> as in the <hi>Image,</hi> with <hi>Feet of Iron</hi> as by the <hi>fourth Beaſt,</hi> in the <hi>viſion</hi> of the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and they muſt be <hi>Romans.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For it is very well known, that the <hi>Grecian Partite Monarchy</hi> came near to the <hi>days of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in the Fleſh,</hi> and yet not ſo near, as to make any fair Interpretation of ſo much, as the <hi>God of Heaven</hi> ſetting up the <hi>Spiritual Kingdom</hi> of <hi>the Goſpel</hi> in the <hi>days</hi> of thoſe <hi>Kings,</hi> pourtrayed in the <hi>Image,</hi> if that <hi>divided Grecian Kingdom</hi> had been the <hi>Fourth,</hi> and <hi>Laſt;</hi> and yet again ſo near, that it is moſt known in all <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> that no other <hi>Monarchy</hi> could come between that <hi>Grecian Monarchy,</hi> and the <hi>Birth of Chriſt,</hi> but the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> onely, ſo that if the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Stone</hi> out of the <hi>Mountain,</hi> had been onely a <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Kingdom;</hi> Yet ſtill the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> muſt be the <hi>fourth.</hi> This ſeems order'd as on purpoſe to divert Interpreters from
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106747:19"/> the <hi>divided Grecian Kingdom</hi> as the <hi>fourth Monarchy,</hi> and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily to ſhape them on the <hi>Romans;</hi> And it is moſt evident, not onely in all <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> that the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> was then come to its <hi>Zenith</hi> in the <hi>Reign of Auguſtus,</hi> but eſpecially in the ſacred <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> for there came out a <hi>Decree</hi> from <hi>Caeſar Auguſtus,</hi> at that very Time<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that <hi>our Lord</hi> was <hi>Born.</hi> And that it particularly cover'd the <hi>Jewiſh Nation</hi> the onely <hi>People of God</hi> at that Time, to which <hi>Prophecy</hi> had ſo ſingular an Eye; And the <hi>decree</hi> from <hi>Auguſtus</hi> was, to Tax or deſcribe the whole <hi>Oecumen,</hi> or <hi>Habitable World</hi> as by the poll; Was not this a <hi>Fourth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> from the <hi>Babylonian,</hi> the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> the <hi>Grecian,</hi> and was it not <hi>Roman &amp;c?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But further to make it more known, at the death and <hi>Crucifixion</hi> of our Lord, The <hi>Sentence</hi> was given by <hi>Pilate</hi> the <hi>Roman Subſtitute,</hi> or <hi>Governour,</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> declared on the occaſion; They had no <hi>power to put any one to death.</hi> So that the <hi>Roman <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> at that Time, is become an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith, Crucified under Pontius Pilate,</hi> declares the <hi>Roman fourth Monarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now that the <hi>Evangelical Kingdom</hi> by the <hi>Birth, Miniſtry, Death, Reſurrection</hi> and <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>ſet up by the God of Heaven,</hi> that we might not think, This <hi>Spiritual Kingdom</hi> was the <hi>Fulfilling</hi> of <hi>Prophecy;</hi> There was no <hi>Breaking of this fourth Kingdom</hi> by it, nor of any other <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as is Foretold in theſe <hi>Viſions;</hi> But <hi>Chriſt,</hi> altho' he own'd himſelf <hi>King of the Jews,</hi> yet<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 18. 36.</note> declar'd his <hi>Kingdom not of this World,</hi> nor <hi>from hence;</hi> That is, not from below, but to come down in the <hi>Jeruſalem from above;</hi> He did not therefore diſannul <hi>Caeſar's Kingdom,</hi> nay He <hi>Eſtabliſh'd</hi> it by that Command, <hi>Render unto Caeſar &amp;c.</hi> as it were in care, that <hi>Prophecy</hi> might be <hi>Fulfill'd</hi> concerning that <hi>fourth Monarchy;</hi> Agreeably after the <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> of <hi>Chriſt, Paul,</hi> as directed by<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 25. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> God, made that Famous <hi>Appeal to Caeſar,</hi> and all the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> taught ſubjection to the <hi>Roman Powers.</hi> This ſhews, a <hi>ſpiritual Kingdom</hi> was not the deſign of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> but an <hi>Imperial;</hi> For when <hi>Constantine,</hi> as an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Emperour</hi> declared for <hi>Christ;</hi> It was then ſaid, with high <hi>Doxologies,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of our God<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 10</note> is come, as an <hi>Emblem</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> yet to come.</p>
               <p>Thus far I have then undeniably, as I muſt be Bold to ſay, Reaſon'd; That ſeeing the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> is not yet come, ſome of theſe <hi>four Monarchies</hi> muſt be in Being; For they are a <hi>Calendar</hi> to it; that it can be onely the <hi>fourth Monarchy,</hi> that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106747:20"/> is thus in Being; For the <hi>Babylonion,</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Grecian,</hi> which were the three firſt even by name in <hi>Daniels prophecy,</hi> are paſt and gone off, as in the ſucceſſive <hi>Dominion</hi> of Each; The <hi>Roman</hi> then ſucceeding the <hi>Grecian</hi> and being ſo <hi>Great a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> after it, as hath appeared, muſt be the <hi>Fourth.</hi> And even becauſe, it is the <hi>Fourth,</hi> it muſt be in Being, becauſe the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Christ</hi> is not yet come; And it muſt therefore continue in Being, till that <hi>Kingdom</hi> comes.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, we may aſſuredly Argue, that as the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> was in Being, as an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> ſince the <hi>days of Chriſt,</hi> ſo by the general knowledge we have of the World; It continues in Being in the <hi>Roman Papacy,</hi> and the <hi>Kings</hi> yet devoted to it: It is therefore certain, the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Christ</hi> is not yet come, as it is to come according to this <hi>Prophecy.</hi> And thus much then we are ſure of before hand, that we cannot ſtir off from this very <hi>Roman Monarchy,</hi> till we come to the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> For if it were ever a <hi>fourth Monarchy,</hi> there is no <hi>Monarchy</hi> after, nor beſide it, according to this <hi>ſure word of Prophecy,</hi> that can be a <hi>Remaining Calendar</hi> to us to that <hi>Kingdom;</hi> Becauſe whatever <hi>Monarchy</hi> was the <hi>fourth Monarchy,</hi> muſt continue to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> we muſt therefore run upon it, as upon an <hi>Ecliptick Line</hi> given us, from which there muſt be no variation.</p>
               <p>And if we can hold the <hi>Footing</hi> we have hitherto found in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> by the <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſucceding it, and to which the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> leads us, and in Agreement with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Hiſtory,</hi> we ſhall certainly come down with the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar</hi> we are upon, to our own Times, and know how near we are to the End of it, and ſo to the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſit. </seg>3</label> I come therefore to the third Poſition, There is ſuch an <hi>Idea</hi> of the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> in the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as will moſt exactly Correſpond the <hi>Prophecy of Daniel,</hi> in concert with moſt Agreed, and Indiſputed <hi>History,</hi> and ſhew us, whereabouts we are in this <hi>Calendar,</hi> and how near to the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But before I come to compare this <hi>Idea</hi> with the <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and moſt known <hi>Roman History,</hi> and thereby to Educe the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendar,</hi> as it goes on, I muſt obſerve by way of premiſal theſe Three Things.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106747:20"/> 1. That the <hi>Prophecy of Daniel</hi> does not name the <hi>fourth Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> nor tell us what <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or what <hi>National Cognomination</hi> it hath, as it hath in ſome part of <hi>Daniels Prophecy</hi> (as hath already appear'd) told us, that the <hi>Head of Gold</hi> or <hi>firſt Kingdom</hi> was the <hi>Babylonion,</hi> that the <hi>Babylonian Kingdom</hi> was divided to the <hi>Medes and Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom</hi> therefore neceſſarily after it; And the <hi>He Goat of Greece</hi> was <hi>moved with choler</hi> againſt the <hi>Ram</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and ſtamp'd upon Him, that is ſubdued Him, and therefore that muſt be the <hi>Third Kingdom of Braſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All this notwithſtanding, it never diſtinguiſhes the <hi>Fourth Kingdom</hi> by its name; Herein the <hi>Apocalyptic Proyhecy</hi> agrees; It very plainly, as we ſhall ſee, deſcribes a <hi>Monarchy</hi> or <hi>Kingdom,</hi> yet it never expreſſes to us what <hi>Kingdom</hi> it was; As <hi>Daniel</hi> tells us, the <hi>fourth Kingdom</hi> in the <hi>Image</hi> is in the <hi>Legs</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> and <hi>Feet,</hi> and <hi>Toes part of Iron, part of Clay;</hi> and in the <hi>Viſions</hi> of the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> the <hi>fourth Beaſt</hi> with its <hi>Feet of Iron,</hi> its <hi>Horns</hi> and its <hi>little Horn</hi> was the <hi>fourth Kingdom</hi> upon <hi>Earth,</hi> and yet never ſays, in any part of his <hi>Prophecy,</hi> what <hi>Kingdom</hi> it was; even ſo the <hi>Revelation</hi> deſcribes a <hi>Dragon,</hi> giving His <hi>Throne, Power,</hi> and <hi>Great Authority</hi> to a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> to whom <hi>Power was given over all Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, People, Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> and therefore muſt have a <hi>Great Kingdom,</hi> yet it never declares, of what Nation or People, this <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhould take its name.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, if it be ſo evident, as it hath been, that no <hi>Kingdom</hi> came between the <hi>Grecian</hi> and the <hi>Romans,</hi> no not ſo much, as any <hi>Spiritual,</hi> or <hi>Evangelical Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as hath evidently appear'd by expreſs <hi>Scripture Hiſtory;</hi> It is even <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Demonstration,</hi> the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> was the <hi>fourth Monarchy,</hi> and therefore muſt be the continuing <hi>Monarchy,</hi> until it, and all the reſt ſhall be <hi>Broken</hi> by the <hi>Kingdom of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There muſt be therefore ſome great Reaſon, and which <hi>Prophecy</hi> would have us take notice of, why it Throws ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvedly ſuch a veil of Secreſie over this <hi>Monarchy;</hi> And we may plainly find, it is for the ſake of the laſt part of this <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> which is in a <hi>mystery,</hi> an <hi>Apostaſie</hi> comming out of a <hi>mystery of Iniquity,</hi> a <hi>City</hi> in the <hi>mystery</hi> of an <hi>Apostate Adulterous Church</hi> and an <hi>Imperial Idolatrous power</hi> in the <hi>mystery</hi> of a <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Supremacy:</hi> For the ſake of which laſt ſtate of this <hi>Monarchy</hi> the firſt is not diſcloſed; Becauſe if the laſt were joyn'd, as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> hath joyn'd it; The diſcloſing the firſt, would diſcloſe the laſt; and that both ſhould be joyn'd, the very <hi>Prophetick</hi> frames require.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106747:21"/>
               <p> Thus the Covering this <hi>fourth Kingdom</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation,</hi> doing the ſame in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> it deſcribes, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues they are both one and the ſame <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and that He that would underſtand them, muſt have <hi>Wiſedom,</hi> as the <hi>Prophecy</hi> admoniſhes to lay things together, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them; For if this ſtate had been openly Foretold, the very opportunity and Action of this <hi>Apostaſie</hi> had been ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd. The very Concealment is therefore to the prudent conſiderer a diſcoverery and an aſſurance, what <hi>Kingdom</hi> it is; And the unwary, which are the multitude; And even the wiſe, under the Enchantment of the growing <hi>Apostaſie</hi> knew little of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The frame of the <hi>Divine prophecy</hi> is herein very admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and obſervable, in that there is no determinate form aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd to the <hi>fourth Beast,</hi> whereas the <hi>first</hi> had the <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>a Lyon,</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> of <hi>a Bear,</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> of <hi>a Leopard,</hi> the <hi>Fourth</hi> had no Form at all aſcrib'd to it.</p>
               <p>Now the Reaſon of this is, partly, that the Ballance of <hi>Prophecy</hi> might be held even, between the Concealment of its mind to the generality, and the poſſible diſcovery of it by the wiſe, and conſidering Reſeacher of <hi>Prophecy.</hi> If there had been a form given in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the ſame form given in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> it had been too open, and plain a diſcovery: If there had been one form given in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and another in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> it had made a confuſion ſo great, that even the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and prudent ſearcher of <hi>Prophecy</hi> could not have Broken through, except there had been ſuch an Expoſition, as is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the change as it were of Scenes, as of the <hi>Perſian Ram</hi> in <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. which was Emblem'd by a <hi>Bear, c.</hi> 7. and of the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian He Goat, c.</hi> 8. which was as a <hi>Leopard, c.</hi> 7. and ſuch an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition had been too open in this caſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Daniel</hi> therefore gives no ſhape at all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Prophecy</hi> in the <hi>Revelation</hi> would have a peculiar reaſon to give the <hi>fourth Beast,</hi> in its firſt ſtate or <hi>Legs of Iron,</hi> and a <hi>Beast</hi> with <hi>Iron Teeth,</hi> the form of a <hi>Dragon,</hi> which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon had not been ripe in <hi>Daniels</hi> Time, as we ſhall ſee preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; And it had great Reaſon to give the ſame <hi>Roman Beast</hi> in its laſt ſtate, [peculiarly to ſhew its ſucceſſion to the <hi>Three first Beasts,]</hi> firſt the form of a <hi>Leopard,</hi> as in the <hi>Belly</hi> and <hi>Thighs,</hi> becauſe of its immediate ſucceſſion to the <hi>Grecian Monarchy,</hi> as it was <hi>Roman;</hi> And then as by the <hi>Grecian Monarchy,</hi> it ſucceeded
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106747:21"/> the <hi>Perſian Monarchy,</hi> it is ſaid to have the <hi>Feet of a Bear;</hi> Eſpecially, as the <hi>Bears Fore-feet</hi> are its ſtrength, and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Arms in the Body</hi> of a Man, and ſo agree with the <hi>Arms</hi> in the <hi>ſecond Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Image;</hi> and then it had the <hi>Mouth,</hi> or <hi>Head</hi> of a <hi>Lyon</hi> reſembling the <hi>Head of Gold;</hi> whereby its ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion by the <hi>Graecian</hi> and <hi>Perſian</hi> to the <hi>Babylonian</hi> is aſſured. And thus the <hi>Calendar</hi> of Time in theſe ſucceſſive <hi>Monarchies</hi> is firmly eſtabliſhed, and brought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> down and Recapitulated, as in the laſt ſtate of the <hi>Fourth Kingdom;</hi> both as in the <hi>Image,</hi> and as in the <hi>Viſion of the Beaſts;</hi> wherein alſo it is to Expire: Apply further to the <hi>Fourth Roman Kingdom</hi> in its laſt ſtate the <hi>Legs of Iron,</hi> all other parts of the <hi>Image</hi> being already diſpos'd, in the <hi>Dragon,</hi> giving his name <hi>[Beaſt]</hi> abſolute, and without any <hi>Form,</hi> which the <hi>Revelation</hi> aſcribes ſo generally, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically to the laſt ſtate of the <hi>Roman Beaſt</hi> in the <hi>Head of Ten Horns,</hi> as one with the whole <hi>Roman Beaſt,</hi> and alſo with the <hi>Image;</hi> and you have the <hi>Calendar</hi> of the <hi>Four</hi> ſucceſſive <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies</hi> brought down to this laſt <hi>Roman ſtate</hi> in an <hi>Emblem</hi> ſo lively and certain, that no wit of Man could have Exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitated; Onely the <hi>divine Spirit</hi> hath found it, which is a great Aſſurance of <hi>Prophecy</hi> in this matter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is yet to be Remark'd, There muſt needs be many conſiderable variations betwixt the <hi>Prophecy of Daniel,</hi> and of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> Becauſe both Time was ſo much further and higher advanc'd at that Time, and alſo becauſe it may well be expected, The <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> may accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the excellent Light of the Goſpel throughout it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell the <hi>Revelation of the Old Teſtament,</hi> or the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Prophet Daniel;</hi> This is to be well ſettled in our Thoughts, that we may not be ſtumbled or offended, when in after parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars we obſerve the Variation.</p>
               <p>And firſt there is this general variation, that the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> knowing, that the <hi>Three firſt Kingdoms</hi> were paſs'd off before the days, even any of ſo much, as the very firſt of the days of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> gives no Repreſentation of them any further, then as They are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulated in the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> So that the whole <hi>Apocalyptick Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> appertains onely to, and gives the Schemes of the ſtate of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> after it had ſubdued all the <hi>Three firſt Kingdoms</hi> under it ſelf, and become the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> of the World. And this it does with Relation to the <hi>Church</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106747:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106747:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106747:23"/> 
                  <hi>of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as its principal object and aim, which is a moſt remarkable Conſideration, Aſſuring us, the <hi>Revelation</hi> is a Continuation, and further Explication of what remain'd unfulfill'd of <hi>Daniel's Prophecy,</hi> from thoſe very firſt days of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> or when They began.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>That we may then go on with the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Daniel;</hi> As the <hi>Calendar</hi> we are upon, was moſt declaredly brought down to the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> at the <hi>Birth of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> So there are ſeveral Periods of the <hi>Calendar</hi> from that Time, wherein the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> Agree moſt Illuſtriouſly with <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> in Relation to the <hi>Roman Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Period. </seg>1</label> It is moſt notorious notwithſtanding the <hi>Birth, Death, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtolical preaching;</hi> The <hi>Roman Empire</hi> continued one, and continued <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan</hi> in the ſupreme <hi>Powers,</hi> and in the Body and Bulk of the People; From hence it is evident, the <hi>Calendar</hi> was not Run out, becauſe the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> did not onely, not <hi>Fill the Earth,</hi> but did not conſume other Kingdoms, as it is firſt to do, before it <hi>Fills the Earth;</hi> And therefore no Interpretation of <hi>Filling</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> with the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> or <hi>Spiritual Kingdom</hi> can ſtand Good: And further, the <hi>Calendar</hi> was not come down to the <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> nor into the <hi>Head of the Beaſt,</hi> diſhevelling it ſelf into <hi>Ten Horns,</hi> as it muſt in its laſt ſtate; But during the <hi>Pagan Empire,</hi> it remained perfectly <hi>One;</hi> and therefore was not in its laſt ſtate.</p>
               <p>Now of this <hi>Pagan Empire,</hi> Two Things are moſt known.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> having <hi>come into the Fleſh</hi> under the <hi>Roman Monarchy, Sathan</hi> the <hi>old Serpent</hi> and <hi>Dragon</hi> being aware, that that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which ſhall utterly deſtroy his <hi>Kingdom</hi> was entred; He as a <hi>Dragon</hi> watch'd that <hi>manly Birth</hi> to deſtroy it, if it were poſſible firſt; He then inhabiting the <hi>Pagan Roman Empire,</hi> it is fitly Reſembled to a <hi>Dragon</hi> in regard of that <hi>Spirit,</hi> that inhabited it by a moſt particular influence over it; And becauſe when <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> began to ſpread it ſelf in that <hi>Empire</hi> in a multitude of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> It had a Jealous eye over it, and over the <hi>Empire,</hi> it might raiſe; Therefore by <hi>Ten</hi> ſo known and Famous <hi>Perſecutions</hi> it endeavour'd as a <hi>Dragon</hi> to <hi>devour it,</hi> and to ſurprize that <hi>Supreme Monarch Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who ſhould Rule the <hi>Nations with a Rod of Iron,</hi> which the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> compar'd to a <hi>Travelling woman</hi> was to <hi>Bring forth;</hi> Herein the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> is Reſembled to <hi>Pharoh</hi> the <hi>Egyptian King of Old,</hi> who fearing the overgrowth of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as a <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106747:23"/> lying in the <hi>Nile</hi> waited to <hi>devour it,</hi> by <hi>Killing the Male Children;</hi> And thus <hi>Herod</hi> the <hi>Roman Vaſſal,</hi> though <hi>King of the Jews, watch'd</hi> to have <hi>devour'd Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Incarnate King,</hi> who ſhall ſit on the <hi>Throne of his Father David,</hi> and of whoſe <hi>Kingdom, there ſhall be no End.</hi> Thus admirable is the Concinnity and Agreement between the <hi>Pagan Emperors</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> that was to be a <hi>Spiritual Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon.</hi> How plain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the <hi>Calendar</hi> of the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> in this particular to the very laſt of it, as <hi>Pagan; Diocleſian</hi> and the other laſt <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Emperors</hi> being among the Perſecutors of the firſt rank, and therefore we muſt needs be certain whereabout the Time of the <hi>Calendar</hi> then was. For we know this ſtate laſted about 300 Years after the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and in the clearneſs and particularity of this, the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> exceeds the old. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider further this <hi>Imperial power</hi> with relation to the reſt of the World, and it was <hi>Salvage, Dreadful,</hi> and <hi>Terrible,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſtyles it, and as the <hi>Revelation</hi> ſtyles it, as a <hi>Dragon, devouring</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming</hi> all other powers as <hi>with Iron</hi> Teeth, and ſtamping on them as with <hi>Legs of Iron,</hi> on which account the <hi>Dragon</hi> is ſaid, as it were, to <hi>ſweep down</hi> the <hi>Third part of the Stars,</hi> or other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 4.</note> and powers of the World with its <hi>Syrma,</hi> its Tail or Train of Power, and enlarged <hi>Empire;</hi> And in that, it is call'd the <hi>Third part of the Stars</hi> It thus <hi>ſweeps down;</hi> It is agreeable, that its Succeſſion to the <hi>Third,</hi> or <hi>Graecian Empire</hi> ſhould be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted, which it ſo particularly <hi>drew down;</hi> from whence the <hi>Third</hi> or <hi>Third part</hi> becomes in this <hi>Prophecy</hi> a Cypher or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Character of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> Whether in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> the moſt proper peculiar <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> or in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> that affected alſo to be call'd <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> even as <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople, New Rome;</hi> and Theſe Two are therefore in theſe <hi>Prophetick Hieroglyphics</hi> call'd <hi>Two Wings</hi> of the <hi>one Great Eagle</hi> or <hi>Roman Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that we may know the <hi>Prophetick Calendar</hi> was taken care of in this <hi>Pagan ſtate</hi> of <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> the whole <hi>Roman Beaſt,</hi> that is ſaid to be diverſe from the <hi>other Beaſts</hi> in regard of its many, and more Eminently <hi>Seven forms of Government,</hi> very ſtrange to the other <hi>Three Kingdoms</hi> before it, eſpecially in the laſt, the <hi>Papal Supremacy,</hi> was pictured as with <hi>Seven Heads, Heads</hi> of that <hi>City,</hi> that when St. <hi>John</hi> wrote the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, Reign'd over the Kings of the Earth,</hi> and therefore could be no other, then <hi>Rome.</hi> And it is particularly ſaid, <hi>Five were</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106747:24"/> 
                  <hi>Fallen, One</hi> then was; which we know, could be no other, then the <hi>Pagan Emperors;</hi> Thus exact is the <hi>Calendar,</hi> or account of Time, till <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> under whom the <hi>Empire</hi> became <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> Becauſe all <hi>Hiſtory</hi> Agrees whereabouts in Time it was.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Period. </seg>2</label> The ſecond <hi>Period</hi> of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> ſince the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> according to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> and moſt known in <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> is the <hi>Chriſtian Roman Empire</hi> under <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and his ſucceſſors; And the Time is very well known in <hi>Hiſtory</hi> and Agreed, whereabouts it was.</p>
               <p>But it muſt be acknowledged, this <hi>Period</hi> or change of the <hi>Empire</hi> from <hi>Pagan</hi> to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is not at all ſhaddowed in <hi>Daniel's Prophecy;</hi> in either of the Two <hi>Viſions</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> or of the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> it hath no Lines, or Mentions.</p>
               <p>And the reaſon is very clear, and plain; For when the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> was pleas'd to give a <hi>Calendar</hi> of Time by Two <hi>Viſions,</hi> Both repreſenting a <hi>Monarchic Frame,</hi> though of <hi>Four Monarchies;</hi> Yet they were but <hi>One</hi> in a <hi>Beſtian</hi> enmity, and Contrariety to the great <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Chriſtian Monarchy,</hi> that was given for a ſhort ſpace, as an <hi>Emblem,</hi> ſhade or <hi>Specimen,</hi> though but a dark one, of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> could have no proper place there, but muſt have confus'd the Frame.</p>
               <p>But as if it were on purpoſe to compenſate the ſilence of the <hi>Chriſtian Monarchy</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and becauſe it may ſeem a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuer in the <hi>Beſtian Calendar</hi> of <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and in that Frame of <hi>Four,</hi> and yet but <hi>One;</hi> and eſpecially in the Two ſtates of the one <hi>Roman Fourth Monarchy;</hi> The <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> is much the more careful, and Abundant, and ſeems as it were to make Amends for this Appearing violati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that whereas all the <hi>Four Monarchies</hi> are as one <hi>Beſtian Monarchy,</hi> or <hi>Image,</hi> and the <hi>Fourth Monarchy,</hi> but <hi>one Beaſt</hi> There comes in as <hi>Ex improviſo,</hi> as unforeſeen a <hi>Chriſtian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> in the midſt of that Laſt <hi>Fourth Monarchy,</hi> and ſpoils the whole Frame; and diſturbs eſpecially the <hi>Calendar</hi> as it may ſeem, but it will be found much otherwiſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For there is, as I may Reverently call it, a <hi>Prophetical</hi> ſcene in the <hi>New Teſtament Prophecy</hi> on purpoſe to Repreſent a <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Empire caſting</hi> out the <hi>Pagan,</hi> in the <hi>Woman</hi> the <hi>Church bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth</hi> after moſt painful <hi>Throws, Sufferings</hi> and <hi>Martyrdoms</hi> a <hi>Manly Child, caught up to the Throne of God,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon Cast</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:106747:24"/> 
                  <hi>down,</hi> and and a ſolemn <hi>Doxology</hi> upon it; <hi>Now is the Kingdom of our God come,</hi> This was a great <hi>Emblem</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> as it is an <hi>Imperial Kingdom</hi> and not a <hi>Spiritual</hi> onely; And this is ſo plain, that no Interpreter doubts it of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Roman Empire,</hi> nor of the Admirableneſs of the <hi>Emblem</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a diſtinct account of the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> in its <hi>Seven Heads,</hi> which were <hi>crowned Heads,</hi> or Formes of <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Government,</hi> and all <hi>Beſtian,</hi> or <hi>Idolatrous, full of the names of Blaſphemy.</hi> And they muſt needs be of <hi>Rome</hi> that was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alought by them, becauſe <hi>Rome</hi> without diſpute was the <hi>City,</hi> that <hi>then Reign'd over the Kings of the Earth,</hi> as <hi>It is ſaid Revel.</hi> 17. <hi>ult.</hi> Among theſe There is <hi>one King,</hi> that is plainly ſtyl'd <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be a <hi>King of another ſort, No Head;</hi> For there were but <hi>Seven,</hi> and the <hi>Eighth</hi> is expreſly to be <hi>One of the Seven, viz. Heads;</hi> So the <hi>Seventh King</hi> could be no <hi>Head,</hi> for <hi>Five</hi> had been <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Fallen,</hi> and <hi>One</hi> then <hi>was,</hi> and the <hi>Eighth</hi> was of the <hi>Seven,</hi> therefore the <hi>Seventh</hi> could be no <hi>Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Room, therefore of this <hi>King</hi> in the <hi>Calendar</hi> is <hi>Embo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limean,</hi> and perfectly <hi>Intercalar;</hi> And it is ſo plac'd, that it muſt be, as I may ſo ſpeak in the <hi>Seventh Stall</hi> of thoſe <hi>Kings,</hi> immediately after the <hi>Pagan,</hi> as All <hi>Hiſtory</hi> knows, the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Empire</hi> was, and juſt before the <hi>Eighth King,</hi> or <hi>Papacy,</hi> as <hi>Hiſtory</hi> alſo knows, the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> was in ſuch a ſenſe, as <hi>Prophecy</hi> will guide us unto.</p>
               <p>But that it might be known to make no great Infraction in the <hi>Beſtian Calendar,</hi> It is ſaid <hi>Emphatically,</hi> He <hi>must</hi> or He<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> ought in regard of his unnaturalneſs to the <hi>Beſtian Monarchy,</hi> according to <hi>Prophecy</hi> to <hi>continue but a ſhort Space;</hi> that is but about a hundred and fifty Years.</p>
               <p>Can now any care be greater with Relation to the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Empire,</hi> that we may know it was; That it was by way of Interpoſal, as in the midſt of the <hi>Roman Beſtian Monarchy,</hi> and the very Time, when, and where it came ſo between, and the general Scantling of Time, it laſted?</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Apostle Paul,</hi> according to the <hi>wiſdom given to Him,</hi> diſcourſing of theſe Things ſhews, that the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> that was to have its Times, its <hi>own proper Times,</hi> could not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain its proper Times, even according to his own <hi>Oath,</hi> till an <hi>Apostaſie</hi> according to <hi>Daniel's Prophecy,</hi> had brought forth<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 15.</note> the <hi>Man of ſin,</hi> and He had had his <hi>own Times;</hi> and therefore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106747:25"/> the <hi>Apostle</hi> is moſt vehement upon <hi>Christians,</hi> not to expect that day of <hi>Christ</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s <hi>Kingdom,</hi> till then; For he knew the <hi>Oath</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>of Christ</hi> was abſolutely againſt it; There ſhall be <hi>Time, Times, Half Time firſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> though <hi>Chriſt be come into the Fleſh,</hi> though the <hi>Roman</hi> laſt <hi>Monarchy</hi> be now in its Courſe, which may quicken your Expectations, yet expect not that <hi>day of Chriſt,</hi> till after the <hi>Times of the Man of Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that you may not expect thoſe Times too ſoon, Know that God hath Interpos'd a Curb, an Hold faſt, that ſhall keep back the <hi>Man of ſin,</hi> till his <hi>own</hi> juſt <hi>Times;</hi> For the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity</hi> is now at work, and would bring him forth before his Time, but there is a <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> that will <hi>Hold faſt its Time, and be before Him,</hi> and will caſt him on his juſt point of Time, that his <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time</hi> aſſign'd him by that <hi>Oath of Christ</hi> may ſo end, that the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> may ſucceed in its proper <hi>Time</hi> immediately after the <hi>Times of the Man of ſin,</hi> which had not God thus Interpos'd a <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> and the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> had continued no longer, it would not have done according to the great Times deſign'd by God; <hi>Set</hi> in, and by his own <hi>Power</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> diſcourſe the <hi>Calendar</hi> is not weakned, but ſtrengthn'd, and the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Times, and of all Times, ſince he writ, may be led through the ſtages of Time ſince the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> As if the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſhould ſay, Watch the <hi>Pagan Empire,</hi> when it ends; For after that, there ſhall be a preternatural <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Succeſſor of another kind, a <hi>Chriſtian Emperour</hi> who keeps back the Succeſſion of the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> that ought to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed immediately, after the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> according to the Courſe of nature; But yet it will not diſorder but keep Tight the whole <hi>Calendar,</hi> the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> ſhall after that <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> be <hi>Revealed juſt in his own Time;</hi> and whenever the Times of the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> ſhall end, expect the day, <hi>comming</hi> and <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall <hi>conſume</hi> him with the <hi>Approach of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,</hi> and <hi>Aboliſh</hi> Him with the <hi>Brightneſs of his own Appearance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the <hi>Reſurrection of Chriſt</hi> then, the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> laſts to the <hi>Christian Empire,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> till the <hi>days</hi> of the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> The <hi>Times</hi> of <hi>Antichrist</hi> till the <hi>Times of Christ</hi> and of <hi>his Kingdom,</hi> an exact, and an eaſie <hi>Calendar,</hi> Solid, and Subſtantial; And ſeeing we all know the <hi>Pagan</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106747:25"/> 
                  <hi>Empire</hi> is paſt, That <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> we ſpeak of, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> and of his ſucceſſors, till <hi>done out of the way,</hi> had its Courſe, and ceas'd; if we can but know then, how long the <hi>Times of the Man of Sin</hi> laſt, we muſt needs know, how long it is to the <hi>Kingdom of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is moſt plain, this <hi>Holder back</hi> is a very Elegant Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of a <hi>Chriſtian Emperor,</hi> that ſtay'd the Succeſſion of the <hi>Man of Sin</hi> after the <hi>Pagan Empire,</hi> till his own juſt <hi>Times,</hi> and no longer, though the Con-naturalneſs of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſm</hi> was ſo Great, and the <hi>Miſtery</hi> of <hi>Iniquity</hi> then at work to attemper one to the other, that he might very well have come juſt after <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and <hi>Paganiſm</hi> have merg'd into it; but God had decreed a <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> between, a <hi>Specimen</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> (even as in <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> firſt <hi>Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Kingdom there were thoſe ſudden Appearances of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Kingdom in his Acknowledgments of God) which <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi> ſupplanting, it made him the more exceedingly, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. As a further Care of <hi>Prophecy</hi> concerning the <hi>Calendar of Time,</hi> and the Interpoſal of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> it gives us this plain Account of the State of the <hi>Roman Beſtian Empire,</hi> during that <hi>Chriſtian Empire, viz.</hi> That by Reaſon of the Chriſtian Empire, that was not <hi>Beſtian,</hi> nor any of thoſe <hi>Heads.</hi> The <hi>Roman Beaſt</hi> lay <hi>wounded;</hi> and it is ſaid, the <hi>Wound</hi> was a <hi>Wound</hi> unto <hi>Death,</hi> and a <hi>Wound</hi> with a <hi>Sword,</hi> and a <hi>Wound in one of the Heads;</hi> and that we may take further notice of the <hi>Wound,</hi> It is ſaid, <hi>His deadly Wound was healed,</hi> and he did <hi>Live.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev. c.</hi> 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now this <hi>Wound</hi> hath been much miſtaken by ſome Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, as if it were the <hi>Wound</hi> given by the <hi>Barbarous Nations,</hi> invading the <hi>Empire,</hi> of which in the next particular we ſhall find another Account; But it is very plain, becauſe the <hi>Wound</hi> was in <hi>one of the Heads,</hi> and that the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> upon which the <hi>Barbarians</hi> fell moſt peculiarly, was none of the <hi>Heads;</hi> It muſt needs be, that the <hi>Wound</hi> intended was on the <hi>Pagan Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Head,</hi> whom <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius the Great,</hi> beſides other the Chriſtian Emperors ſo remarkably <hi>Wounded,</hi> even unto <hi>Death,</hi> that It never recovered in a pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Pagan</hi> but only in the <hi>Pagan Anti-chriſtian Head.</hi> To which, becauſe of the Congenialneſs of the one to the other, the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> is ſaid in <hi>prophetic Language</hi> to deliver his <hi>Throne, Power,</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106747:26"/> 
                  <hi>Authority</hi> by way of <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and to <hi>live</hi> and to be <hi>worſhip'd in Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that though we are not plainly told, it was the <hi>Draconic Head,</hi> which we found to be the <hi>Pagan Empire,</hi> was <hi>wounded,</hi> yet in that it is ſaid, The <hi>Dragon</hi> was <hi>caſt out of Heaven;</hi> that the <hi>Dragon</hi> gave his <hi>Power, Throne,</hi> and <hi>Great Authority</hi> to the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and was <hi>worſhip'd</hi> in Him, the <hi>World wondring</hi> after the <hi>Beaſt.</hi> There is nothing more plain, then that it was the <hi>Pagan Dragon</hi> that was <hi>wounded</hi> by the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> coming next after it, and <hi>healed</hi> in the <hi>Beaſt</hi> coming in as a <hi>Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This then was the <hi>Wound,</hi> that the <hi>ſixth Head,</hi> as <hi>Pagan, Idolatrous,</hi> and <hi>bloody,</hi> could not maintain its <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and <hi>Imperialiſm,</hi> till the <hi>Antichriſtian Head</hi> ſucceeds it; but an <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> a <hi>Chriſtian Empire, prophetic</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> rooting out <hi>Pagan Idolatry,</hi> and advancing Chriſtianity ſo newly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted to death by <hi>Paganiſm</hi> came between, by which, though the <hi>Empire</hi> continued, yet the <hi>Beſtianiſm of the Empire</hi> was <hi>ready to dye,</hi> and had <hi>dyed,</hi> but that there was a decree, to permit it to be <hi>Heal'd,</hi> and <hi>Reviv'd</hi> within a <hi>ſhort ſpace</hi> in the <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Beaſt;</hi> which could therefore be no other, then whatever ſucceeded the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> in <hi>Roman Beaſtian Supremacy;</hi> though, as we ſhall find only in an <hi>Image of Supremacy,</hi> and therefore muſt be the Papacy; elſe the <hi>Wound</hi> were not <hi>Healed</hi> to this day, which were moſt contrary to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the frame of the <hi>Beſtian Monarchies</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the whole Image of Things in the <hi>Apocalyps of John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this Note of the <hi>Beaſt wounded</hi> is ſo great an aſſurance of the Care of <hi>Prophecy</hi> over the <hi>Calendar,</hi> given in <hi>Daniel,</hi> (though this <hi>Wound</hi> was not revealed in his <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper to it, and not to its Time) as can be given; and makes us more certain of the Truth of it, then if that occaſion of its Care had not been, as the Truth of a Prediction is more ſeen by taking notice of a preternatural Accident, and foretelling it, then if ſuch an Accident had not been; we are therefore to conſider the Prophecy of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> as all one <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> in both; and as but of one, and the ſame Author, writing ſeveral <hi>Propheſies</hi> in ſeveral Times, and filling up the former by the latter.</p>
               <p>And thus all <hi>Hiſtory</hi> agrees; That the <hi>Chriſtian Emperors</hi> came after the <hi>Pagan Emperors,</hi> and diſabled their <hi>Idolatrous</hi> and perſecuting Power. And that after the <hi>Chriſtian Emperors</hi> came
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106747:26"/> the divided State of the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> in ſeveral <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> united in the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and hath continued to this very Day; which muſt therefore be the <hi>Beaſt</hi> with his <hi>Ten Horns;</hi> (though all be convey'd, as it ought to be, according to this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> in a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and in an <hi>Image,)</hi> or elſe the <hi>Revelation</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a <hi>True Prophecy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. There is another principal Note, that the <hi>Sacred Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> gives, on purpoſe to ſhew, that the <hi>Beſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-Antichriſtian-Roman Supremacy</hi> in the <hi>ſeventh Head;</hi> call'd the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and his <hi>Ten Horns;</hi> did not immediately ſucceed to that <hi>Pagan, Beaſtian Monarchy;</hi> but that there was the coming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween of a <hi>Chriſtian Empire;</hi> and that the <hi>Beſtian Kingdom,</hi> that followed that <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> was the <hi>Papal Kingdom;</hi> the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and regard to which is of ſo great moment to this <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetic Calendar,</hi> that <hi>Prophecy</hi> hath taken ſo great Care in it; and It is thus to be underſtood;</p>
               <p>The <hi>Four Monarchies</hi> ſucceding one another, as in the <hi>Image</hi> of a <hi>Humane Body,</hi> the Succeſſion muſt be, as by way of kind Communication, as is between the ſeveral parts of the ſame body; And this was to ſhew, one <hi>Idolatrous Spirit,</hi> a <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> contrary to the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> inform'd, and intelligenc'd the whole from Head to Foot.</p>
               <p>But though theſe <hi>Monarchies</hi> were ſo united in one Spirit, and therefore as in <hi>one Body;</hi> yet to ſhew the contrariety of each ſucceding to each former Kingdom; they are in another Viſion repreſented, as <hi>Four</hi> Salvage <hi>Beasts,</hi> each latter ravaging on that in power before it.</p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Perſian,</hi> as by a <hi>Belluine</hi> Might, vanquiſhed the <hi>Babylonian,</hi> the <hi>Graecian</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> the <hi>Graecian,</hi> as <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions, <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 8. and all Hiſtory make notorious.</p>
               <p>And thus it was determin'd by God, that the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> that came in, as <hi>Feet of Iron</hi> in Succeſſion to the <hi>Legs of Iron;</hi> and the <hi>Horns</hi> in Succeſſion to the <hi>Iron Teeth,</hi> ſhould come in as by way of <hi>Leaving,</hi> or <hi>Legacying,</hi> or kind Communication, as from part to part. And ſo indeed, the <hi>Pagan idolatrous Empire</hi> did, as it were naturally, and ſpontaneouſly reſign, and dye into the Antichriſtian riſing out of it; thus it is repreſented after a <hi>prophetical, emblematical manner</hi> by the <hi>Revelation;</hi> The <hi>Dragon gave its Throne, Power,</hi> and <hi>Great Authority</hi> to the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> that is, the <hi>Pagan Emperor</hi> to the <hi>Papal Antichrist,</hi> what ever diſtance of Time there was between them; and ſo they worſhipped the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106747:27"/> 
                  <hi>Dragon</hi> in the Beaſt, as aforeſaid; Thus it was as between the Congenial, one <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Papal Beast,</hi> and the <hi>Legs</hi> and <hi>Feet</hi> of the <hi>Image.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then as the <hi>Viſion</hi> of the <hi>Beasts</hi> imports each <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſucceding the former, as by violence; ſo theſe <hi>Horns</hi> or <hi>Ten Kings</hi> came by violence into the <hi>Empire;</hi> for ſo it pleaſed the wiſe, and Holy Governour of the World, it ſhould be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Nations foreign to the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> tranſplanted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their own Seats, and by armed force plac'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in <hi>Italy,</hi> and the ſeveral parts and Provinces of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet they all made ſtill the ſame <hi>Roman Monarchy,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Beaſt,</hi> becauſe, whereas the <hi>Perſian King</hi> ſucceding the <hi>Babylonian</hi> did not place his Royal Greatneſs in <hi>Babel,</hi> but in <hi>Shuſhan,</hi> nor <hi>Alexander</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> but in <hi>Graece,</hi> nor the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> in <hi>Graece, Perſia,</hi> nor <hi>Babylon,</hi> but transferred all to <hi>Rome;</hi> The <hi>barbarous Nations</hi> on the contrary do not remove the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentacy from the <hi>Roman Territories</hi> to the Countries, from whence they came, but continue it, where they found it, and Inhabit, and Inherit the former Reſidencies of <hi>Roman Power,</hi> and ſo are the ſame <hi>Empire</hi> in <hi>Feet of Iron,</hi> and of <hi>Clay.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For if the <hi>Feet of Iron</hi> make no Tranſplantation, much leſs would, or could the <hi>Feet of Clay,</hi> much more tyed to the ſame <hi>Earth,</hi> from whence they ſprung; and above all to the <hi>Roman Earth</hi> of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> where He, ſay they, as <hi>Biſhop</hi> left the print of his Foot, as in <hi>Clay,</hi> that the <hi>Roman Hierarchy</hi> might ſprout from it.</p>
               <p>And they are all the ſame <hi>Beaſt</hi> alſo, whereby the <hi>Calendar,</hi> and Succeſſion is maintained; for to ſhew, the ſame <hi>Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>Hoſtile Spirit</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> influx'd all; the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> gave his All, as was noted before; and the whole is, as nearly allyed as part to part in the ſame <hi>Body,</hi> acted by one and the ſame Spirit.</p>
               <p>And this was all certainly an Illuſtrious, and adorable Care of <hi>Providence</hi> over <hi>Prophecy;</hi> That Things ſhould be juſt thus; that <hi>Prophecy</hi> might be <hi>fulfilled</hi> in the <hi>Roman Monarchy,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing <hi>One</hi> and the ſame <hi>Monarchy,</hi> as we ſhall ſee, in <hi>Ten Kings</hi> united, in one <hi>Eccleſiaſtic Roman Supremacy,</hi> as <hi>Ten Horns</hi> in one <hi>Head;</hi> and the <hi>Capital, Imperial City Rome</hi> was continued for the ſame <hi>Head,</hi> by a moſt aſtoniſhing, and even amazing Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of God, as the other <hi>Capital Cities</hi> within the <hi>Roman Dominion</hi> for the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> each in their own <hi>Kingdoms.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:106747:27"/>
               <p> But ſtill, there were all the Violences of War made uſe of for the Succeſſion of the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> as <hi>Feet</hi> of <hi>Iron;</hi> and they were as neceſſary for the <hi>Feet of Clay,</hi> to riſe in the midſt of thoſe Noiſes, ſtilly, ſilently, unobſervedly to their <hi>Grandeur,</hi> and the <hi>Supremacy</hi> of One <hi>Pontiff,</hi> even <hi>He</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> among them.</p>
               <p>To adjuſt therefore every thing to this Succeſſion with the <hi>Decorum</hi> of the <hi>prophetical Types,</hi> let us now obſerve the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Concert of <hi>Providence</hi> and <hi>Prophecy</hi> in this Period.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place therefore as a great <hi>Emblem</hi> of the <hi>Glorious Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy</hi> over all Nations, and eſpecially his Triumph over that Ancient <hi>Kingdom of Sathan, Pagan,</hi> and <hi>Heatheniſh Idolatry;</hi> wherein Himſelf, and his <hi>Angels,</hi> and the <hi>Demoniz'd Spirits</hi> of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants were ſo immediately <hi>worſhip'd;</hi> there is a wiſe Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by God of a <hi>Christian Empire,</hi> to remonſtrate this Victory in an <hi>Empire</hi> then own'd, as the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Empire</hi> of the World, and where <hi>Heatheniſm</hi> had ſeem'd to Triumph over <hi>Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> but <hi>Chriſtians</hi> thus <hi>overcame,</hi> by the <hi>Blood of the Lamb,</hi> by the <hi>word of his Teſtimony,</hi> and by <hi>Chriſtians</hi> not <hi>Loving their Lives unto Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Empire</hi> therefore enter'd, as into the Heart of the <hi>Fourth Monarchy</hi> in <hi>Daniels Viſions</hi> by a High Dominion, and Ordination of God, though ſo contre-natural to it, that on all Accounts It is as a caſting <hi>Sathan out of Heaven,</hi> and as it were the <hi>Coming of the Kingdom of our God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The whole Order therefore of theſe <hi>Emperors</hi> throughout the whole Time of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> is ſo far all one order,<note place="margin">Revel. 17. v. 10.</note> that from firſt to laſt, they are All one <hi>ſeventh King,</hi> as the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Judah</hi> were All, <hi>One Houſe of David;</hi> but this <hi>Empire</hi> in its former and in its latter Times differ'd much in the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Chriſtian State,</hi> and in the Illuſtrious Preſence of God with it; as <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and thoſe <hi>latter Kings</hi> did from <hi>David and Solomon;</hi> yet ſo, that while the order it ſelf ſtood, there could be no Succeſſion of the <hi>Bestian Kingdom;</hi> for they are ſpecificly diſtinct, which is a note of great weight in the <hi>Calendar;</hi> and it is even demonſtrated, That all thoſe Chriſtian <hi>Emperors</hi> in ſacred Regiſter, are but One; becauſe They are called <hi>One other King,</hi> and that they are ſpecificly diſtinct; becauſe the <hi>Eighth</hi> is of the <hi>Bestian Heads,</hi> the <hi>ſeventh</hi> before it is not.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:106747:28"/>
               <p> But now, as to our Note; this <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Empire look'd like an Infracture on the Calendar; for that, a Succeſſion was due to the <hi>Feet of Iron,</hi> and <hi>Clay,</hi> and to the <hi>Ten Horns,</hi> and to the <hi>little Horn;</hi> that is; to the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Papacy,</hi> as ſoon as ever the <hi>Legs of Iron,</hi> and <hi>Head</hi> as of the <hi>Teeth of Iron,</hi> that is, the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> was depriv'd of ſupreme Power; ſo that this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſtian Empire according to <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions was to have dyed, as ſoon as it was born.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prophecy</hi> therefore, as it were remembring in the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> what it ſelf had ſaid in the <hi>Old,</hi> and, as conſcious of the <hi>ſhort ſpace, This Empire</hi> was to continue; and knowing well, That there were four <hi>Trumpets of War</hi> decreed, and prepar'd, as Storms and Tempeſts to remove it; in the very next <hi>Viſion</hi> to that of <hi>Heatheniſm deſolated,</hi> which was <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. laſt; It pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents four <hi>Angels,</hi> c. 7. 1. <hi>Holding the four Winds,</hi> that They ſhould not blow by thoſe <hi>Trumpets,</hi> c. 8. and a charge is given them, to take heed to their Commiſſion, that they ſhould not let out thoſe <hi>Winds,</hi> until the <hi>Servants of God were ſealed in their Foreheads;</hi> that is, That the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> ſhould continue, and continue in Glory, and Peace, till Things were prepared for the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> that <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> or <hi>Beaſt,</hi> as this <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſtyles Him; and as we ſhall find preſently, that <hi>ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the <hi>Servants of God</hi> in the <hi>Forehead</hi> imported; Till the <hi>Feet</hi> of <hi>Clay</hi> then were ready for their Succeſſion, the <hi>Feet of Iron</hi> ſhould not ſucceed; for they were <hi>Feet</hi> together, though of ſo different a Mettal, and not to <hi>cleave;</hi> nor the <hi>Ten Horns,</hi> till the <hi>little Horn,</hi> though in another appearance. <hi>viz.</hi> of a <hi>Head</hi> in the <hi>New Teſtament-Prophecy,</hi> ſhould be ready for his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Succeſſion alſo; for at the ſame <hi>Hour</hi> Both were to <hi>receive Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what does this ſo peremptory Charge import, but a <hi>miraculous,</hi> as it were, and immediate over-rule of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral courſe of Things, according to <hi>Daniels Viſions?</hi> and the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of it laſted in full force from the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine the Great,</hi> till the Death of <hi>Theodoſius the Great.</hi> Then there was ſuch a Relaxation of this Charge, that the <hi>Angels prepared</hi> Themſelves to <hi>ſound,</hi> but did no more, then prepare.</p>
               <p>Now how agreeable is this to <hi>Hiſtory?</hi> ſoon after <hi>Theodoſius</hi>'s <hi>Death,</hi> theſe Clouds and Storms began to hover and hang, but did not fall, in their full effect of <hi>doing the Chriſtian Empire</hi> out <hi>of the middle,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 7. where it ſtood as a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106747:28"/> 
                  <hi>Wall of partition</hi> betwixt the <hi>Beſtian Times</hi> of the <hi>Pagan Empire,</hi> and the Times of the <hi>Antichriſtian Beſtian Empire,</hi> that They could not meet; but then according to <hi>Daniels Prophecy</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by the <hi>Revelation,</hi> They clos'd; for then the <hi>Dragon,</hi> or <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> gave its <hi>Throne,</hi> and <hi>Great Authority</hi> to <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> or the <hi>Beſtian Empire,</hi> and the <hi>Antichriſtian Times</hi> began<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And thus the <hi>man of Sin</hi> was <hi>held back,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaid, that <hi>He might be revealed in his own Time,</hi> and the <hi>middle Time</hi> being of an arbitrary interpoſal, but Divine, is, an Inter-reign of no Account in the <hi>Beſtian Empire,</hi> but all comes naturally toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the <hi>Dragon,</hi> as was ſaid, <hi>Gave his Throne, &amp;c.</hi> as if there had been no Interruption.</p>
               <p>And how decorous now to the <hi>Type</hi> is All the State of Things, as to the <hi>Heathen Empire</hi> remov'd!</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was abſolutely neceſſary to the Succeſſion of the <hi>Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> the <hi>Heathen Empire</hi> ſhould be removed; It was then moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corous, it ſhould be <hi>done</hi> by a <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> the <hi>Emblem</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> and not that the <hi>Feet,</hi> and <hi>Toes of Iron</hi> of the <hi>Roman Beſtian Empire</hi> ſhould ravage on the <hi>Legs</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> nor the <hi>Horns of the ſeventh Head</hi> on the <hi>ſixth Head,</hi> which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>prophetic</hi> Repreſentation kindly yielded the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to it, as was ſaid.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> gave Great Advantage to the <hi>Feet of Clay,</hi> or the <hi>Antichriſtian Hierarchy</hi> to negotiate their own power by the Favour of Chriſtian Emperors, and their Donations of Titles, and Revenues to Chriſtian <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and to a Chriſtian <hi>Clergy,</hi> as they affected to be call'd.</p>
               <p>And Shoales of People then coming in to the <hi>Princes Religion,</hi> there was a condeſcending to the <hi>Pagan Divi, conſecrated Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Holy-days, Prieſts, Pontiffs, Rites to the Dead, Images;</hi> So, that Reſemblances were found for them of a Chriſtian Name, until Things came to that paſs, that the Servants of God were <hi>ſeal'd,</hi> that is, the true <hi>Chriſtian Glory</hi> was ſtay'd, <hi>ſeal'd up,</hi> and reſerv'd to the future Time of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſecur'd for that againſt <hi>Antichriſtian Contagion;</hi> The <hi>Gentiles</hi> in <hi>Pagan Rites</hi> enter'd into the <hi>outward Court,</hi> or <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Name,</hi> and the <hi>True Worſhippers</hi> retir'd into the <hi>Temple;</hi> The <hi>Witneſſes</hi> put on their <hi>Sackcloth,</hi> out of whith they are not yet, and the True <hi>Chriſtian Church fled into the Wilderneſs,</hi> in which it is ſtill <hi>Hid,</hi> though not ſo cloſe, ſince the <hi>Reformation,</hi> but yet waits the perfection of the Reformation; All which are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106747:29"/> Expreſſions of the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Succeſſion, together with the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> and for which the <hi>Trumpets</hi> were ſtay'd from <hi>ſounding,</hi> till he who judg'd Righteouſly of the True <hi>Epoch</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie,</hi> gave them leave to <hi>ſound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſecond place, as to the <hi>removing of the Chriſtian Empire,</hi> how admirably fitted are the Types alſo! For ſeeing the <hi>Beſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Supremacy</hi> in the <hi>ſeventh Papal Head,</hi> and the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> could not be, till all Light of the <hi>Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars</hi> of the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Empire</hi> were <hi>darkned,</hi> and the <hi>Empire</hi> it ſelf <hi>quench'd,</hi> as a <hi>Lamp in Water,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> ſo often taken, and re-taken; that it had no Title of <hi>Supremacy</hi> over it, but that of <hi>Biſhop;</hi> and the whole Glory of the <hi>Empire</hi> blaſted, as by <hi>Hail mingled with Fire;</hi> who ſo fit to do this, as <hi>Barbarian Nations,</hi> whom Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy brands as the Inſtruments of <hi>Sathan,</hi> the <hi>Dragon perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Woman</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> that <hi>brought forth the manly Child,</hi> and who were to be the <hi>Horns of the Antichriſtian Beaſt,</hi> by whoſe Mediation the <hi>Dragon</hi> gave his power to Him?</p>
               <p>But this <hi>Empire,</hi> however it carried the Name of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and bore the <hi>Emblem of the Kingdom of Chriſt ſtill,</hi> as <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> even after the <hi>Crucifying of Chriſt</hi> was call'd the <hi>Holy City,</hi> yet it was ſo deeply by this Time <hi>Antichriſtianiz'd,</hi> that the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God adminiſter'd by theſe <hi>barbarous Nations</hi> did indeed purſue it. For he abhor'd the <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Proſtitutions, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſes to <hi>Paganiſm</hi> under the diſguiſe of Antichriſtianiſm, from which he had ſo wonderfully reſcued it.</p>
               <p>As therefore of old, He gave up <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to be either <hi>Captivated</hi> or deſtroyed by <hi>litteral Babylon,</hi> on whoſe <hi>Idolatries</hi> it doted; even ſo He now delivered up the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> and <hi>Empire,</hi> as ſo <hi>Antichriſtianiz'd</hi> to be either <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> or <hi>enſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> by thoſe <hi>Feet of Iron</hi> and <hi>Clay,</hi> and that <hi>ſeventh Head,</hi> and its <hi>Ten Horns;</hi> ſo that what Sathan did with a Helliſh malice, God moſt Righteouſly, and Supremely, though moſt ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed by Him.</p>
               <p>And thus we have brought down the <hi>Calendar,</hi> and ſettled it on that great <hi>pillar of Time,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> Inaugurated in <hi>Constantine,</hi> Illuſtrated a new in the great <hi>Theodoſe</hi> and <hi>Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> in <hi>Augustulus,</hi> from which as we ſhall find the <hi>man of ſin</hi> in <hi>his own Times,</hi> as the <hi>Apostle</hi> calls them, commencing, and of which we have a numeral <hi>Calendar</hi> given us by <hi>Prophecy.</hi> And the Time where we are to begin, we are moſt certain of by <hi>History;</hi> That it was cloſe to 475, from whence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106747:29"/> it is to be dated, for then <hi>Augustulus</hi> was compell'd to <hi>Abdicate Empire.</hi> Then therefore <hi>Antichristian Times</hi> began, as I ſhall now go on to make out and to ſhew the ſtate of Things from that Time going on, till now; as we all in great meaſure muſt needs know to be very <hi>Astoniſhingly</hi> agreeing with <hi>Prophecy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have now, I ſay, brought down the <hi>Calendar</hi> in my own Judgment, and I offer it to the Judgment of all the Serious, (ſuppoſing it acording to the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> and therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable) to the <hi>fourth Roman Monarchy,</hi> eſtabliſh'd upon an <hi>Article of Faith,</hi> at the <hi>Crucifixion</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> I have led it from thence through the <hi>Pagan State</hi> of it, of which a <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon watching</hi> a <hi>Manly birth</hi> to devour it, is an <hi>Emblem</hi> ſo ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant of the dreadful <hi>Perſecutions</hi> for above 300 years after <hi>Chriſt</hi> as to be even demonſtrative; and ſo conducted it to the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Empire,</hi> of which the <hi>Dragon caſt out</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and a <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Child</hi> caught up to the <hi>Throne of God,</hi> in a <hi>Kingdom</hi> decreed him as in <hi>Heaven</hi> (though not immediately Appearing on Earth, as is manifeſt by the <hi>Churches flying into the Wilderneſs)</hi> is an <hi>Emblem</hi> ſo Beautiful, and Inviting, as not to be refus'd.</p>
               <p>And if we do but yield that, to be the <hi>Emblem</hi> of the <hi>Roman Monarchy,</hi> firſt perſecuting <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and then it ſelf becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> we are of neceſſity concluded, that either that <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> was all the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> or that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Monarchy</hi> is that <hi>Roman Fourth Monarchy</hi> ſtill in a direct op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> For ſo the <hi>Fourth Monarchy</hi> muſt be the <hi>fourth Monarchy</hi> till then, and if the <hi>Roman</hi> be the <hi>Fourth,</hi> that muſt be ſo.</p>
               <p>Now that that <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> is not the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> we muſt needs know, becauſe it did not <hi>conſume all other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> and becauſe that of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall never end, but that of a <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> would <hi>continue</hi> but a <hi>ſhort ſpace;</hi> About an 150 years was the bounds of it. And violently it was made to ceaſe by the <hi>Barbarian Force,</hi> which <hi>Prophecy</hi> calls the <hi>Dragon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting</hi> that <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> that brought forth as a ſhort <hi>Emblem</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in that <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> the <hi>Manly</hi> Birth, <hi>Chriſt</hi> as a Soveraign.</p>
               <p>And leaſt we ſhould think, it had a ſucceſſion, and ſo an endurance in the <hi>Papacy</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Kings,</hi> and <hi>Emperours</hi> that roſe out of its ruins, we find according to <hi>Prophecy;</hi> All
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106747:30"/> that ſucceſſion is involv'd in the dark Portraictture of a <hi>Beaſt</hi> and its <hi>Ten Horns;</hi> That true <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> that brought forth that <hi>Empire,</hi> is cloſe <hi>Hid in the Wilderneſs,</hi> for 1260 years, till the end of which it cannot return; beſides, even that <hi>Papal ſtate</hi> ſuppoſe it had been a ſucceſſion of a <hi>Chriſtian Kingdom;</hi> It hath been, if I may ſo ſpeak, <hi>Woe Trumpetted</hi> by the <hi>Saracens,</hi> and <hi>Turks,</hi> for ſo great a ſpace, that as hath been ſaid, it could not be the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and therefore muſt be the <hi>Kingdom of Antichriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For ſo we find the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> as an <hi>Eighth King</hi> ſucceeded the <hi>Seventh</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian King</hi> after a <hi>ſhort ſpace,</hi> and the very ſame <hi>Beaſt</hi> of the <hi>Seventh Head</hi> ſucceeded the <hi>Sixth Pagan King wounded in his Head,</hi> ſo his ſucceſſion was double; In Time, He ſucceeded the <hi>Chriſtian Emperour;</hi> as <hi>Beſtian,</hi> He ſucceeded the <hi>Pagan ſixth King,</hi> who according to <hi>Daniel</hi> gave him his <hi>Throne, Power,</hi> and <hi>great Authority.</hi> For the <hi>Papacy</hi> in his <hi>Ten Kingdoms,</hi> devoted to him, is a <hi>Pagan Chriſtian,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Supremacy;</hi> Thus it was, and thus it ought to be, that <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy might be fulfill'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far then we are moſt aſſured, whatever ſucceeded the <hi>Pagan Empire</hi> in Time, was the ſhort ſpac'd <hi>Chriſtian Empire;</hi> whatever ſucceeded the ſhort <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> in Time muſt be the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> that notwithſtanding the Interpoſal of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> is united according to <hi>Daniel</hi> to the <hi>fourth Beſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and according to the <hi>Revelation</hi> to the <hi>Dragon;</hi> And ſeeing no other ſucceeded the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> in Time, but the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and the <hi>Ten Kings;</hi> Therefore that is the Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the <hi>fourth Monarchy</hi> in the <hi>Image,</hi> as <hi>Feet of Clay</hi> and <hi>of Iron;</hi> and in the viſion <hi>of the Beaſts,</hi> as the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and <hi>Ten Horns,</hi> and remains, and ſhall remain ſo, until it ſhall be <hi>Broken</hi> by the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Period. </seg>3</label> Our <hi>Calendar</hi> Reaches down to 475. by <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> and by <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> and here there enters a <hi>Beſtian</hi> ſtate which will take up more then Half the Time, from the giving of theſe <hi>viſions</hi> to <hi>Daniel;</hi> and a Moyety, or thereabouts of the whole Time, that the <hi>fourth Kingdom</hi> had ſo much, as a Being, even at the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs Condita,</hi> or the building of the <hi>Roman City;</hi> more then the Time thrice over, that it came into this <hi>Calendar,</hi> which was at the Ceſſation of the <hi>Graecian Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe therefore this Time would be ſo long, it pleaſed the infinite wiſdom, and goodneſs of <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106747:30"/> give ſome light before hand to his Servants, how long this Time ſhould laſt; It pleas'd it, I ſay, to give here a <hi>Numeral</hi> though a <hi>myſtic Calendar,</hi> even juſt here, and to tell us, that <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Times</hi> ſhould be given for <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and the <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Time</hi> into the <hi>Hand of the little Horn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And why, ſeeing were are bound to <hi>ſearch</hi> as far as we can, <hi>what,</hi> and <hi>what manner of Time,</hi> the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt</hi> did <hi>ſignifie,</hi> was it given here, rather then in any other part of the <hi>viſion of the Beaſts,</hi> if it had not been the pleaſure of God, that we ſhould know before hand, how long this laſt <hi>Beſtian</hi> ſtate ſhould exiſt?</p>
               <p>For if we had been to wait the event onely; There had been leſs need of a <hi>Calendar</hi> here, then in any other part of the <hi>viſion:</hi> For the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> immediately comming into its ſucceſſion, after the Times of this laſt <hi>Roman</hi> ſtate; It will give a more Indubitable Reſound of its event than any other event of the viſion can be ſuppos'd to do; It was certainly therefore given to define Time before hand.</p>
               <p>But if with the Comment of <hi>Prophecy</hi> it ſelf in the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> it were not to be underſtood, Then it muſt be given to no end; Let us therefore be encouraged to ſearch it; For it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly to be underſtood, as I hope we ſhall find.</p>
               <p>And that we may underſtand it, Theſe Two Things are neceſſary: 1. To expound the <hi>Calendar</hi> in its <hi>Epoch,</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and in its juſt Courſe, Extent, and <hi>Period:</hi> and then, Secondly, to Adjuſt by the <hi>Symbols of Prophecy,</hi> and the moſt noble Aſſurances of <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> or rather of our own knowledge and Experience (The Things being much in Being, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence at this Day) the Congruity of Events according to it, ſo far as They are already paſs'd, and thereby to derive the moſt aſcertain'd Expectations, of what is yet to come.</p>
               <p>Now that we may do the firſt, it is neceſſary, that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cert <hi>Time, Times, Half a Time</hi> with <hi>Forty two Months,</hi> which are the <hi>Apocalyptick Calendar</hi> for the <hi>Regnancies</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and his <hi>Ten Horns</hi> or various <hi>Kingdoms</hi> according to the Reſemblance of the <hi>Ten Toes</hi> in the <hi>Image;</hi> which have been already prov'd to be in an immediate ſucceſſion to the <hi>Chriſtian Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt place therefore, we muſt obſerve the Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence betwixt the <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time,</hi> and the <hi>Forty two Months;</hi> Let therefore <hi>Time</hi> ſignifie a year, according to that note, <hi>Prophecy</hi> hath undoubtedly on purpoſe provided us with, of <hi>Seven Times paſſing</hi> over the <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106747:31"/> his <hi>Lunacy;</hi> for that Times ſhould be more than Years, the courſe of his Conqueſts till within about Ten years of his Death will not allow; for in the <hi>Twenty ſeventh year</hi> of <hi>Jehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins Captivity,</hi> He made, as it appears, his laſt Conqueſt, and had been as we may perceive by <hi>Ezekiels Prophecy</hi> in a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al courſe of Victory to that Time, as hath been more at large in a former Diſcourſe diſcuſſed. Now that <hi>Twenty ſeventh of Jehoiach.</hi> muſt be the Thirty fifth of <hi>Nebuchad.</hi> for <hi>Jehoiakims Third</hi> was his <hi>Firſt;</hi> Add therefore the laſt eight of <hi>Jehoiakim</hi> to <hi>Jehoiachims Twenty ſeventh,</hi> they make <hi>Nebuch.</hi> Thirty fifth; and <hi>Evilmerodachs</hi> Firſt, who according to Scripture ſucceeded <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> his Father, falling on <hi>Jehoiachins Thirty ſeventh;</hi> there remained Ten to <hi>Nebuch.</hi> when <hi>Ezekiel propheſied</hi> his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of Egypt,</hi> within which Ten the <hi>ſeven</hi> of his <hi>Delirium</hi> muſt be comprehended; the ſeven Times therefore could not ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic more, then <hi>ſeven Years.</hi> For his Life we ſee would not allow more; nor can They in any fair ſuppoſal ſignifie leſs, there being no determinate meaſure of Time, worthy to be call'd <hi>Times,</hi> except Months; and ſeven Months is a Time much too ſhort for his being turn'd out, as among the <hi>Beaſts;</hi> or that the <hi>ſtump,</hi> or little ſhort Time of his Reign ſhould be ſo <hi>Banded with Iron,</hi> that It might be ſecur'd to Him. Now I have thus induſtriouſly debated this Matter, becauſe I would gain by it that, I think cannot now be deny'd; That a Time in Time, Times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> denotes a year. If then a <hi>Time</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes a year, <hi>Times</hi> joyn'd with <hi>Half a Time</hi> muſt denote two Years, becauſe there is no <hi>medium</hi> betwixt One <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time,</hi> but two <hi>Times</hi> or two years; ſo that the whole is Three years and a half.</p>
               <p>Let us then calculate the <hi>forty two Months,</hi> and we find They anſwer juſt <hi>Three years,</hi> and a <hi>Half,</hi> ſo that when we come to find as we ſhall do all along, by the compare, that the <hi>little Horn</hi> among the <hi>Ten Horns</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> however they may ſeem to differ, are the very ſame; Even the <hi>Forty two Months</hi> will demonſtrate, that the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> are <hi>three Years and Half,</hi> as <hi>forty two Months</hi> in general Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count make.</p>
               <p>Now if They are <hi>Three Years,</hi> and a <hi>Half,</hi> we know certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly They muſt be <hi>prophetically multiplyed,</hi> according to the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of All <hi>prophetical Time,</hi> given to <hi>Ezekiel, c.</hi> 4. except there be a plain Reaſon againſt it; each day of each year muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106747:31"/> a <hi>Year.</hi> Beſides no Time ſo ſmall, as <hi>Three years</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> can ſerve ſuch a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as that of the <hi>Beaſt's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The General ſenſe of the <hi>Calendar</hi> then, being thus eſtabliſh'd, the next thing to be done is to fix the <hi>Epoch of the Calendar,</hi> which is as it were the Foundation, of every <hi>Calendar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſeeing the <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> gives, as we have found, ſo clear an Account of the Time of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> interpoſed to the <hi>Roman Beſtian Empire</hi> betwixt the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> and the <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> of which <hi>Daniel</hi> ſays nothing; we may from thence learn the moſt preciſe, and definite Time of the Succeſſion.</p>
               <p>And It is evident, The Succeſſion muſt be immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Abdication</hi> of <hi>Empire</hi> by <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> which was the very Time of the deceaſe of the <hi>ſeventh King;</hi> and therefore, as cloſe as Succeſſion is to Succeſſion, ſo cloſe muſt be the <hi>Antichriſtian Empire</hi> to the <hi>Chriſtian Empire.</hi> For ſo the general Laws of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion require.</p>
               <p>And much more when God interpos'd an <hi>Empire,</hi> that ſhould be an <hi>Emblem</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> till that was <hi>done out of the midſt</hi> by an Ordination, as Supreme, as It was there ſet, there could be no Succeſſion, ſo that It could not be till <hi>Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi> Thus on one ſide.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, ſeeing It was an unnatural Interpoſal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Pagan-beſtian</hi> and the <hi>Antichriſtian-beſtian Kingdom,</hi> as ſoon as ever that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Empire was according to that moſt pregnant Expreſſion of the <hi>Apoſtle done</hi> out of the <hi>midſt,</hi> That Separation and diſtance made as it were by <hi>violence</hi> and not <hi>willingly</hi> betwixt <hi>Beſtian</hi> and <hi>Beſtian</hi> clos'd up; and as in the moment, <hi>Beſtian</hi> reunited to <hi>Beſtian,</hi> as by an <hi>Elaſtic</hi> force of ſelf Reſtitution; ſo that the Succeſſion could be no longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd, then juſt the <hi>Abdication</hi> of <hi>Auguſtulus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by the way we may obſerve, <hi>Abdication,</hi> whether out of fear, and neceſſity, or a deſertion out of Reſolution, rather to part with Government, than to govern according to the fundamental contract of Government, is a <hi>doing</hi> a Government <hi>out of the midſt,</hi> and makes a good, and valid Succeſſion, in Gods Account, even where He had ſo particularly order'd a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, becauſe Government is ſo neceſſary, that no <hi>vacuum</hi> can be allowed<note n="*" place="margin">Opor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t Impera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>; The <hi>Powers</hi> therefore, that are <hi>Powers in Being,</hi> and in the actual Execution of Juſtice, are <hi>ordained of God,</hi> and to be obey'd. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. 2.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:106747:32"/>
               <p> For thus it appears here, the <hi>ſeventh King</hi> was, according to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> to <hi>continue</hi> only a ſhort ſpace; and being conſtrained by <hi>Odoacer</hi> the <hi>Barbarian Conqueror</hi> to renounce Government; Himſelf took the Title of <hi>King of Italy,</hi> and not of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Providence of God ſo ordering it, as it were to keep the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion clear; and ſo the Succeſſion immediately veſted in the <hi>ſeventh Head</hi> and <hi>Eighth King,</hi> that is, in the <hi>Antichriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of this, the <hi>Sacred Prophecy</hi> gives all the Teſtimony poſſible; for when it gives a <hi>ſeries of Kings,</hi> One after another, and ſays <hi>Five were fallen, One is, Another is not yet,</hi> and when <hi>He</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 17. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>comes,</hi> muſt <hi>continue a ſhort ſpace;</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> is the <hi>Eighth;</hi> It is plainly to ſay, though in other words, <hi>The Eighth King,</hi> who ever He is, that is the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> ſucceeded immediately to the <hi>ſeventh,</hi> who was the Chriſtian King or Emperor. Now ſeeing whoever was the Supreme of <hi>Rome</hi> all along hitherto, and muſt continue ſo till the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> muſt have ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the <hi>Chriſtian Emperor,</hi> and been the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> I do but ask then, who hath demanded, claim'd, and been defended by the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> as Supreme of the <hi>City Rome</hi> for hundreds of years? He muſt be <hi>This Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, becauſe the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> as <hi>Feet of Iron</hi> with the <hi>Feet of Clay,</hi> and as <hi>Horns</hi> with the <hi>Head,</hi> were to have a Succeſſion at equal dates with the <hi>ſeventh Head,</hi> and <hi>Eighth King,</hi> the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> having ſo definitively given the Time of the <hi>Beaſts Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion;</hi> that it was, whenever the <hi>ſeventh Head</hi> ceas'd; It gives alſo the Time of their Succeſſion, that It was at the very ſame Time, even at<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. The like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining Time is other Times uſed in the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> John 4. 52. Acts 10. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>One Hour</hi> with the <hi>Beaſts Receiving Power;</hi> That is; At the very ſame Time, the <hi>Beaſt received Power,</hi> They <hi>received Power</hi> alſo, for they <hi>received Power at one Hour with the Beaſt;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Feet of Iron,</hi> and of <hi>Clay,</hi> and the <hi>Head</hi> and the <hi>Ten Horns</hi> together <hi>received Power</hi> immediately upon the <hi>Abdication</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Emperor,</hi> which was at 475. The ſame Phraſe or manner of ſpeaking is therefore us'd concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both; <hi>Power</hi> was given to the <hi>Beaſt</hi> to <hi>continue Forty two Months,</hi> That He might <hi>do</hi> all Things ſpoken of Him from Firſt to Laſt. He had <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>continue forty two Months,</hi> or<note place="margin">Rev. 13. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for his whole Action; <hi>Power</hi> was <hi>given to Him,</hi> during the ſpace of <hi>Forty two Months;</hi> ſo the <hi>Ten Horns received Power</hi> as <hi>Kings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 17. 12.</note> though They had a motion and violent Action before, yet as in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Time, They had no <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſo They had no
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106747:32"/> Right of Succeſſion until the <hi>Beast received Power;</hi> and They then <hi>received Power</hi> as <hi>Kings</hi> of a lawful Succeſſion, even <hi>at one</hi> and the <hi>ſame Hour</hi> with the <hi>Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now ſeeing the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>Ten Kings received Power together,</hi> there muſt be ſome very <hi>Cardinal Time</hi> for them to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Power in;</hi> the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> altogether with one another; and then, They altogether with the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with every one of them; This, I ſay, cannot be in Reaſon ſuppoſed without ſome ſupreme, and eminent Deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Prophecy</hi> concerning the Time, when It ſhould be, and when God would be pleas'd to have it ſo accounted to be; for could ſo many <hi>Kings,</hi> who by various Accidents and Emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents of War aroſe to <hi>Kingly Power,</hi> ſome at one Time, and ſome at another, be ſuppos'd to <hi>receive Power together</hi> at <hi>one,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Hour,</hi> Hiſtorically, and in matter of Fact? Beſides, according to all <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> It was not ſo; ſome of theſe <hi>Kingdoms</hi> got up much ſooner, then others; It is therefore on a <hi>Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Account,</hi> and on poſitive determination of the Time by Divine Authority; God, by <hi>whom Kings Reign,</hi> and who dates <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> as He pleaſes, dated the <hi>Power of the Beaſt,</hi> and the Power of theſe <hi>Ten Kings;</hi> All to an <hi>Hour;</hi> and He hath told us, when It was; It was, when that peculiar <hi>Chriſtian Empire of Rome</hi> He had ſet up, was by his <hi>Providence</hi> ſuperſeded; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that, though theſe <hi>Kings were Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop of Rome Biſhop of Rome;</hi> yet they were <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Pope of Rome Pope of Rome under one Imperial Head,</hi> who ſtood by Divine Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment as their Supreme Lord; He was their <hi>Head</hi> by a <hi>Divine Right;</hi> and They All under Him, and in that Right in a dependence upon him, even as <hi>Herod</hi> on <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> though not in Fact; for He, who gives the <hi>Kingdoms of the Earth</hi> to whom <hi>He pleaſes,</hi> declares ſo; and tells us, The <hi>Beaſt</hi> came into his <hi>Hour</hi> as an <hi>Eighth King,</hi> when the <hi>ſeventh</hi> gave up; and though the <hi>ſixth Head,</hi> or <hi>Pagan Emperor</hi> was gone off ſo long before, yet as in the Water, or Air, when the interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Body is removed, the ambient Air, and Water from eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide immediately clap together; ſo the <hi>Beſtian Pagan,</hi> and the <hi>Beſtian Antichriſtian Kingdom</hi> does, when the <hi>Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> was <hi>done</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles Phraſe,</hi> ſo full of this Senſe, <hi>Out of the midſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Having therefore clear'd, and made Good the Epoch of the <hi>Time, Times, Half Time,</hi> I will now before I proceed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106747:33"/> their extent, ſhew how great the Agreement of what we have ſeen in the ſtate of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> ſince the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> in it was <hi>done out of the midſt,</hi> how great, I ſay, the Agreement of it with <hi>Prophecy</hi> is, which will make good that Solid, Subſtantial part of the <hi>Calendar,</hi> and ſhew us, How plainly Time hath run on according to the Aqueducts, and Chanels foretold to it ſo long before in theſe following Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervat. </seg>1</label> Let us then obſerve the <hi>Papacy,</hi> the <hi>Cardinaliſm,</hi> the <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> the whole <hi>Roman Hierarchy,</hi> and their depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies in ſo great numbers on the one ſide; and on the other the ſeveral <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> into which the <hi>Roman Empire</hi> hath been ſo long and is ſtill parted, with the warlike <hi>Kings,</hi> and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thereof; And I may appeal to all the World, whether there could be a fitter <hi>Emblem,</hi> or Repreſentation on both parts, then <hi>Feet, part of Iron, part of Clay;</hi> What weaker then the one? What more Potent, and puiſſant then the other? And yet notwithſtanding the weakneſs of the one, and the puiſſance of the other; The <hi>Ten Kings, Agreeing to give their ſtrength, Power,</hi> and <hi>Might,</hi> and their <hi>Kingdom</hi> to <hi>the Beaſt,</hi> They make the <hi>Pope</hi> a <hi>Seventh Head</hi> of <hi>Roman Supremacy,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality,</hi> and the <hi>Hierarchy Feet,</hi> Foundations of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of the ſtate of the World, by being <hi>mingled with the Iron,</hi> however <hi>They do not cleave:</hi> Surely this matter being ſo well known, as to run into ſenſe; we ſee it with our eyes, as to the Event; and the <hi>Emblem,</hi> as eaſie to be underſtood, as Familiar, as the Notices of <hi>Iron, Clay, Feet,</hi> of which the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem</hi> is compos'd are; The attent conſideration then would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince even an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> of the <hi>Truth</hi> of <hi>Scripture Prophecy;</hi> even a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,</hi> that the <hi>Roman Hierarchy</hi> is intended; how much more then may it convince <hi>Proteſtants?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Kings</hi> have alſo made the <hi>Pope</hi> a <hi>little Horn,</hi> They have given him <hi>Territories, Guards, Forces, Revenues,</hi> as a <hi>King,</hi> pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling up the <hi>Gothick,</hi> the <hi>Graecian,</hi> the <hi>Lombardic power,</hi> as <hi>Three Horns before Him,</hi> wherein <hi>Martell, Pipin, Charlemaign</hi> and <hi>Ludovi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us pius</hi> were his great Benefactors; But all this was but very inconſiderable in compare with the reſt, as to an <hi>Iron Potentacy,</hi> were it not for the <hi>Spiritual Supremacy,</hi> the Riches of which is Incomputable.</p>
               <p>Therefore he <hi>Looks with the Eyes of a man,</hi> as the only <hi>Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Seer</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian World;</hi> He hath a <hi>Countenance,</hi> more
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106747:33"/> ſtately then his <hi>Fellows,</hi> the other <hi>Ten Kings;</hi> over whom he hath a <hi>Mouth ſpeaking great Things</hi> in the challenges of <hi>Supreme Dominion,</hi> as the <hi>Vicar of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and as in his place, <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lord of Lords;</hi> He hath <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Laws given into his Hand,</hi> and a <hi>Calendar of Time</hi> peculiar to Him; He hath been for ſeveral Hundreds of years the <hi>great Leviathan</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian World,</hi> the Chief of the <hi>Sons of Pride,</hi> and of the ways of <hi>Providence,</hi> and God's Government of the World; That a <hi>Horn ſo weak</hi> in its true <hi>Anatomy,</hi> and Intrinſick value ſhould have borne ſuch a ſway in the <hi>Empire,</hi> and Governments of the Earth, piercing even to the <hi>Indies</hi> and formerly unknown parts of it: who that reads <hi>Daniel</hi> in compare, with what he hath ſeen, known, read, or even heard of the <hi>Papacy</hi> will not rather think, <hi>Daniel</hi> of late <hi>years</hi> took the <hi>Portraicture</hi> and writ the <hi>Character</hi> of the <hi>Papacy,</hi> then ſpoke of it at the diſtance of ſo many Ages before it! But he was guided by Him, to whom all Things, <hi>paſt, preſent</hi> and <hi>to come</hi> are an even Now.</p>
               <p>In the ſame manner let us reflect upon the <hi>Cardinaliſm, Arch-Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Inferior Clergy</hi> with their Innumerable Train of officers, as on the <hi>Feet of Miry Clay,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt riſing out of the Earth;</hi> more often in their originals, not of the Blood of Kings, and Nobles, weak in their warlike Proweſſe, <hi>Prophets teaching lyes,</hi> who are the Tail of Mankind; Yet with theſe as with the <hi>Seed of Men,</hi> poor, weak, Inconſiderable men, ſprung from the <hi>Earth,</hi> The <hi>feet of Iron</hi> mingle themſelves, and make together the <hi>Feet</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> as equally eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al parts of Government; and the <hi>Clay</hi> is, as we ſay, <hi>Cheek</hi> by <hi>Jole</hi> with them; Theſe <hi>Merchants of Rome</hi> become the Grands of the Earth; I deſire no other, but a Free, Impartial, Frank Judgment upon the Evidence now given, that the <hi>Papacy,</hi> and <hi>Roman Hierarchy</hi> are moſt lively Repreſented by the long, and ſo known Conjunction of the <hi>Powers of Clay</hi> in Conjunction with thoſe of <hi>Iron,</hi> the Kings, and Princes lying within the <hi>Roman Dition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervat. </seg>2</label> Equal to the firſt is the ſecond Obſervation, wherein we ſhall find the preſent ſtate of the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and linck'd to <hi>Prophecy,</hi> both in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation</hi> in that great and Remarkable point of Agreement; <hi>An Image made to the Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> joyn'd ſo often after with his <hi>Image,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and his <hi>Image.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:106747:34"/>
               <p> Let us then reflect on the Famous <hi>Memoir</hi> of <hi>Prophetick Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in the firſt univerſal <hi>Monarch;</hi> the <hi>Golden Head of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, Litteral Babylon; Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in conceipt of that <hi>mighty Image,</hi> He had ſeen in a <hi>Dream</hi> ſo divinely expounded, and of which Himſelf was the <hi>Head of Gold,</hi> would be <hi>worſhipped,</hi> and obeyed in the Counter-point of that <hi>Image ſet up,</hi> and whoever would not worſhip that <hi>Image,</hi> was to be <hi>caſt into a fiery Furnace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In like manner the <hi>other Beaſt,</hi> or the <hi>Antichriſtian Hierarchy</hi> to raiſe up the <hi>Papacy,</hi> as another <hi>Golden Head</hi> of <hi>myſtical Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> ſaid (by way of <hi>Oracle,</hi> and with <hi>lying Wonders,</hi> and <hi>bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> down the <hi>Fire</hi> of <hi>divine Vengeance</hi> by <hi>Anathemaes,</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications,</hi> as <hi>from Heaven,)</hi> to the <hi>Beſtian people,</hi> that they ſhould <hi>make an Image</hi> to the Honour and Glory of that <hi>Roman Pagan Idolatrous Empire,</hi> that had ſuch a <hi>wound by the ſword of Conſtantine,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius, deſtroying Pagan Idolatry,</hi> and yet did <hi>Live,</hi> and did ſo plainly appear to <hi>Live</hi> in the New <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Idolatry;</hi> Eſpecially in that <hi>Image</hi> now to be <hi>Dedicated</hi> to it; <hi>viz.</hi> a new kind of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> a <hi>Spiritual, Eccleſiaſtick Supremacy,</hi> that ſhould have <hi>Power to ſpeak,</hi> and to <hi>Cauſe,</hi> That <hi>All who would not worſhip that Image, ſhould be kill'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I confeſs, is in <hi>Daniel</hi> no more, then <hi>Prophetical Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> and Alluſion; but in the <hi>Prophecy of the Revelation,</hi> It riſes to the very Height of Argument.</p>
               <p>That we may then underſtand this great point, let us ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrictly attend the <hi>Prophecy;</hi> and we ſhall find, that the <hi>Image</hi> is made to the <hi>firſt Beast,</hi> that is, to the <hi>Roman Idolatrous Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> conſider'd as one, and the ſame <hi>Beast,</hi> though of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>Heads;</hi> yet neceſſarily <hi>One,</hi> and the <hi>ſame Beaſt</hi> in both the <hi>Pagan</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian Heads,</hi> as if we ſuppoſe a <hi>Beaſt</hi> of <hi>Two Heads,</hi> each and both would be the ſame <hi>Beast.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> conſidered as <hi>Beaſtian,</hi> having loſt <hi>Supremacy</hi> in its <hi>Pagan,</hi> and <hi>Imperial Head,</hi> ſo <hi>wounded</hi> as hath been ſaid; The <hi>Hierarchick Beast</hi> or <hi>Roman, Antichriſtian Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> with its <hi>Two Horns</hi> like a <hi>Lamb;</hi> of which the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> was, even before the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> ceas'd, a Principal, and almoſt ſupreme part, <hi>Exerciſes the power of the first Beast before it,</hi> and <hi>in its ſight,</hi> that is, before an <hi>Empire,</hi> that was to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of a <hi>Pagan,</hi> an <hi>Antichriſtian Beaſtian Empire</hi> and therefore ſurviv'd; and it ſpake <hi>as a Dragon</hi> for the Reſtoring, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erecting a <hi>Beaſtian Supremacy,:</hi> And becauſe by the decree of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106747:34"/> God, and the ſtate of affairs; This could onely be an <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Supremacy,</hi> which is a <hi>Supremacy,</hi> but in an <hi>Image,</hi> and in an <hi>Antichriſtian Supremacy</hi> which is not <hi>Pagan,</hi> but in an <hi>Image;</hi> There is a Revival of <hi>worſhipping</hi> the <hi>Babylonian Prince</hi> in an <hi>Image,</hi> but ſuch an <hi>Image,</hi> that could <hi>Speak,</hi> and <hi>cauſe to be kill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d,</hi> All, who <hi>would not worſhip according to its Antichriſtian Idolatry,</hi> the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Pagan;</hi> and who would not profeſs ſlavery, and vaſſalage under the <hi>Eccleſiaſtick,</hi> or <hi>Pſeudo-Spiritual Supremacy,</hi> the <hi>Image of the Imperial.</hi> So it would be effective of all <hi>Beſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm,</hi> yet it would be to the former <hi>Beſtian, Pagan Head,</hi> but as in an <hi>Image,</hi> This is a moſt diſtinguiſhing, aſſuring note of <hi>Prophecy,</hi> whom it means, wherever we can find this <hi>Beſtianiſm</hi> as in an <hi>Image;</hi> Let us then behold it in the <hi>Roman Papacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. To this <hi>Beſtianiſm,</hi> there is eſſentially required <hi>Monarchic Roman power,</hi> and <hi>Supremacy;</hi> And was there ever more plainly <hi>Monarchic Roman power</hi> then in ſeveral (and for the ſake of the number of <hi>Toes, Ten) Kings,</hi> expreſly noted to <hi>Receive power as Kings,</hi> of great power and ſtrength, and Independency, and then <hi>giving their Kingdoms, Power,</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> to the <hi>Pope,</hi> on a <hi>Spiritual</hi> account, or as an <hi>Eccleſiaſtick ſupreme;</hi> Juſt as All their Territories were <hi>held in Chief</hi> heretofore, by their depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence upon, and ſubmiſſion to a <hi>Roman Martial Emperour,</hi> fear'd, and obeyed of all; in whoſe Court, they had their <hi>Embaſſadors, Reſidentiaries, Leigiers, Envoys;</hi> In the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner on a <hi>Spiritual</hi> account, they ſubmit to the <hi>Pope,</hi> as the <hi>Holy Father,</hi> as <hi>his Holyneſs,</hi> as the <hi>Vicar of Christ,</hi> and the onely <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme</hi> on Earth over <hi>Conſciences;</hi> They unite in him, have their ſeveral <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Embaſſie</hi> with him, and he hath put on, and kick'd off <hi>Crowns;</hi> Behold, and ſay, whether this is not the former <hi>Ceſarean Supremacy</hi> and yet in an <hi>Image!</hi> How fitly therefore does the <hi>Prophecy</hi> ſay! They <hi>Receive power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> as <hi>Kings,</hi> and yet with the <hi>Beast,</hi> through the Deſtination upon them under a divine decree, to <hi>give their Power</hi> thus, as if they could not have it without him. Thus his <hi>Great power</hi> lies in <hi>his Image,</hi> and for all his vaunts of <hi>Ecce duo Gladii,</hi> His <hi>Hornſhip</hi> were moſt <hi>Puny</hi> without this <hi>Image,</hi> a very <hi>little Horn</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Idolatry</hi> is a ſecond eſſential Conſtituent of <hi>Beſtianiſm,</hi> in ſo much, that as we have found; The <hi>Christian Emperour,</hi> tho' he had the <hi>Roman Supremacy,</hi> and was in his latter Time much <hi>Antichristianiz'd,</hi> yet was as the <hi>Kings of Judah</hi> of a <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah-order;</hi> The <hi>Pagan Emperors,</hi> All <hi>Idolaters</hi> were alſo All
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106747:35"/> 
                  <hi>Beſtian,</hi> however ſome, as the <hi>Antonines, Alexander Severus</hi> as alſo others of them were more more Humane; Juſt ſo, the whole order of <hi>Popes,</hi> however ſome better, ſome worſe, yet are all <hi>Beſtiam</hi> becauſe all <hi>Idolatrous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this <hi>Idolatry</hi> is in an <hi>Image;</hi> It is therefore by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Prophecy</hi> peculiarly ſtyl'd in <hi>Daniel, ſpeaking great words againſt the moſt High,</hi> which is expounded by <hi>John, Blaſphemies;</hi> Now <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> is a Form deriv'd from the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the <hi>Ancient Iſrael,</hi> under the Appearance of a <hi>Church of God;</hi> They held the name of the <hi>true Jehovah,</hi> and yet joyn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d the <hi>Idols</hi> of the <hi>Heathen, Your Fathers Blaſphem'd me on the Hills;</hi> This <hi>Idolatry</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 7.</note> cover'd with the name of the <hi>True God</hi> is peculiarly call'd <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy,</hi> for it is the making the name of God a pander to <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi> which is <hi>Blaſphemy.</hi> And this is moſt particular to the <hi>Antichriſtian Idolatry,</hi> committed upon the name of <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> as in Honour of God, and of Chriſt, and ſo deriv'd on <hi>Images;</hi> And whoever does not worſhip thus, is <hi>Anathematiz'd,</hi> as Prophane, Sacrilegious, Blaſphemous, Branded by the <hi>lying Spirit of Antichriſt</hi> with ſome note of vengeance from Heaven, even as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of old were vilified as Injurious to the Gods, and perſecuted as publick Peſts, and Cauſes of misfortune.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Idolatry</hi> therefore ſtrictly ſpeaking, is an <hi>Image</hi> made to the ancient <hi>Roman Idolatry,</hi> not to the <hi>Pagan Names of Idols</hi> but under the <hi>Imagery</hi> of <hi>names,</hi> truly great and ſacred in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and who, ſo far, as they know it, Abominate the <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry</hi> commited upon them; as a <hi>prophetick Type</hi> of which, <hi>John</hi> was Twice ſo ſeverely reſtrain'd in his Veneration of the <hi>Angel;</hi> This kind of <hi>Idolatry</hi> is therefore ſo notably according to the event defin'd a <hi>Blaſpheming of God,</hi> and of his Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Humanity of Christ;</hi> and of Them, who <hi>dwell in Heaven, viz. Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints;</hi> For theſe pretended Honors are in Heaven Interpreted, as the greateſt diſhonors, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and ſo <hi>Blaſphemies,</hi> both upon the Excellency of the Divine Being, and the Glory of his <hi>Saints</hi> ſo courſly Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented; as alſo as if the <hi>Saints</hi> were pleas'd with ſuch Entrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on the <hi>One God</hi> and <hi>One Mediator</hi> which is indeed to <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheme</hi> Them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Beſtianiſd</hi> is, Bloodineſs, Cruelty, and Perſecution, Ravaging upon the <hi>Saints</hi> of God, and of <hi>Chriſt; Wearing out the Saints of the moſt High, making war</hi> with, <hi>trevailing over, overcoming</hi> and <hi>killing</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:106747:35"/> the <hi>Witneſſes of Jeſus;</hi> And this is alſo cover'd under the <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery</hi> of Extirpating <hi>Hereſie, Blaſphemy,</hi> and Irreligion; which are the odious <hi>Sambenitoes,</hi> Diſguiſes clap'd on Saints, and the <hi>Imagery</hi> put upon them by that <hi>Beſtianiſm</hi> in an <hi>Image,</hi> even as <hi>Pagan Perſecutors</hi> cover'd <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with the <hi>Skins</hi> of <hi>Beasts,</hi> and the more cruel Imputations of Beaſtlike Enormities to them; And to ſum up all, how exact is <hi>Prophecy</hi> in the manner of the Execution of this Feral Rage! The <hi>Image ſpeaks,</hi> and <hi>cauſes to be kill'd,</hi> All, who do not worſhip; which is, as it were, Word for Word; The <hi>Spiritual power Delivering up</hi> to the <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar;</hi> This <hi>Spiritual Beſtianiſm,</hi> as it is part of <hi>Clay,</hi> can put no man to death; It muſt be done for it by the <hi>Iron</hi> of the <hi>Feet,</hi> and yet this <hi>Little Horn</hi> hath often appear'd in Armour as in <hi>Iron,</hi> and found means to puſh and gore to death by himſelf, and to make Good the <hi>Prophecy,</hi> He is a <hi>Horn,</hi> yet but a <hi>Little one;</hi> and therefore it is generally done by the other <hi>Horns</hi> for Him, when <hi>Iron</hi> is required.</p>
               <p>Now in all this <hi>Imagery,</hi> There appears a Recapitulation of the <hi>whole Image,</hi> commanded by the <hi>King of Babylon</hi> to be <hi>worſhipped;</hi> In the wiſe <hi>Providence of God,</hi> the laſt ſtate of the <hi>Image</hi> is enſhrin'd, as it were in an <hi>Image,</hi> ſets up the great <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Image-worſhip,</hi> cas'd up, and veil'd under reverence to <hi>God,</hi> and to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to the <hi>Holy ones;</hi> And for the ſake of this <hi>Imagery,</hi> the Servants of God are made Sacrifices to Flames, and all kinds of death really and effectively, though under an <hi>Image,</hi> and by an <hi>Image;</hi> In the ſame manner there is a Recapitulation of the <hi>Beaſts</hi> in the <hi>Little Horn;</hi> For He is <hi>Leopard,</hi> as it were all over; <hi>Antiochus,</hi> that infamous <hi>Little Horn</hi> of the <hi>Graecian Leopard</hi> in its <hi>four Heads</hi> was his exact <hi>Type,</hi> betwixt whom, and this <hi>Roman Beast, Daniel</hi> twice notes the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion; paſſing over the <hi>Pagan Empire: c.</hi> 8. 23. <hi>c.</hi> 11. 36. This <hi>Beast</hi> had alſo the broad <hi>Feet</hi> of a <hi>Bear,</hi> reſembling <hi>Hamans Letters</hi> ſign'd by the <hi>Perſian Ahaſuerus,</hi> throughout his 150 <hi>Provinces</hi> to put to death the <hi>Jews;</hi> So the <hi>Beast</hi> by his <hi>Ten Kings</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his <hi>Kindred, Tongues</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> cauſes the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> to <hi>dye,</hi> by the decrees like the <hi>Mouth of the Babylonian Lyon Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> commanding <hi>Idolatrous Image worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus we ſee every way what a definitive Character of the laſt <hi>Roman ſtate,</hi> the <hi>Image made to the Beast</hi> is.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervat. </seg>3</label> Let us obſerve, how <hi>Prophecy</hi> is <hi>Fulfill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</hi> in the laſt ſtate of the <hi>Image,</hi> in that Character or Note of the <hi>Feet,</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:106747:36"/> as <hi>part of Iron, part of Clay;</hi> that tho' the <hi>Iron,</hi> and the <hi>Clay</hi> ſhall mingle, They ſhall not <hi>Cleave.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is admirably anſwer'd in Two Things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the notorious diſtinction of <hi>Eccleſiaſtick,</hi> and <hi>Secular</hi> or <hi>Laic,</hi> the latter of which cannot without great Profanation, and even ſacriledg be confounded with the Former; A thing very ſtrange to <hi>Apoſtolick writings,</hi> wherein the whole <hi>Flock</hi> are call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a <hi>Holy Prieſthood, the Church;</hi> And the Miniſters of the <hi>Goſpel, Elders</hi> and <hi>Preſidents,</hi> noting onely order, and not diſtinction of any other kind; Although therefore the <hi>Spirituality,</hi> as They are call'd, often invade the <hi>Secular Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> and <hi>Power;</hi> Yet it is in the Guarb and Canonical habit of <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtic,</hi> to keep that Character High and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delible, herein the <hi>Little Horn</hi> was in <hi>Daniel</hi>'s <hi>Prophecy</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark'd ſo <hi>diverſe</hi> from the <hi>other Horns. Dan.</hi> 7. 24.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It imports the always ſeparableneſs, and the certain Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, that ſhall be betwixt the two Powers, when theſe <hi>Ten Kings</hi> ſhall <hi>hate the Whore,</hi> and <hi>burn her Fleſh with Fire;</hi> So that though the <hi>Kings,</hi> or <hi>Feet of Iron,</hi> as well as of <hi>Clap,</hi> ſhall be broken, as is foretold of Them; Yet it is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood onely, as they are parts of the <hi>Image,</hi> and as toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the <hi>Clay</hi> they make the <hi>Feet</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> and are as <hi>Horns</hi> on the <hi>Head</hi> of a <hi>Beast;</hi> whenever they ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the <hi>Papacy,</hi> They become <hi>Princes of the Reformation,</hi> and if zealous, and ſincere therein, They are with the <hi>Lamb,</hi> as his <hi>Faithful, Called,</hi> and <hi>Choſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of this, for near theſe Hundred, and Eighty years laſt paſt, God hath been pleas'd to give an <hi>Exemplar</hi> though but very Imperfect in Compariſon, of what ſhall be, in that Separation, Princes, and States, ſtyled <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have made from the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> But how dark and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure is it, and how much brighter ſhall it be, when it ſhall be done univerſally, by all theſe <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> and their <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,</hi> when the <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> ſhall be drawn of, and the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt</hi> ſhall be in its ſucceſſion.</p>
               <p>The very ſame ought to be acknowledg'd of the <hi>Reformed Epiſcopacy;</hi> It is by no means to be confounded with the <hi>Feet</hi> of <hi>Clay,</hi> whoſe <hi>Idolatrous Apoſtaſie,</hi> degrades them to ſo low a Station; Yet it were to deal deceitfully in the <hi>divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> not to ſay; That a much higher ſtate of the <hi>Churches of Chriſt</hi> ſhall ſuperſede preſent Conſtitutions by the very dawns of the glory of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:106747:36"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſervat. </seg>4</label> It is no Indiſcernable Character of this <hi>Roman ſtate</hi> in its <hi>Feet of Iron</hi> and <hi>Clay,</hi> that it remains to this day, waiting, as it were, for that ſtroke, from the <hi>Stone cut out of the Mountains without Hands:</hi> For it hath already, as hath been noted, conſum'd more Time, then had paſs'd before it from that ſo fam'd <hi>Ere</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs condita,</hi> or the <hi>building of Rome;</hi> But becauſe this is matter yet to come, and when it is come will put all out of doubt, I ſhall onely obſerve, that as in theſe two <hi>Viſions</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> ſo in the <hi>Apoſtle Paul,</hi> and in the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> Notes of Ruin, <hi>Comſumption, Abolition Son of Perdition, going into Perdition,</hi> Being <hi>deliver'd to the conſuming Flames, the Beast taken with his falſe Prophet,</hi> and caſt into the <hi>Lake,</hi> are Brands deeply ſet upon Him; and together with his <hi>Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> the <hi>Glory of the Kingdom of Christ</hi> is declared, which is ſo certain an Aſſurance, that neither the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> is yet come, nor this laſt ſtate of the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> yet paſt, that a greater cannot be given. And when theſe things are, Then ſhall the whole <hi>Image</hi> in its <hi>Idolatrous Frame</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure, Fall,</hi> and be <hi>Broken,</hi> and <hi>Riſe no more:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>Roman Monarchy</hi> in the <hi>Feet</hi> is the very Foundation of the whole <hi>Image;</hi> As the <hi>Feet</hi> are to all parts of the <hi>Body,</hi> So alſo are theſe <hi>Feet,</hi> and <hi>Toes</hi> to the <hi>Image;</hi> And becauſe, They are <hi>part of Clay,</hi> thither is the ſtroke eſpecially directed, and there is the <hi>Image</hi> to be <hi>broken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as the <hi>Gold</hi> of the <hi>Head</hi> Communicated its luſtre; the <hi>Silver, Braſs,</hi> and <hi>Iron</hi> Communicated their value, and ſtrength to all the parts; and as the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of the whole <hi>Image</hi> gave it <hi>Dread</hi> and <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality of power;</hi> So the <hi>Clay,</hi> on which the <hi>Image</hi> ſtands, as part of the <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes</hi> Communicated its <hi>Weakneſs, Brittleneſs,</hi> and under thoſe, as <hi>Types,</hi> its <hi>Antichriſtianiſm</hi> to the whole; So that the <hi>Clay,</hi> Symbolizing that <hi>Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> is inſerted in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. 45.</note> betwixt the <hi>Iron,</hi> the <hi>Braſs,</hi> the <hi>Silver,</hi> and the <hi>Gold;</hi> To ſhew, it communicated it ſelf to the whole; and by it the force of the blow was diſtributed through the whole, ſo that All was <hi>Broken,</hi> that made up that Compoſition of the <hi>Image</hi> with the <hi>Clay;</hi> and ſo far, as it was tainted with that <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtianiſm,</hi> it is utterly <hi>Broken,</hi> and made as the <hi>chaff of the Summer Floor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as if <hi>Samſons ſtrength</hi> had paſs'd from his <hi>Head,</hi> and <hi>Locks,</hi> where it firſt dwelt, while the dimenſions, and particular Characters of his perſon remain'd; and ſo come down from
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106747:37"/> higher to lower to his very <hi>Feet,</hi> and there <hi>Broken;</hi> So have we ſeen the <hi>Monarchic Spirit,</hi> aod <hi>Life,</hi> here deſcrib'd, paſſing from <hi>Mettal</hi> to <hi>Mettal,</hi> from part to part, comming down to the <hi>Feet,</hi> the Seat of that <hi>Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> that is to be <hi>Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi> and the whole <hi>Image</hi> with it to <hi>Powder;</hi> And ſeeing theſe <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Toes</hi> have continued ſo many Ages beyond all the former parts, how can we but earneſtly pray for that happy Revolution; and if we are not ſo in Love with that ſtate, as to pray ſo for it, yet however we ſhould fear, and prepare for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Thus far I have been repreſenting the real, and ſolid part of the <hi>Calendar,</hi> of which I cannot doubt the Satisfaction, It hath given to every obſerving Mind; It now remains, that the numeral, though <hi>myſtic</hi> part of it be conſider'd under that Characteriſm of it; <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time</hi> in the <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Daniel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that this may be underſtood, It muſt be expounded to us by that ſo divinely Learned, and truly infallible Key of it, and of the whole Prophecy of <hi>Daniel,</hi> the <hi>Apocalyptical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> and the Expoſition it gives, is as in a Complication of Charactoriſms of Time; <hi>Twice forty two Months, Twice twelve hundred, and ſixty days,</hi> and <hi>Twice three Times,</hi> and a <hi>Half,</hi> but with the little variation of <hi>Three Days</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> for the great Reaſon of alluding to our <hi>Lords three Days</hi> in the <hi>Grave;</hi> that we might learn to find a deeper, and more intimate part in the ſpace given, as <hi>our Lord</hi> was but a deep part of the firſt, the whole of the ſecond, and a ſmall deep part, <hi>viz.</hi> the very dawn or Morning-Break of the <hi>Third Day</hi> in the Grave; which yet is call'd, being <hi>Three Days and Three Nights in the Heart of the Earth.</hi> This plainly teaches us, there was parallel-wiſe in theſe; <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> a <hi>Time;</hi> a deeper Tyranny of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and of the <hi>Apoſtolical Church</hi> cclips'd by it; and its <hi>Seed,</hi> the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ſuffering under it, in ſome parts of theſe Times, then in others.</p>
               <p>And Theſe Things I have more at large handled in their proper place of the <hi>Line of Time,</hi> and ſhall now only recal what is neceſſary to preſent this Time more at full.</p>
               <p>And in the firſt place It is duly to be Remark'd, that as <hi>the Spirit</hi> gave a <hi>Calendar,</hi> however <hi>Myſtic,</hi> but juſt at the <hi>Riſing</hi> of the <hi>Ten Horns</hi> on the <hi>Head of the Fourth Roman Beaſt,</hi> which appears the <hi>ſeventh Head</hi> or <hi>Papacy</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> with his <hi>Ten Horns</hi> or <hi>Kings,</hi> and He a <hi>little Horn</hi> among them; So in the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106747:37"/> 
                  <hi>Revelation,</hi> It affixes thoſe Charecteriſms of Time to the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles coming in to the outward Court,</hi> and to the <hi>Witneſſes putting on Sackcloth,</hi> and to the <hi>Church fled into the Wilderneſs</hi> upon it; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the Times of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> who is the <hi>ſeventh Head</hi> of the <hi>Fourth Beaſt in Daniel,</hi> which we have proved to be <hi>Roman;</hi> and to his <hi>Ten Horns,</hi> and to the <hi>Woman</hi> perſecuted by the <hi>Dragon, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king War with its Seed by the Beaſt, to whom he gave his Throne, Power, &amp;c. Killing her Seed the Witneſſes.</hi> By which as alſo by the very expreſs uſe of <hi>Three Times,</hi> and <hi>Half the Spirit</hi> hath, if we will receive it, demonſtrated to us; That the <hi>Ten Horns,</hi> and <hi>Little Horn</hi> in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and its <hi>Ten Horns</hi> in the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament-Prophet John</hi> are the very ſame <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Time is <hi>doubled</hi> in the <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and the <hi>Woman</hi> both for the <hi>certainty,</hi> and alſo explanation of the <hi>Church</hi> not to be found, as the <hi>Beaſts</hi> and <hi>Romaniſts</hi> vaunt before <hi>Luther;</hi> but Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectively as a <hi>Church, Woman,</hi> or <hi>Mother, Hid in the Wilderneſs,</hi> and yet diſtricutively <hi>War'd with,</hi> and <hi>kill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</hi> in ſingle Saints, or <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> as its <hi>Seed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now it is moſt Evident, that in every one of theſe <hi>Characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſms of Time, Three equal parts</hi> and a <hi>Half part</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> are ſtill moſt clearly, and peremptorily defin'd, that we may thereby be moſt aſſuredly guided in the Calculation, or Computation of the whole ſpace; And then, they are made up into eighty four <hi>Indictions,</hi> giving a broad Indication, It was a Time ſoon after <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> that was intended to be defin'd; For ſo, ſoon after Him, <hi>Indictions</hi> came to be general Characters of Time, being as Chronologers moſt agree, inſtituted under him.</p>
               <p>That we may then find the fundamental Reaſon of this Time, we muſt conſider, that the Kingdom of Chriſt having made an Appearance, and given a Specimen of it ſelf, as hath been ſhewn, It was <hi>Eſtop'd</hi> by that <hi>Oath of Chriſt;</hi> There ſhall be <hi>Time, Times</hi> and half a <hi>Time</hi> for that <hi>Kingdom</hi> to be under an <hi>Eclipſe;</hi> In which Time, That <hi>He,</hi> the <hi>little Horn</hi> made ſo Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. ſhould <hi>ſcatter the Power of the Holy People,</hi> or drive the <hi>Church</hi> into the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> for thoſe <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Accordingly <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. This very <hi>Eclipſe</hi> is repreſented to come to paſs; For the Kingdom of Chriſt, from <hi>Conſtantines Chriſtian Retgn</hi> to the Death of <hi>Theodoſius the Great,</hi> as the <hi>Church cloathed with the Sun;</hi> had the <hi>Beſtian Pagan Kingdom</hi> compar'd with the <hi>Moon, under its Feet,</hi> as it were <hi>diametrally;</hi> Hereupon there begins a gradual darkneſs, or <hi>Eclipſe</hi> upon the <hi>True</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:106747:38"/> 
                  <hi>Church;</hi> For the <hi>Pagan, Beſtian Kingdom,</hi> being now to become <hi>Antichriſtian-Beaſtian,</hi> That <hi>Antichriſtian Beaſtian Kingdom</hi> bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows (as the Moon in an Eclipſe does) moſt Light and Glory from the Sun, and yet <hi>Eclipſes</hi> that <hi>Light from the World;</hi> For it turns its own dark obſcure ſhade downward, and retires the Light from above.</p>
               <p>How does this moſt admirably Reſemble the <hi>Antichriſtian Church,</hi> in which former <hi>Paganiſm</hi> finding it ſelf ſo to lye un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Sun,</hi> takes as it were, the advantage to guild it ſelf with the Beams of <hi>Christianity;</hi> It takes upon it ſelf the <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith,</hi> the Acknowledgment of Scripture, the names of <hi>Christ,</hi> and of his Saints, the ſtyle of <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And all this it does, That it may engroſs to it ſelf Thoſe Titles of honour, and Glory, that Riches, and ſplendor which is onely due to the True, and pure <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereby it robs the World of the Light, and glory of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> for inſtead of thoſe powerful, and enlivening rays, it caſts upon the Earth, <hi>Idolatry, Superſtition, Ceremony, Foppery of Religion,</hi> which are ancient <hi>Paganiſm Antichriſtianiz'd,</hi> and muſt needs chill, make wan and pale all appearances of <hi>Goſpel Truth,</hi> ſo far, as any were, but in deed rather darken and obſcure them, altogether, as truly <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and this indeed was turning <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> as much as is poſſible into <hi>Fable,</hi> according to that <hi>Papal Prophaneſs,</hi> that ſtyl'd it ſo, when themſelves had made it ſo.</p>
               <p>Together with this obſcuring of Truth; that Honour, and Glory moſt due to the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> and to his <hi>Servants,</hi> that ſhould fill the World, is ſo intercepted by the <hi>Children of the Night,</hi> uſurping it; that while the <hi>Church</hi> is in the <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> and unſeen, tho' <hi>cloath'd with the Sun,</hi> its <hi>Seed, the Witneſſes,</hi> that ſhould ſhine with the ſame Beams, are <hi>cover'd with Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth</hi> according to the <hi>Prophetical</hi> alluſion; the <hi>Sun became as Sackcloth</hi> of <hi>Hair;</hi> and <hi>Kill'd all the day long.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Never was ſhade, or portraicture thus fitted to the life, but who, as the <hi>divine Spirit,</hi> can at the ſame Time hide in <hi>Cyphar,</hi> and yet <hi>declare the thing plentifully, as it is?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now this Time of the <hi>Eclipſe</hi> is determin'd to be <hi>Twelve Hundred ſixty prophetical days,</hi> or years of the <hi>Sun,</hi> whoſe ſtate is to guide, and determine this Time; In which regard the <hi>Moon,</hi> that is, the Times of the <hi>Moon,</hi> are under <hi>its Feet,</hi> and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106747:38"/> to be guided, and over-rul'd by it; It comes then to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, that the <hi>Times of the Moon</hi> are not equal to the <hi>Times of the Sun;</hi> For the Time, in which the Moon meaſures the <hi>Zodiac</hi> twelve Times, and hath as often New Congreſſes with the Sun, and thereby makes the <hi>lunar year,</hi> is agreed to be, as near, as can be computed a thirty eighth part leſs, then what the <hi>Sun</hi> requires to viſit the <hi>Twelve Signs</hi> of the <hi>Zodiac,</hi> and to give twelve meetings to the <hi>Moon</hi> in its yearly Courſe; ſo that the Moon is advanced near eleven days in the ſtage of a New Year, before the <hi>Sun</hi> hath finiſh'd any year.</p>
               <p>Proportionably the <hi>Beaſts Times</hi> and <hi>Half Time</hi> are expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Revelation</hi> by <hi>Forty two,</hi> not only <hi>Months,</hi> but <hi>Moons;</hi> For every ſeveral <hi>Month</hi> is as under another <hi>Moon,</hi> call'd therefore, a <hi>New Moon,</hi> and therefore <hi>Months</hi> muſt be <hi>Times</hi> of the <hi>Moon,</hi> for they are <hi>Moons;</hi> but the <hi>Moon</hi> is not the <hi>Sun;</hi> If therefore Theſe <hi>Moons</hi> had begun at the ſame Time, the <hi>twelve hundred ſixty days</hi> began, They muſt have ended Thirty eight years ſooner, then They could end according to the <hi>Symbol;</hi> For then the Eclipſe ſhould have laſted, when the Moon had no longer been ſo poſited, as to intercept the <hi>Suns</hi> Beams, that is, the <hi>Glory of Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore in the <hi>Jews</hi> Times, from whom This, as All the other <hi>Types</hi> in this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> relating to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Servants of Chriſt</hi> are taken; There was the <hi>Intercalation</hi> of a <hi>ſecond Adar</hi> the laſt <hi>Jewiſh Month,</hi> betwixt each precedent and following year, that was to be <hi>intercalar,</hi> that it might ſupply the hollow, or vacuity in the <hi>Moons</hi> Time, and guide the <hi>Paſchal New Moon</hi> in its due regard to the <hi>vernal Sun,</hi> to keep Time with it.</p>
               <p>Now the Rule of this <hi>Intercalation;</hi> becauſe the balance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Motion of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and of the <hi>Moon;</hi> was the <hi>Decem-Novennal Cycle,</hi> or ſo generally known <hi>Golden Number.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And laſtly, this <hi>Intercalation</hi> was generally neceſſary, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Third year,</hi> of all which particulars the Treatiſe of that learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Jew, Maimonides,</hi> concerning the <hi>New Moons</hi> and <hi>Intercalati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is a Great Teſtimony, and his <hi>ſixth Chapter</hi> gives Great Light to the <hi>Type,</hi> we are are upon.</p>
               <p>For proportionably, The <hi>Forty two Months</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are, as <hi>Intercalary,</hi> to the <hi>Months of the Beaſts,</hi> and begin Thirty eight years before them, and are, as it were, a <hi>ſecond,</hi> ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental <hi>Adar,</hi> to the Time of the <hi>Draconic ſixth Head,</hi> and come in as a fit ſpace of the <hi>Dragons</hi> giving his <hi>Throne to the Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106747:39"/>
               <p> For the Barbarous Nations are call'd <hi>Gentiles,</hi> becauſe They ravag'd on the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> the <hi>Emblem of Chriſts Kingdom,</hi> though indeed <hi>Sathan</hi> by Them, as hath been ſay'd, miſs'd his Aim; For the <hi>Empire</hi> was now <hi>Antichriſtianiz'd,</hi> and the <hi>True Church hid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet their coming into the <hi>outward Cuort of the Empire,</hi> and of the <hi>Profeſſion of Chriſtianity,</hi> and to become the <hi>Beaſts People,</hi> manag'd at firſt by the <hi>other Beaſt,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtian Roman Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> God was pleas'd to ordain as the beginning of the <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> upon which the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> put on <hi>their Sackcloth,</hi> and the <hi>Woman</hi> actually <hi>fled into the Wilderneſs,</hi> and the <hi>Twelve hundred ſixty days</hi> began; And becauſe the Beaſts Moons did not begin till thirty eight years after; Here is the <hi>Intercalation</hi> of the <hi>Thirty eighth part,</hi> the <hi>Beaſts Moons</hi> would want; and given in two <hi>Nineteens</hi> or <hi>Cycles of the Moon,</hi> ſetting right the <hi>Moon</hi> to the <hi>Sun,</hi> that ſo the <hi>Moon</hi> of the <hi>Antichriſtian Beſtian Kingdom</hi> might be in its juſt Time under the <hi>Suns Feet,</hi> with which the <hi>Church</hi> was <hi>cloath'd,</hi> to <hi>Eclipſe</hi> it.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>Type</hi> is ſo wonderful, as not poſſibly to fall into this Model of Time by chance, with that <hi>admirable</hi> Congruity, and therefore cannot be look'd upon, but as divinely deſign'd, and ſo to be accepted, as demonſtrative; That the <hi>Beasts Months</hi> beginning at 475. There muſt have been Thirty eight years of <hi>Beſtian</hi> preparatory Time before them; with the firſt of which the <hi>twelve hundred ſixty days,</hi> or years beginning, All may end together 1697.</p>
               <p>And if it be ask'd, what becomes of the <hi>Months</hi> of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> after the <hi>Beaſts Months</hi> enter'd; and of the Action of the <hi>other Beaſt,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtian Hierarchy,</hi> who exercis'd the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Draconic Beaſt,</hi> and ſpake as the <hi>Dragon,</hi> not dead, but to live in the <hi>Antichriſtian Beaſt;</hi> The Anſwer is; The <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles Months</hi> merg'd into the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> who had <hi>Power given Him over all Kindreds, Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Nations,</hi> as an <hi>Antichriſtian Head;</hi> and ſo though for the Grace of the Type, They are given, as <hi>Forty two Months;</hi> yet They are drown'd in the <hi>Beaſts Months</hi> after They have done their Service of <hi>Intercalation,</hi> before the <hi>Beaſts Months began;</hi> even as ſmaller Accounts of Time are ſwallowed up in that of the Reigns of Supreme Princes, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting All Times; Then alſo the <hi>other Beaſt</hi> became the <hi>Beaſts falſe Prophet,</hi> the Tutor or Guardian of his Infantile Power, till He came to his manly <hi>Number</hi> 666. and after that, his Inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Spirit, and Intelligence; as hath appear'd in all <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels;</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:106747:39"/> before the <hi>Beaſts Times,</hi> wherein the Hierarchy had been Heaving the Papacy into an Antichriſtian Idolatrous Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy; The Dawn of which was viſible in the Councel of <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> within the <hi>Gentiles Intercalary Months;</hi> within his <hi>Times</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming and ſwelling it to a Height, as in the <hi>ſecond Councel of Nice,</hi> and in the <hi>Lateran Councels</hi> of the <hi>Eleventh,</hi> and <hi>Twelfth Centuries;</hi> Or ſupporting the declining State of it, as in that laſt Famous <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> in his <hi>Half Time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beſides all, that hath been ſpoken, let us, but take <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time;</hi> and we may by one eaſie way of Argument, and in which any one may ſatisfie himſelf, aſſure our ſelves in this determination of Time, that I have made.</p>
               <p>For when a <hi>Calendar of Time</hi> is given in <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time,</hi> as the meaſure of that ſpace, wherein a <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> as of returning <hi>Pagan Bestianiſm,</hi> ſhould <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> and obſcure the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> after it had given an <hi>Emblem</hi> and appearance of it ſelf, (which is the Foundation of the whole <hi>Type)</hi> the very Frame and aſpect of ſuch a <hi>Calendar</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily imports, that the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Times</hi> are Three equal parts, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Time</hi> one ſingle part, and <hi>Times</hi> Two equal parts in themſelves, but double, when conjoyn'd; and then the <hi>Half Time</hi> the juſt Half of any of thoſe equal parts.</p>
               <p>And thus the explication of <hi>Time, Times, Half a Time</hi> by thoſe ſo particular <hi>Characteriſms</hi> aſſure us; For <hi>Twelve hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſixty days,</hi> and <hi>Forty two Monnhs</hi> neceſſarily carry us up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Three equal years, and one Half year; and <hi>Three days</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> are yet more expreſs, that There are Three equal parts, and one Half part of any of the Three equal parts, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be given.</p>
               <p>Now that theſe are explanatory of theſe <hi>three Times</hi> and a <hi>Half</hi> is in two Inſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>twelve Hundred ſixty days</hi> and of the <hi>Beaſts Forty two Months</hi> moſt clear, which is enough to the preſent purpoſe; For the <hi>twelve Hundred ſixty days</hi> and the Three <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Half,</hi> are both the meaſure of the ſpace of the <hi>Woman in the Wilderneſs,</hi> and ſo the ſame; And the <hi>three Times</hi> and <hi>Half,</hi> and the <hi>Beaſts Forty two Months</hi> are both given, as the ſpace of the <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>little Horn in Daniel</hi> and of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> both which I have already prov'd are the ſame, and therefore the <hi>Times,</hi> and the <hi>Forty two Months</hi> muſt be neceſſarily the ſame; and ſo equal in the Three parts, and a half part.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:106747:40"/>
               <p> But further, when the <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> are thus diſtributed, and with ſuch alluſion to the <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Burial</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as in the <hi>Witneſſes lying dead three days and a Half.</hi> It is both in the thing it ſelf, as in the alluſion moſt evident, that the <hi>firſt Time</hi> is allowed for the Aſcendency of this <hi>Kingdom of the Beaſt,</hi> till the <hi>Eclipſe</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> by it becomes <hi>Total;</hi> The <hi>two Times</hi> are the uniform Continuation of things in that very State, the end of the Firſt <hi>Time</hi> left Them; But when It comes to a <hi>Half Time,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom of the Beaſt,</hi> being at the very moment of that <hi>Half Time</hi> entring, what It was, all the <hi>Two Times;</hi> It juſt then comes under a check, and ſurpriſe, and can continue the <hi>Total Eclipſe</hi> no longer; but ſhall continue a partial <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> till the <hi>Half Time</hi> given to Him be alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pir'd: Then that Kingdom ſhall be preſcinded, as at the <hi>middle,</hi> with both Ruin, and Infamy; upon which the <hi>Glory of Chriſt,</hi> his <hi>Kingdom, Church</hi> and <hi>People</hi> ſo long <hi>Eclipſed</hi> ſhall at the End of that <hi>Half Time</hi> ſhine out much more gloriouſly, then ever yet It hath done, and after a ſhort preparation, to a <hi>perfect day</hi> without any more <hi>Night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us then examine, at what Time the <hi>Half Time</hi> enter'd, which may be certainly known by that check, and ſurprize upon the <hi>Antichriſtian Kingdom,</hi> that It could no longer totally <hi>Eclipſe</hi> the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> as it had done; And what Time that was, there is a <hi>Vox Populi,</hi> a common ſaying, even of the <hi>Antichriſtian People,</hi> that indeed is <hi>Vox Dei,</hi> the very <hi>Oracle of God</hi> concerning the <hi>Half Time;</hi> Where, ſay They, was your Church before <hi>Luther?</hi> that is; It was before indeed all along from Chriſt, but It was for <hi>Time,</hi> and <hi>Two Times</hi> under an <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> even <hi>Total,</hi> that It could not be ſeen before <hi>Luther</hi>'s Time; From his Time It hath been (bleſſed be God) to be ſeen, but not as It ſhall be at the End of the <hi>Half Time,</hi> ſo here is evidently the <hi>Half Time</hi> begun.</p>
               <p>Now what <hi>Chronology</hi> is not agree'd, that <hi>Luther</hi> appear'd at 1517? Here then, <hi>viz.</hi> at 1517, the <hi>Half Time</hi> moſt certainly Began; For from that Time, not any accidental change, or for a Time, but an unmoveable <hi>Reformation,</hi> and Retrenchment upon the <hi>Antichriſtian Kingdom</hi> hath enſued in the revolt of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and States from it; And how unmovable it hath been; So univerſal conſent in the late Revolution, as it appear'd againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> is in this <hi>Proteſtant Nation</hi> a Monument, undoubtedly ſet up by God as a <hi>Specimen,</hi> what ſhall be at the end of the <hi>Half Time,</hi> whatever Judgment our ſins may in the mean Time provoke upon us!</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:106747:40"/>
               <p> Being thus aſſur'd then, when the <hi>Half Time</hi> began, we are alſo moſt certain, the <hi>Half Time</hi> is a Half, equal to each of the Three equal parts; In twelve hundred and ſixty therefore, an equal Half part to each equal whole part muſt be one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and eighty; And if this Half part begin at 1517. It muſt end at 1697. by a conſequence undeniable.</p>
               <p>And then, if from 1517. where the <hi>Half Time</hi> began, we carry backward one Thouſand and Eighty, the juſt Amount of the three equal parts, They muſt needs reach back by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trograde motion to Anno 437. of the <hi>Chriſtian Account;</hi> at which Time the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> were every where, carving their <hi>Kingdoms</hi> out of the <hi>Empire,</hi> under the play of the <hi>firſt Trumpet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the <hi>Gentiles</hi> at that very time came, as before explain'd, into the <hi>outward Court,</hi> and their <hi>Forty two Months</hi> began, and gave Thirty eight <hi>Intercalar</hi> years, till the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and the <hi>Ten Kings receiv'd Power,</hi> as hath been explain'd, which was at 475, as was before explain'd.</p>
               <p>And thus the <hi>Times</hi> of the <hi>Beaſts Moon,</hi> ſo <hi>under</hi> the <hi>Feet</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> as to <hi>Ecclipſe</hi> it, by ſurprizing the Glory proper to it, as <hi>Cloath'd with the Sun,</hi> are made equal to the Times of the <hi>Church in the Wilderneſs,</hi> and of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> in their Sackcloth, and run equal with them to the end; and the <hi>Gentiles Months</hi> are of no further conſiderations but moſt naturally, and ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milarly ſink into the <hi>Months</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and are united with them.</p>
               <p>And yet laſtly, to make this <hi>Calendar</hi> moſt undoubted, If we ſhould lay aſide the diſtinction betwixt <hi>Lunar</hi> and <hi>Solar</hi> Time, and the <hi>Intercalation</hi> upon it, and take the <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half Time</hi> as of the <hi>little Horn</hi> onely, abſolutely, and by themſelves; Yet allowing the <hi>Little Horn,</hi> the ſame with the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> the <hi>eigth King,</hi> ſucceding the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> at 475; as hath been ſo fully prov'd, and let the <hi>Half Time,</hi> as hath been alſo prov'd enter with <hi>Luther,</hi> they will come to the very ſame point of 1697; if we allow but five Years from <hi>Luther</hi> 1517, <hi>viz.</hi> till 1522 for the revolts from the <hi>Beſtian Kingdom,</hi> which <hi>Reformed Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> in that Time made; and which have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to this day; at which very Time <hi>Images,</hi> and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of them, of greateſt Intereſt in <hi>Beſtianiſm</hi> began to be caſt out; And then proportion the Times, and half Time among themſelves; (as was before moſt undeniably ſtated) The expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients of <hi>Lunar Time,</hi> and of <hi>Intercalation</hi> will be more neceſſary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ſet the <hi>Beſtian Time</hi> at an even ballance with the whole <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calyptical</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:106747:41"/> 
                  <hi>Emblem</hi> both of the ſtate and Characters of this Time, then to make certain the <hi>Calendar,</hi> and its computation. For <hi>Luther</hi>'s appearance or ſo very little diſtant from it, as not to deſtroy the very ſymbol of the <hi>Half Time,</hi> is ſo certain a <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier</hi> of that <hi>Half Time;</hi> and the <hi>Ceſſation</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> ſo certain an <hi>Epoch</hi> of the three equal <hi>Times,</hi> that we cannot fail of proportioning them all amongſt themſeves and knowing, the longeſt of their duration can be but till 1697.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Calendar</hi> being thus determin'd, let us conſider the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution, and as the <hi>Half Time</hi> hath appear'd to be a Time of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination; So the <hi>firſt Time</hi> Comprehended his ſucceſſion, his aſcending to <hi>Supremacy</hi> receiv'd from <hi>Phocas,</hi> ratified by a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel at <hi>Rome</hi> ſoon after; and ſo onwards his <hi>Beſtianiſm</hi> and <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous</hi> eſtabliſhing <hi>Imageworſhip</hi> by the <hi>ſecond Counſel of Nice;</hi> His becomming a <hi>little Horn,</hi> and rooting up any <hi>Horns</hi> in his way, his diſpoſing of Crowns, and Excommunicating <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours;</hi> All which he attain'd before 797. the Period of his <hi>first Time,</hi> acording to the ballance of it, with the 1260. day; And the conſtituting and Crowning as <hi>Emperour Charls the Great</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> very cloſe to it in the year 800. and within it, if we Calculate the <hi>Times and Half</hi> of the <hi>little Horn,</hi> (as we may with very little variation do) within themſelves.</p>
               <p>This Obſervation of the <hi>Beast</hi> riſing, as from an <hi>Infantile</hi> State, ſhews us; The <hi>Revelation</hi> conſiders his ſucceſſion as an <hi>Imperial Beſtian Seventh Head</hi> bearing <hi>ten Horns,</hi> who becoming within his firſt Time, a <hi>little Horn</hi> alſo, himſelf riſes according to <hi>Daniel,</hi> to his <hi>number</hi> at his powerful and effective <hi>Image;</hi> And this ariſing to and ſettlement of power very naturally agrees with the firſt Time of any Potentacy.</p>
               <p>His <hi>two Times,</hi> however full of variety of accidents, as All worldly power is, yet ſpeak one main, and deep of power, as the <hi>two Times</hi> are joyn'd; but with ſome little diſtinction, as they are <hi>two Times;</hi> in which there was a ſpread of the roots and Branches of <hi>Beſtian</hi> power; <hi>viz.</hi> in the coupling of the <hi>two Times;</hi> and ſo we may obſerve at that very Time, <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>Eleventh,</hi> and <hi>Twelth Centuries;</hi> enlarged <hi>Idolatries</hi> to the <hi>Hoaſt,</hi> more Blaſphemous aſſumptions in the <hi>Temple,</hi> and <hi>Church of God;</hi> His <hi>Perſecution</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Churches of Christ,</hi> more Bloody; the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> and <hi>Waldenſes</hi> is the Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid of it; His <hi>Exaltation</hi> of himſelf above all, even the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Names of <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and <hi>Empire</hi> more prodigious, and <hi>Lucife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian;</hi> as the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of his Treaty of the <hi>German Emperors,</hi> and of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106747:41"/> our own <hi>King John,</hi> are abundant Teſtimonies: Theſe things were moſt notorious about the latter part of the <hi>Firſt</hi> of the <hi>two Times</hi> ending 1157. and the ſecond of the <hi>two Times</hi> beginning, when the other ended.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Half Time</hi> is remarkable for the <hi>Cutting</hi> off ſuch a <hi>Lap</hi> of his <hi>Beſtian Purple,</hi> and <hi>Scarlet,</hi> with ſo much Diſhonor; the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance yet of ſo Great a part as neceſſary to his <hi>Half Time;</hi> and that yet more Infamous and Deſtructive ſtroke on theſe <hi>Feet of Clay,</hi> that now hangs over Him, and will certainly Fall by his <hi>Periodical,</hi> and <hi>Fatal</hi> 1697. Thus every way is our <hi>Calendar</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd in the whole, and in the Diſtribution.</p>
               <p>And with how great Grace do theſe <hi>three Times,</hi> and <hi>Half</hi> agree with that <hi>Moon</hi> intercepting and ſo <hi>Eclipſing</hi> the <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> firſt <hi>partial,</hi> till after the middle of the <hi>Firſt Time;</hi> then <hi>total</hi> till the end of the <hi>Two Times;</hi> At the <hi>Half Time</hi> the Firſt Re-appearances of Light were very ſurprizing; But there is yet an obſcurity; But It ſhall at laſt ſo go off, So that the <hi>Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> ſhall <hi>ſhine out in its Strength,</hi> and the <hi>Light of one Day</hi> ſhall be then as the <hi>Light of any ſeven,</hi> that have been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, ſince the <hi>Reformation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> Now if It ſhould ſeem any Diſparagement to the <hi>Calendar,</hi> that the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> ſo vaſt <hi>Empire</hi> hath no place in it, though ſeated in ſo large Traicts of the Ancient <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and in the <hi>Imperial City</hi> of its <hi>Eaſtern Empire, Conſtantinople,</hi> call'd <hi>New Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> The Anſwer is clear; It is ſo far from diſparaging the <hi>Calendar,</hi> that It much ſtrengthens, and Illuſtrates it; For It hereby is moſt evident, that only thoſe <hi>Four Monarchies,</hi> we have ſo much ſpoken of, make the <hi>Calendar</hi> and only in that order, wherein the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> plac'd Them; ſo that neither <hi>Perſia,</hi> nor <hi>Graece,</hi> whatever Greatneſs They have had, ſince the former was <hi>demonarchiz'd</hi> by <hi>Alexander,</hi> and the latter by the <hi>Romans,</hi> have any place in this <hi>Calendar;</hi> And though the <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh Power</hi> hath invaded ſo much, what was heretofore <hi>Roman Empire;</hi> Yet It hath been on purpoſe ſo plac'd by Divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, that It might the more cloſely offend, and annoy the <hi>Apoſtate Roman State,</hi> and be a more effective Woe upon it. In the mean Time, It hath been ſo limited, that It could never <hi>poſſeſs Rome,</hi> nor the Amplitude of the <hi>Weſtern Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet it is evident, <hi>Prophecy</hi> is not ignorant of the <hi>Mahometan Greatneſs,</hi> but moſt abundant in the deſcypharings of it, both in <hi>Daniel, Dan.</hi> 11. 40. under the <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>South,</hi> as the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racens,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:106747:42"/> and of the <hi>North</hi> in the <hi>Turks;</hi> and ſo in the <hi>Revelation, chap.</hi> 9. in the Firſt <hi>Woe Trumpet</hi> of the <hi>Locusts,</hi> and the <hi>Second Woe Trumpet</hi> of the <hi>Armed Horſemen;</hi> and that They Both Fall in with the Times of the <hi>Calendar,</hi> and are as much engrafted into it, as They have been, or are into the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> as hath been ſhown in the <hi>Line of Time;</hi> where It ought to be; and the Times of the preſent <hi>Mahometan Kingdom</hi> in the <hi>Turks</hi> ſhall certainly take End with this <hi>Calendar,</hi> when that <hi>Apoſtate Beſtianiſm</hi> ſhall ceaſe to require ſo Great a Vengeance upon the <hi>Chriſtian World;</hi> on which Account, when the <hi>Witneſſeſs</hi> enter into Glory at the <hi>Period</hi> of the 1260 <hi>Days;</hi> It is ſaid the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Woe is paſt,</hi> but a Greater <hi>Third Woe</hi> immediately ſeizes the <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> even the ſucceeding <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The naming of which by way of ſtrongeſt Intereſt ſhould oblige us to <hi>watch,</hi> and <hi>keep our Garments,</hi> that our <hi>Shame may not be ſeen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For as that <hi>Kingdom</hi> will put an utter end to all <hi>Pagan Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſm in the World,</hi> by ways and Methods known to Him, who does, <hi>whatever He pleaſes,</hi> and as It ſhall utterly deſtroy <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſm</hi> which we ſo Highly have diſavowed; So It will be as ſevere on all Formal, Ceremonial, Perſecutory <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> and not only that, but all Prophane, Irreligious <hi>Proteſtants unreform'd</hi> in Heart, <hi>unreform'd</hi> in Life; For It is a Kingdom of <hi>Truth, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> not in <hi>Word</hi> but in <hi>Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeeing, It is certainly ſo near, as I have Repreſented, and that All the Policy and Power of the World, can no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger interpoſe againſt it; but that <hi>Chriſt will take to Himſelf,</hi> his <hi>Great Power,</hi> and <hi>Reign;</hi> however Angry the <hi>Nations</hi> will be at it, and will <hi>destroy them,</hi> that have <hi>destroyed</hi> ſo long <hi>the Earth,</hi> and will <hi>ſtay the Wicked</hi> with the <hi>Rod of his Mouth,</hi> and with the <hi>Breath of his Lips;</hi> How diligent ſhould All be, to prepare for ſo Happy a <hi>Revolution,</hi> if we are <hi>found of Him in Peace;</hi> For if not, we ſhall in vain call to the <hi>Mountain to Hide us,</hi> and to the <hi>Rocks to cover us,</hi> when the <hi>Great Day of His Wrath is Come.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>The <hi>Prophetical</hi> Map of which Holy and Bleſſed State, is too large here to preſent, but it is neceſſary, that a ſhort delineation of it, ſo far, as is agreeable, to ſupport the laſt, and moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling part of the <hi>Calendar,</hi> be given.</p>
               <p>For in both the <hi>viſions,</hi> the <hi>viſion</hi> of the <hi>Image,</hi> and the <hi>viſion of the Beast;</hi> There enters at the end inſeparably, and no way poſſible to be divided a <hi>divine Kingdom,</hi> of which the expreſſions are ſo full, and high, that it is ſelf evident, the grand Intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106747:42"/> of the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> was by the <hi>four Monarchies</hi> to lead to that <hi>Supreme Kingdom,</hi> that where They end, That may begin; which is of it ſelf a great proof, that if we are thus far right in the <hi>Calendar;</hi> as the Evidence of <hi>Divine Revelation</hi> aſſures me, we are; We muſt be near ſo great, and happy a Revolution, the Complement of the <hi>Calendar;</hi> and are now as on a <hi>Piſgah</hi> view of it.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> hath an immediate ſucceſſion to the <hi>Times of the Beaſt,</hi> even as the <hi>Beſtian Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Times</hi> had to the <hi>Chriſtian Empire;</hi> The ſucceſſion is immediate, but the Illuſtrious <hi>Glory</hi> hath a Time of Preparation after the ſucceſſion.</p>
               <p>In the Face of all <hi>Prophecy</hi> This ſucceſſion appears in <hi>Daniel</hi>'s two <hi>Viſions:</hi> the <hi>Divine Kingdom follows</hi> the <hi>Feet,</hi> and the <hi>Little Horn,</hi> even ſo cloſe, as to be ſaid in <hi>their Days</hi> of <hi>thoſe ten Kings.</hi> The <hi>God of Heaven Sets up a Kingdom, Dan.</hi> 2. 47. as it were, within them, becauſe ſo juſt at the end of their Time; The <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paul</hi> tells us The approach of <hi>Christ,</hi> to the <hi>Beſtian Times</hi> is ſo near, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> blaſts Him with the <hi>Spirit of his Mouth,</hi> and brings to nothing the blaze of his <hi>Moon,</hi> by the full Glory of his own appearance: That <hi>Illuſtrious Man of Sin,</hi> the <hi>Antitype</hi> of <hi>Antiochus the Illuſtrious</hi> is ſo out-ſhone, that He is a <hi>Lamp put out in obſcure Darkneſs;</hi> In the whole view of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Chriſt's Kingdom</hi> riſes as the <hi>Beast</hi> falls; and when He, and his <hi>Falſe Prophet</hi> are <hi>caſt into the Lake;</hi> or, as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks, His <hi>Body deliver'd to the conſuming Flames,</hi> Then the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is <hi>given to Christ</hi> and his <hi>Saints,</hi> as in full Glory: They ſit on <hi>Thrones</hi> and <hi>Reign</hi> with Him.</p>
               <p>But nothing is ſo expreſs, as the <hi>Oath of Christ,</hi> as at the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Half Time,</hi> or <hi>Reformation;</hi> a beginning Glory <hi>Seal'd,</hi> or ſtay'd in the <hi>Thunders ſeal'd,</hi> till the end of the <hi>Half Time; Christ</hi> ſolemnly ſwears at that Time, There ſhall be after <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half Time</hi> allowed No more ſuch kind of <hi>Time;</hi> The falſe <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> the Counterfeit of the True is not <hi>made without an Oath,</hi> indeed; But becauſe, he is but a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit; He is cut off at his <hi>Half Time</hi> by an <hi>Oath</hi> alſo, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a Prieſt any longer; He is <hi>broken without Hand from Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſoon as ever the <hi>Oath</hi> takes place, That <hi>Time</hi> of the former date of <hi>Times</hi> and <hi>Half Time</hi> is no longer, it Immediately follows. The <hi>Myſtery of God,</hi> that is, the <hi>Glorious Kingdom of Christ,</hi> ſo much, and ſo long ſpoken of by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> ſhall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:106747:43"/> be immediately in Motion by it ſelf to its complement, and perfection.</p>
               <p>Accordingly at the end of the <hi>Twelve Hundred</hi> and <hi>ſixty days,</hi> and of the <hi>Three days and Half,</hi> the ſame, as hath been prov'd, with <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half Time;</hi> There is as in their <hi>Days</hi> of thoſe <hi>Ten Kings</hi> the appearance of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Witneſſes riſing, &amp;c.</hi> even juſt before the Blaſt of the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet;</hi> And then the <hi>Seventh Trumpet ſounds,</hi> and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there are <hi>Loud voices</hi> in <hi>Heaven;</hi> The <hi>Kingdoms of this World are become the Kingdoms</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> and of his <hi>Christ;</hi> The <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> is <hi>proclaimed</hi> and advances all the Time of the <hi>Seventy five years,</hi> in which the <hi>Twelve Hundred ſixty years,</hi> become <hi>Twelve Hundred ninety years,</hi> and then <hi>Thirteen Hundred Thirty five</hi> the <hi>Epoch</hi> of the perfectly <hi>Bleſſed ſtate</hi> of that <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Christ:</hi> All which lay'd together, is perfect <hi>Scripture</hi> Demonſtration of the Complement of the <hi>Calendar,</hi> and of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> in its ſucceſſion ſo near to us, as 1697, and then riſing to perfect glory.</p>
               <p>And until that Time, there is to be a continual prayer for, and Expectation of ſuch preparatory motions in the World, as by which <hi>Beſtianiſm</hi> ſhall not onely, not be allowed to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurgitate on any of the reformed Nations, by any of their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>Giving</hi> anew <hi>their power to the Beast,</hi> that had Revers'd their power from Him, but that the reſt of the <hi>Ten Kings,</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> ſhall <hi>hate the Whore;</hi> And that within the Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſelf, that <hi>Synagogue, Prophecy,</hi> Brands, as the <hi>Synagogue</hi> of <hi>Sathan,</hi> that was always <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Friend to <hi>Primacy,</hi> and to caſting out of the Church on its unſcriptural Canons, ſhould be bending to <hi>worſhip</hi> at <hi>Philadelphiaes Feet,</hi> and thereby the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> become perfect, and Illuſtrious.</p>
               <p>Let us then take off our Hearts, and Eyes from all worldly Glory, whether <hi>Civil,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtic,</hi> which is now in its low <hi>Weſt,</hi> and adore the <hi>Glory of Christ</hi> in his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as the <hi>riſing Sun,</hi> now near its <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>Morning Dawn.</hi> As the <hi>Stars,</hi> let every one move, and even <hi>Fight in their Courſes,</hi> and <hi>help the Lord againſt the Mighty;</hi> Let us wait for <hi>Jeſus Chriſt from Heaven,</hi> who before <hi>Pontius Pilate witneſs'd</hi> that <hi>good Confeſſion of his Kingdom,</hi> which though it is not of this <hi>World,</hi> is yet of the approaching <hi>World to come, whereof we ſpeak;</hi> and though, it is not from hence, or from beneath, yet is the <hi>Jeruſalem coming down from Heaven;</hi> which he in his <hi>own proper Time,</hi> now at Hand <hi>will ſhew,</hi> who is <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> and <hi>King of Kings.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:43"/>
            <head>The <hi>Rationality</hi> of this <hi>Calendar</hi> in a <hi>Review,</hi> and in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with the <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> of the 2300 <hi>Evens. Morns.</hi> Or, a Table of Time, eſpecially of that part of it within the foregoing <hi>Calendar,</hi> and Explanatory of it ſo, that its Truth is Evinc'd, by i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Conformity to the Infinite Wiſdom, that hath <hi>made every Thing Beautiful in its Seaſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Great Reaſon of All Time, is the Allowance of ſpace to the World, for the variety of Action in it, under the Government of ſupreme Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; whereby things are Roll'd this way and that way, between the <hi>Kingdom of Sathan</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtaſie of Humane Nature,</hi> and the <hi>Reſtoration</hi> of it by the <hi>Seed of the Woman, Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> until his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low up the <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> and <hi>appear in Glory;</hi> which <hi>Appearance in Glory</hi> is determined by God, who hath <hi>Reſerved Times and Seaſons in his own Power,</hi> to Come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igh upon the ſeventh Millenary of Time, which is the Grand Sabbatiſm under the Son of Man, the <hi>Lord of it,</hi> who is alſo the Son of God.</p>
            <p>Time therefore, being ſeven Millenaries in the whole, as Incluſive of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> was for about the Firſt Half of it meaſur'd out by the <hi>Holy Line,</hi> of whom this <hi>Seed</hi> was to <hi>Come,</hi> according to the Great Revolutions, order'd by God with Relation to this <hi>Seed;</hi> As firſt by the <hi>Patriarchal Ages</hi> till <hi>Abraham;</hi> From <hi>Abraham</hi> to the <hi>Giving of Canan</hi> to his Seed; from the Giving of <hi>Canan</hi> to the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of David,</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Great <hi>Type</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> But becauſe This <hi>Kingdom</hi> fell from the very Glory of the <hi>Type</hi> by the <hi>Rending Ten Tribes</hi> from the <hi>Houſe of David</hi> at the Death of <hi>Solomon;</hi> and that within 390 years after, Both <hi>Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> were in Captivity; Time is drawn from <hi>Solomons</hi> Death to the Great <hi>Viſion</hi> of the <hi>Reſtoration</hi> of <hi>All Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Ezekiels Temple,</hi> and <hi>City,</hi> and by <hi>Forty</hi> Additional years to the <hi>Reſtoring</hi> the Houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> particularly, out of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity by <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other Half of Time, beginning ſoon after <hi>Ezekiels Viſion</hi> till the <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> is call'd by our Lord, <hi>The Times of the Gentiles.</hi> 1. Becauſe the <hi>Jews,</hi> the then People of God, from that Time would be, till <hi>Ezekiels Viſion</hi> came into Effect under <hi>Gentile</hi> Servitude. 2. Becauſe the <hi>Church of God</hi> would, after the Death of <hi>Meſſiah</hi> by <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Hands, be to Remove from the <hi>Jews</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and ſo the <hi>Gentile Monarchies</hi> having the <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Chriſtianiz'd, under them, would be Fit Repreſentatives of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchy of Chriſt</hi> over all Mankind; and yet till the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be perfectly reſtored according to that <hi>Viſion of Ezekiel,</hi> The <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt cannot Come,</hi> which ſhews the Superiority of the <hi>Jews</hi> in that <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> ſhadowed therefore by their <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Temple,</hi> and called for their ſakes, <hi>The New Jeruſalem;</hi> This Honour they have, becauſe Chriſt, <hi>God over All</hi> in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>Bleſſed</hi> for <hi>Ever, Came of Them.</hi> 3. Becauſe however the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> was to be planted among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as <hi>Engrafted</hi> among the <hi>believing Jews,</hi> Yet ſo Great an <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> was to Riſe in the <hi>Gentile Church,</hi> as uniting with the <hi>Pagan Gentiliſm,</hi> would <hi>Ecclipſe</hi> and ſtay off the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Kingdom</hi> from <hi>appearing</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoſe <hi>Gentile Times,</hi> and ſo till the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the Coming of the Glory of the Church out of its <hi>Ecclipſe</hi> among the <hi>Gentiles, Ezekiels Viſion</hi> cannot become Effect,
<pb facs="tcp:106747:44"/> nor <hi>All Iſrael ſav'd,</hi> Rom. 11. and thus the whole <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> are Times wholly oppoſite to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> in its <hi>Glory,</hi> except about an 120 years of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire,</hi> which God ſupremely interpos'd, and the laſt <hi>Half Time</hi> or 180 years ſince the <hi>Reformation</hi> in part reconcil'd to it.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Gentiles-Times</hi> are double <hi>Calendar'd,</hi> becauſe of ſo Great Account.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By a <hi>Calendar</hi> of <hi>Four Great Monarchies,</hi> Each latter in Succeſſion to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going<note place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Monarchy.</hi> The laſt of which remains, till the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> ſhall break that, and all others with it. To ſo Great a <hi>Monarchy of Chriſt,</hi> Theſe <hi>Monarchies</hi> laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing until it, are an agreeable <hi>Calendar.</hi> And becauſe the laſt State of the laſt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> would be very long, and of Great Conſideration, There is a <hi>Numeral</hi> but <hi>Myſtic Calendar,</hi> of <hi>Time, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half a Time</hi> given to that Alone.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This <hi>Monarchic Calendar</hi> is arm'd with a Full <hi>Numeral Calendar,</hi> beginning at<note place="margin">Dan. 8.</note> the end of the laſt <hi>Joynt</hi> of the whole Scripture <hi>Line</hi> before it. <hi>viz.</hi> at the end of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> laſt 40 <hi>Days</hi> for <hi>Years,</hi> and in the beginning of the ſecond of theſe Four <hi>Monarchies. viz.</hi> The <hi>Perſian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Monarchic</hi> and the <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> admirably ſerve One Another; For ſo Great <hi>Pyramids</hi> of Time, as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Monarchies</hi> and their Changes, cannot but be generally known and obſerved; and the <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> keeps theſe <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies</hi> to their own Bounds; and particularly joyning with the <hi>Numeral Myſtic Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar</hi> of the laſt part of the <hi>Fourth Monarchy</hi> binds it to its own Time, and alſo adjuſts the Kingdom of Chriſt after 75 years of preparation to its own <hi>Sabbatic Milenary</hi> by the note of 2300 <hi>Even. Morn.</hi> as <hi>Six Evens. Morns<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> led to the <hi>Firſt Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Calendar</hi> of <hi>Monarchies</hi> was duly given, when the <hi>Ten Tribes, Jeruſalem,</hi> as <hi>Sodom of Old,</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> alſo lay in Ruins under <hi>Litteral Babylon,</hi> that <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Myſtical Babylon</hi> bearing the names of all theſe, <hi>Spiritual Sodom, Egypt</hi> and of the <hi>City</hi> where <hi>Our Lord was Crucified,</hi> what was Irrecoverable in Them All, might fall into its <hi>Everlaſting Burnings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Calendar</hi> of the 2300 <hi>Even. Morn.</hi> is given moſt opportunely, preciſely, and exactly to adjuſt the <hi>Scripture Line of Time</hi> to the great <hi>Sabbatiſm,</hi> and ſo could neither be more nor fewer then the 2300 <hi>Even. Morn.</hi> to be propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally Multiplyed into Years.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> every part of Time is kept, not onely to its <hi>own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Time</hi> in regard of <hi>Time:</hi> but the <hi>Beauty</hi> of every part is ſeen in its own <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> by the diſtribution of this great <hi>Calendar</hi> into ſeveral leſſer parts of the whole. Wherein though it be the <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles Times,</hi> yet there is particular reſpect to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God</hi> under the <hi>Gentiles Times;</hi> as to the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> till it was Renunciated by Chriſt; and ſo to the <hi>Gentile Church</hi> after, under the Apoſtaſie or <hi>Gentiliz'd Christianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> is united to <hi>Ezekiels viſion</hi> of the <hi>City,</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> by<note place="margin">Dan. 8. v. 14.</note> the note of the <hi>Sanctuary Cleans'd:</hi> It is united to the <hi>Monarchic Calendar</hi> by the <hi>Prince, viz.</hi> The <hi>Antichriſtian Prince,</hi> or <hi>Little Horn broken without Hand,</hi> the laſt of the <hi>Princes</hi> in the <hi>Monarchic Calendar.</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>If we then take the firſt 75 <hi>years</hi> of the 2300, and account them by the <hi>Word going forth</hi> by the Three <hi>Perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Kings, Cyrus, Darius,</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> for the <hi>Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> we are ſo far aſſur'd by <hi>Scripture</hi> according to the <hi>Monarchic,</hi> and <hi>Numeral Calendar,</hi> that ſo many years may be allowed: and then parallel to theſe 75, the laſt 75 years at the end of the 2300. <hi>viz.</hi> from the laſt 1260 to 1335. in preparation for the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> and the parallel is very beautiful of <hi>Litteral Babylon</hi> Falling, and the <hi>Litteral Jeruſalem Riſing</hi> at the beginning of the 2300. Even<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Morn: and <hi>Myſtical Babylon Falling,</hi> and the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> Riſing at the End of the 2300 E. M. And 75 years at the Beginning, and at the End 75 years for the <hi>Reſtoring each Jeruſalem</hi> Anſwer One Another in number, and as a Time of preparation, one for the <hi>Litteral,</hi> the other for the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:44"/>
            <p> The <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that then was being thus <hi>Reſtored,</hi> It was preſerv'd 70 <hi>Weeks</hi> of Years, or the 490 years immediately following the firſt 75, though in <hi>Straits,</hi> or <hi>Troublous Times,</hi> that in that as in the <hi>Holy City,</hi> the <hi>Type</hi> of the <hi>New Jeruſalem, Meſſiah</hi> might Found his <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and <hi>Evangelical Kingdom,</hi> and the Right to his Glorious <hi>Kingdom,</hi> becauſe to it the <hi>Kingdom</hi> was firſt to <hi>Come:</hi> And hereunto agree the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchic,</hi> and <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> that 490 years might be thus diſpos'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been preſerv'd ſo long under the <hi>Perſian, Graecian,</hi> and ſucceeding <hi>Roman Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy</hi> Ruling over Them.</p>
            <p>At the <hi>Death, Reſurrection</hi> and <hi>Aſcenſion of Chriſt, Meſſiah</hi> had a Right to a <hi>Glorious Kingdom;</hi> But in Reſignation to the <hi>Divine Will,</hi> that had ſo determin'd; He ſeal'd or ſtay'd <hi>Propheſie</hi> from coming into the Effect of his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which <hi>Kingdom</hi> might well be called <hi>Viſion,</hi> or <hi>Propheſie,</hi> becauſe It is the <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of <hi>All Things,</hi> and the <hi>Myſtery of God ſpoken of by all the Prophets;</hi> and ſo Chriſt bids <hi>Daniel ſeal</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.</note> 
               <hi>the Book,</hi> and accordingly he Receives it from God <hi>Seal'd with ſeven Seals,</hi> and<note place="margin">Revel. 5.</note> Chriſt <hi>open'd</hi> in due order thoſe <hi>Seales,</hi> tho' it had been no <hi>Robbery</hi> to have taken the <hi>Kingdom</hi> immediately; Throughout the <hi>Four</hi> firſt <hi>Seals</hi> there was the <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions</hi> of his <hi>Saints</hi> thro' <hi>his Blood</hi> for <hi>his Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>word of his Teſtimony</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 6.</note> vehemently urg'd, <hi>Come</hi> and <hi>ſee,</hi> and all along there ran a Courſe of <hi>Martyrdoms,</hi> which was compleated at the <hi>Fifth Seal</hi> in the greateſt and laſt <hi>Perſecution</hi> under <hi>Diocleſian;</hi> So at the <hi>Sixth Seal</hi> the <hi>Ancient Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Sathan</hi> the <hi>Dragon,</hi> and <hi>Old Serpent, Fell</hi> as <hi>from Heaven</hi> in the <hi>Deſolation</hi> of <hi>Heatheniſm</hi> thro' the <hi>Roman Empire;</hi> that is, It fell in a <hi>Prophetical Symbol,</hi> of what ſhall be fully done hereafter, rather then <hi>Hiſtorical</hi> of what was then done; And in the ſame <hi>Prophetical ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſm</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 12. 10.</note> in the <hi>Seventh</hi> or <hi>Sabbatical Seal;</hi> The <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> call'd the <hi>Kingdom of our God,</hi> made an appearance.</p>
            <p>And theſe <hi>Seven ſeals</hi> muſt be within four hundred years after the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> in which, what Time the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> had, was cut off from the <hi>wounded ſixth Beſtian Head,</hi> or <hi>Pagan Emperour.</hi> For the 2300 <hi>Even. Morn.</hi> allow ſo much Time, and no more; and the <hi>Monarchic Calendar</hi> requires it to be before the <hi>Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> was divided into 10 <hi>Kingdoms;</hi> So the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> muſt begin 280 years after the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> where it had Right to enter as a <hi>Symbol</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Kingdom</hi> as made <hi>Perfect</hi> by <hi>Sufferings</hi> and his Saints <hi>overcomming by his Blood,</hi> by the <hi>word of his Teſtimony,</hi> and by not <hi>loving their Lives unto Death.</hi> And this <hi>Kingdom</hi> then laſted 120 years, before the <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> had <hi>Eclips'd</hi> it, and ſeeing there was ſo much cut off from the <hi>Pagan Empire,</hi> if the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> had not <hi>held</hi> that Time, <hi>Antichriſt</hi> had been <hi>Reveal'd</hi> before his <hi>own Time,</hi> and thus <hi>Hiſtory</hi> agrees. Now<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Theſ. 2. 6</note> this appearance of the <hi>Kingdom of Christ</hi> in the midſt of a <hi>Beſtian Image of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies</hi> and of the laſt <hi>Beſtian Monarchy</hi> was Immediately interpos'd by God, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever againſt Nature.</p>
            <p>Immediately hereupon even while Thirty eight years of the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> remain'd in a ſupremacy over <hi>Rome</hi> tho' much fallen from Glory, the <hi>Apostaſie</hi> that was to bring forth the <hi>Revelation of the man</hi> of ſin, or his ſucceſſion at the end of thoſe 38 <hi>years</hi> enter'd in the <hi>Gentiles Months,</hi> and began the 1260 years; It enter'd thus ſoon, that the <hi>wounded Beast</hi> might be <hi>Heal'd</hi> and <hi>not dye,</hi> and becauſe the <hi>Christian Empire</hi> ſo unnatural according to <hi>Prophecy</hi> to the <hi>Bestian Monarchic Image</hi> ought to continue but a <hi>ſhort ſpace,</hi> and becauſe there remain'd onely 1260 years of the <hi>Numeral Calendar</hi> beſides the 75 years of Preparation after them for the <hi>Kingdom of Christ;</hi> and becauſe here the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> (to be united to the <hi>Beast,</hi> were to <hi>Receive Power</hi> at the Ceſſation of the <hi>Christian Emperour,</hi> as at <hi>one Hour with the Beast)</hi> enter'd as <hi>Gentiles,</hi> tho' not as <hi>Kings</hi> till that Ceſſation: And here the Apoſtaſie muſt needs enter, becauſe it was to enter by way of undermine and <hi>Eclipſe</hi> upon the <hi>Kingdom of Christ,</hi> which it could onely do, while this <hi>Christian Empire</hi> remain'd a <hi>Symbol</hi> of it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106747:45"/>
            <p> And here let us behold with Humble Admiration, and Aſtoniſhment the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of Chriſt to the divine will; For with Readineſs he <hi>Seal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> up the Glory of his 144000, and ſo of his own <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Swears;</hi> It ſhould be ſo for <hi>Times, Times,</hi> and <hi>Half,</hi> while the daily <hi>Sacrifice</hi> or pure <hi>Worſhip of his Goſpel,</hi> ſhould be <hi>taken away;</hi> But then he <hi>ſwears;</hi> There ſhould be no more ſuch Time of <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> but all along to the <hi>1290th</hi> year from thence, and by the 1335 year from thence, <hi>viz.</hi> in the firſt 75 years of the <hi>ſeventh Trumpet,</hi> the Myſtery of his Kingdom <hi>ſhould be Finiſh'd,</hi> and it ſhould <hi>Appear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here behold again the <hi>Beauty</hi> of Providence in this <hi>Seaſon;</hi> For there was a <hi>Dilemma</hi> upon this Time; If <hi>Beaſtian,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt appearing</hi> in the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Empire,</hi> muſt be revers'd; whereas as in a <hi>Symbol,</hi> It ſhould never be revers'd, the <hi>manly Birth</hi> was <hi>caught up to the Throne of God:</hi> If not <hi>Beaſtian,</hi> how would the <hi>Monarchic Calendar</hi> be ſecur'd? For the <hi>Beaſtian Image</hi> ſtands, till the Glory of Chriſts <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which we are ſure is not yet; or how the <hi>Numeral Calendar,</hi> whoſe 2300 Even. Norn. would want 1260 years? Loe then the Divineneſs of the <hi>Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation;</hi> The very <hi>Ecclipſe</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> is a Confeſſion of the Sun. Elſe there could be no Moon in Brightneſs Ecclipſing it; If no <hi>Chriſt,</hi> no <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> no ſuch <hi>Vicar:</hi> Oh ominous Name, <hi>Vicar of Chriſt,</hi> what is the <hi>Greek Original</hi> for <hi>Vicar of Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>Antichrist;</hi> His High Pretenſions anſwered by the Ten <hi>Kings Giving their Power</hi> to Him, is a Confeſſion of Chriſt, and of his Supreme <hi>Monarchy.</hi> This therefore and no other <hi>Beastiaeniſm</hi> could now Be, or Laſt till the <hi>Kingdom of Christ.</hi> But on the other ſide, <hi>Antichristianiſm</hi> is <hi>Beastianiſm;</hi> The <hi>Ecclipſe,</hi> and Undermine are <hi>Beaſtian;</hi> Chriſt therefore ſubmits to the Ecclipſe of his <hi>Kingdom</hi> for 1260 years, becauſe It was to laſt ſo long according to both theſe <hi>Prophetical Calendars,</hi> as in the <hi>Little Horn</hi> or <hi>Antichrist;</hi> and then He allows to the <hi>finiſhing of the Mystery</hi> 75 years after, that his <hi>Kingdom</hi> might Come in its <hi>own Time,</hi> as on the <hi>Evening</hi> of the <hi>Sabbatical Millenary, appointed</hi> for it by the <hi>Father;</hi> And then the <hi>Ecclipſing Moon vaniſhes</hi> by that B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>neſs of Chriſts <hi>Coming,</hi> call'd therefore ſo often <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and becomes a <hi>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndring Star,</hi> for which is <hi>reſerv'd the blackneſs of Darkneſs for ever.</hi> Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3. 17.</note> every one fear to <hi>Fall</hi> from our own <hi>Fixation</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel Firmament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now whoever <hi>Lays all</hi> theſe Things together, and ſhall conſider the Reaſon of them, and them, and when the <hi>Ten Kings</hi> entred the <hi>Roman Empire,</hi> and how long ago the <hi>Chriſtian Empire</hi> was; how near on All Accounts the <hi>End</hi> of the 1260 <hi>Days,</hi> muſt be; will conclude; They cannot end later then 1697; we might rather think They might have ended ſooner, then now, even ſome years ago, had not Event and this Numeral Calendar guided us; but later then 1697. They cannot end.</p>
            <p>And what we may expect till then, we cannot ſo poſitively determine; But as the <hi>ſeven T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nces Seal'd</hi> gaug'd to each <hi>Church</hi> the meaſure of its State in the Beginning of the <hi>Reformation:</hi> So I obſerve in theſe Three Nations of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, (Ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>land,</hi> the Bulk o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whoſe <hi>Natives</hi> were always <hi>Rebels</hi> to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion)</hi> the very State each was in, as to the <hi>Reformation</hi> then, caſts anew a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable Glance of it ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this Day: There is now therefore to be expected <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Turn in each, as it were <hi>Heliotropically</hi> toward the <hi>Philadelphian</hi> 97. according to the diſtance of Time to it; wherein the <hi>Church Cloath'd with the Sun,</hi> ſhall come out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Eclipſe;</hi> which being ſo near, ſhould both Animate, and ſteer all our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and accordingly the <hi>God of Heaven</hi> (however differing parties may deſign) will <hi>Inſpire</hi> Them: To write all the Correſpondencies of <hi>Scripture</hi> and its <hi>Propheſies</hi> to theſe Great Ends, The <hi>World</hi> would hardly <hi>contain</hi> the Books: What Conſideration then does This Thing deſerve; Or how can we neglect it! Except we can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw <hi>Divine Oracles,</hi> or diſprove what I have written as Founded on them, which, I am well aſſured, cannot be done.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
